[Music]
greetings Explorer day nine is upon us
and it's time you stopped ignoring me or
at least stopped ignoring our battery
levels getting a percentage is fine but
ultimately reading that percentage is on
you and you're not always looking you
will have to look after to yourself in
the future I'm not going to be around
forever I have an update scheduled at
5:00 let's set up an RGB Leed rag status
light wow I think that's the most tlas
I've said in a sentence you know what
led stands for RGB stands for red green
blue and when you combine these three
colors in different intensities you get
all the colors of the rainbow rag is
another TLA or three-letter acronym and
that's stands for red Amber green
otherwise known as a traffic light
system now there are a lot of decisions
to be made on this Mission Explorer
fortunately we don't have to make any of
them we'll bring these new ways to
compare things and we'll use a new
command else if to catch any crazy stuff
in the code else if is another
conditional operator right then since
we're not adding any new hardware today
we'll dive straight into the code pool
our mission to create a colorcoded b
battery status indicator using our
trusty
rgbled imagine this Explorer a bold
green shine to signify a robust battery
level a shifting Amber for when power
starts to WAN and an urgent red
pulsating from our little RGB LED as a
warning when the battery drops too low
my mind's eye could wander forever let's
make it happen remember when we use the
photo resistor to regulate our charging
speed now we're taking it up a notch
every Loop cycle will work out the
battery percentage then we'll test that
percentage if it's within a certain Zone
we'll make the light a certain color the
second step is to use conditional logic
to give our ship a colorcoded mood ring
let's see green brimming with power 50
to 100% And raring to go Amber keep an
eye on it as we're between 25% and 50%
red danger zone we're below 25% and need
to seriously consider charging up you're
smart Explorer our RGB LED only has red
green and blue colors where's the yellow
well we can get yellow by mixing a
little green with a little red a true
Artisan of code you are Explorer now
let's get this show on the road in order
to make our color-coded power level
dreams a reality it looks like we're
going to need a few more Tools in our
coding toolkit it's time to get to know
some of the more sophisticated
comparison operators allow me to
introduce you to our new friends greater
than or equal to greater than less than
or equal to and less than ah and let's
not forget about their Pals The Logical
operators and and or these operators
allow us to make more complex decisions
in our code to start the greater than
and less than signs are likely familiar
to you these symbols are used to compare
two values for example five is greater
than three returns true because five is
indeed greater than three the less than
or equal to and greater than or equal to
operators extend this comparison how
about this is five greater than five we
might need a condition where a value is
both greater than and equal to another
and that's why these chicken Footprints
are very useful I knew you'd catch on
fast now on to The Logical operators and
is a binary operator that requires two
conditions to be true for the overall
expression to be true Stay With Me Now
Explorer let's break it down imagine
this you're planning to leave your cozy
spacecraft to explore the boundless
wonder that is space extra vehicular
activity or Eva as we like to call it
you would only go if both your suit was
functional and the exterior conditions
were safe clearly only when both of
these conditions are met would you step
out of the
spacecraft or is slightly different in
this case if either condition is true
then the overall expression is true
picture this you eat if you are hungry
or you eat if it is meal time if either
condition is true it's Chow Time greater
than or equal to and or decisions
decisions decisions it can be a lot to
think about that's why we code explore
so machines can make the tedious
decisions for us at this time you may
indulge in the highly beneficial
instructional material that I have
gathered cached on the computer as you
know I've also added this to your
mission resources for future reference
good
luck hello everybody and welcome back to
day nine of the code explanations for
the 30 days lost and space adventure kit
yesterday we were able to learn how to
use the RGB LED properly in showing off
pulse modulation and all those other
good things and now we're going to be
using that same RGB LED and integrating
it with our battery percentage circuit
that we had it from before so that
instead of displaying it on a Serial
Monitor and knowing when everything's
going to be completed based on a Serial
monitor we can also have a the RGB
indicator show us those exact same
things based on the state of our battery
so I'm sure you can probably take a
guess as to how we're going to
accomplish this we're basically going to
have it so that if it is between a
certain percentage maybe greater than
50% then we're going to display it as
green if it's going to be less than
25% or greater than 25% and less than
50% maybe switch it to a yellow Amber
and if it's less than 25% we should
probably start saying hey it's red and
maybe give a little pulsating signal
just to let everybody know hey the
batter is getting a little bit low as of
right now so to accomplish this we're
going to be taking a lot of the things
we've learned over the last couple days
to make it happen first let's just
quickly remove all a couple of these the
only reason I'm removing this is because
I can show that the program will work
just fine without it but you can keep it
in of course if you want to next we have
the following we have the Arduino
Concepts that we're going to be
introducing in this lesson and I really
quick want to go over a a couple of
these now let's talk about the new
Concepts that we're going to be
introducing in this lesson I'm sure you
know how integers and bytes and all
those other data types that we've
learned so far work they are just a
number but they're not just a number
they're a number that ends with nothing
it's an you know like six or 48 or 12 or
whatever but it's not 68.3 4 or 60
2.15 no it's uh it's just just 68 or
whatever there's nothing else to it a
float is a new type of data type that
allows us to have those extra decimal
points a good example of when you'd want
to use this might be something like when
you're calculating money or in this case
we're going to be using it to calculate
a percentage that percentage is going to
be what we're going to be displaying for
what our battery percentag is now
another concept we're going to be
introducing along with the float data
type is we're going to be introducing
the else if control structure I'm sure
you know what if statements are and I'm
sure you know what else statements are
but what is an else if statement an else
if is a control structure for making
multiple decisions especially in more
complex scenarios in this case an else
if is only going to run if the following
condition is true and the if statement
above it did not have to execute so if
the above was false and the below is
true then it will execute the else if
statement if you just have else it's
going to execute no matter what as long
as the above statement the first if
statement was false this adds another
additional complexity to it so you have
to make sure that the next statement is
true and we'll get into that in just a
moment because it's it's a little bit
confusing as I explain it here I'm sure
you've seen this a hundred times before
this is the exact same as yesterday
Define our pinouts for the RGB and the
photo resistor and then set the uh
variable for the simulation of our
battery capacity we can skip over that
we've already talked about that in
yesterday's lesson then we have the
following function oh look at this we
did the exact same thing as yesterday
and I'm going to real quick just so I
can get all on one line and show you
guys how I personally prer to set it up
just so you guys can know that this is
also a valid way to write
it and without that it won't change
anything functionality wise if you write
it like
this this is the same function we had
yesterday display color which will
simply write the RGB color to exactly
what we want it to be then we have the
following
setup we're going to have pin mode is
going to be for the rg&b pins or outputs
and we're also going to be this time
using a little bit of extra debugging
using the serial monitor this is so that
we can actually read the exact
percentage as it gets to those certain
points and you guys can see how when it
gets below 25% it'll start kind of
pulsating red for example but you'll see
that it gets to that V variable because
we'll be printing it to the serial
monitor on B rate 9600 please make sure
you select the correct B rate when you
open up the serial monitor
after
setup where do we jump to that's right
you guessed it we jump straight to Loop
now we're going to be seeing that we
have the new unsigned long battery level
is going to be set to zero for the very
first bit of the simulation we're going
to pretend that we don't have any charge
obviously we went through a lot of this
in day seven but you'll notice we added
a little static thing here and that
makes it so that no matter what every
time it goes through Loop it's going to
maintain the value that it had from
before by using this static here if we
didn't have static every time we got to
the beginning of the function it would
just reset itself back to zero since
we're not using this as a global
variable since this is now a local
variable and located specifically inside
of Loop and not if I were to cut this
and paste it up here we can have very
similar functionality simply by putting
static here obviously we learned what
plus equals does back in day s this is
essentially the equivalent of saying
battery level is equal to battery level
plus whatever the reads off the analog
pin and we have to make sure that we
don't go over the maximum value of
50,000 so we just check that here if it
is over and we're going to reset it back
down to
50,000 a lot of this is repeated from
Days eight or seven and eight so I'm
just going to briefly go over quite a
bit of it now here's where we get to the
new stuff we have a float percentage
which means we're it's going to be a
decimal variable is going to be equal to
the battery level divided by the battery
capacity time 100 however you'll notice
I also included this little bit here
which is passing it in as a float and a
float and the reason we want to do this
is because we want our output to be a
float now when we compute the arithmetic
for this
we're taking a nonflat value in this
case the battery level is a long and the
battery
capacity up here is also a long so when
we're converting between Longs and
floats which are different types of data
types we want to make sure that when we
pass it in we're passing it in as a
float and the reason why is because we
want it to essentially be the the number
it has here and then we want to add in
the additional 0 Z and0 0 to the end of
these so that when it converts it and
it's done calculating this here and sets
it to here we have the exact number as a
percentage and we don't have something
that ends in a z0 otherwise that kind of
ruins the point of a float bottom line
is you can read this whole comment here
but arithmetic gets really confusing if
you're converting between data types
like this so for consistencies sake
we're going to make sure that all the
things on this side that should be a
type of float are going to be
if as typee float next we're going to
hop to the section down below which
actually is most of our Logic for this
entire day everything here is simply if
it's greater than 50 it's going to be
green if it's between 25 and 50 it's
going to be yellow Amber and if it's
less than 25% we want it to have a small
pulsating effect of red then we're going
to Simply print that percentage of what
it is to the monitor after every time
going to here in theop Loop and we're
going to give it a tiny tiny little
delay just so it doesn't scroll too fast
now let's start off by doing exactly and
showing off exactly how this works if
the battery percentage is greater than
or equal to 50 then we want to display
it green and that's exactly what we do
red off green on Blue off however
there's a chance the battery isn't going
to be
green but we don't want to use an lse
statement here if we use an L statement
for the next one it would automatically
be run no matter what you could have a a
bit of code where it's else and then in
the brackets you have another if
statement and then another and then an
El statement but to simplify this we can
actually have multiple logic statements
combined together by having if else if
another set of else if another set of
else if and then finally an else if we
wanted to have another else and we can
combine all of that to simplify our code
a lot so this else if is a new statement
that allows us to run only if it's not
supposed to be green it's going to run
this code here but what this allows us
to do is it allows us to have another
logic under here in case let's just say
let's just say theoretically we don't
want to run this because let's just say
that it is supposed to be red if it's
supposed to be red then this would be
false and it would run to here but we
don't want to run this so we have an
else if statement that will only run if
this is true but if this isn't true then
we want to jump to the statement here so
if the battery percentage is greater
than 50 we'll make it green else if it's
going to be between 25 and 50 then we
want to have it as a little yellow
warning and then finally
else we're going to have when it's less
than 25% we're going to have a pulsating
effect that we'd use by simply adding in
a turning off the LED and then delaying
by a very very brief 20 millisecond
seconds which again is even less than
1/10th of a second it's actually closer
to so this is 2/10 of oneth of a second
so it's very very brief but by doing so
and turning off and then displaying the
red red on green blue off it allows us
to have a little tiny pulsating effect
to add a slight bit of extra intensity
to that warning your batter is running
very low finally of course like I
mentioned before we just we print these
percentages out and give a little delay
then hop back to the beginning of Loop
and execute the same thing once again
over and over and over again until the
end of
time once you have all this wired up you
can go ahead and try hitting upload and
see it working for yourself and now with
that that is now the end of day nine um
and I look forward to seeing you guys
again
tomorrow welcome to the day n wiring
example video today we'll be building on
what we've learned in Days Seven and 8
and use both the photo resistor and the
three-color LED to build a visual
indicator that displays the state of
charge of our battery system now looking
at our breadboard we see that once again
we have two subcircuits built on the
left we have the photo resistor circuit
to give us an analog light intensity
measurement and as before it's supplied
with plus 5 volts from the hero via this
red
wire and the circuit which is completed
through the photo resistor and the
series resistor completes back to ground
and this case it's by way of a ground
bus that we've set up along the blue
line on the top side of our breadboard
and the reason for doing that is it will
also use this same ground bus to provide
ground for our other circuit as well now
as we've done before in order to get the
analog signal that we need of light
intensity measurement we have a jumper
wire that connects from the positive
side of our series resistor to pin a z
the analog input pin on the hero and so
that is what will provide our intensity
signal okay shifting our attention over
to the right side of the breadboard we
have the circuit here that drives the
three channels of the RGB LED pretty
much just exactly as we did in day eight
the only minor difference here is in the
ground connection which as before rather
than the ground connection going
directly to the ground pin on the hero
uh controller board instead we uh
connect to ground on the Common Ground
bus that we've provided here along the
top of our
breadboard now if we go ahead at this
point and load the software sketch we
can watch how the LED colors will change
as we watch the charge level rising on
the serial monitor console and what
we'll expect to see is the following
sequence first if the battery starts off
at 0% charge the LED will be then in its
pulsating red warning mode so we should
see a pulsating red light then as we
watch the charge rise as it reaches
25% the sketch will cause the LED to
switch to Yellow for caution mode then
finally as the charge continues to rise
when it gets above 50% the LED switches
over to Green for safe mode and then
it'll remain that way all the way up to
100% charge so at this point we're ready
to go ahead and and try it let's cover
up the photo resistor to start so that
it begins in the dark and once the
sketch is loaded we can go ahead and
expose it to light and watch the
charging process uh take place so going
over to the
IDE let's go ahead and upload the
sketch sketch is now
uploading and we're going we can now see
that we're at 0% charge and we're in the
uh red mode of the LED so I remove the
black cloth I can see that uh the charge
level's Rising we're now up to about
8% 9% 10% and so on once we reach 25% we
should see a change in the LED and so
that should be coming up just about now
and there we go we've switched over to
Yellow mode and we'll be in this yellow
mode here until the charge level reaches
we could pause this if we wanted by
covering up the uh photo resistor but if
I keep it going and we reach
50% there we have switched over to green
and so we can let this go and continue
to rise and in a few more seconds we
should reach 100% and we'll see the
numbers um stop Rising on the on the
serial
monitor so it looks as though our uh
project here is is working as
anticipated and we've made yet another
bit of progress towards uh being able to
use the hero to uh restore our systems
to function so that pretty much covers
the features and functions of today's
project congratulations on the success
you've had so far after another little
break another creative day we'll come
back and we'll dive into the next
challenge and learn how to start sending
keypad input to our hero so until then
have a good time
inventing looks like you've managed to
navigate your way through another week
of this chaotic Adventure you've got
your battery charging up and a shiny new
light indicator to show just how well
you're doing I must say not bad for a
rookie remember when you were struggling
with basic switches seems like ages ago
now you humans grow up so fast you've
come quite a long way fixing power and
oxygen lighting up your life and now
you've even got a handy colorcoded
battery life indicator great job but we
need to start ramping your progress up
this is a spaceship not a submarine our
mother ship's orbit is beginning to
degrade if we don't get our heads above
water soon we'll need to start thinking
long term and batteries don't last
[Music]
forever I've started naming some of
entities that revisit the ship that's
definitely Rachel she sounds
[Music]
hungry