[Music]
oh my that's definitely not good I'm
seeing a lot of red on this error log a
shame you can't just restore from a
backup like myself I'm sure even you
could guess your life is in a rather
precarious situation and there's no time
to waste so let's get started shall we
allow me to first introduce the
foundational material that is so crucial
to ensuring your longevity the
inventor. hero
microcontroller strange what they
considered micro back then in simplistic
terms that your biological brain can
compute it's like a tiny simplified
computer that we can program to do our
bidding and given our dire circumstances
is about to become your best friend well
second best
friend also Al included in your repair
kit is a programming computer it has
been modified to contain a complete
holographic copy of the old internet
thankfully while it does seem to be more
powerful than the herob board it does
not have the connectivity to control
your ship systems as such its ability is
limited to writing the code that the
hero board will
execute another vital component we're
going to use is an integrated
development environment or IDE for short
you will use this software to write a
small program or sketch and upload code
to the hero board we will dive into how
to achieve that a bit later but for now
please install the Arduino IDE software
onto your
computer it is my understanding that
this is a lot to digest and maybe
puzzling at times but please do not be
concerned as I am well-versed in the use
of such technology and am readily
prepared to guide you through each
essential step of the process our
mission today is to assess the condition
of the repair kit identify the operating
system of the programming computer and
start the process of getting the herob
board set up and integrated into your
craft systems if it's not already
abundantly clear time is ticking and the
state of your existence is on the line I
propose we get to
it all right Explorer it's time to roll
up your sleeves and prepare to tackle
the first task at hand to begin you'll
find a USB cable included in the kit
another quaint artifact from the 21st
century we can use this cable that we
are lucky enough to have to connect the
hero to the programming computer this
little wire will be the lifeblood of our
operation powering the hero and also
allowing us to transfer code to it one
end of that cable should fit into the
hero board and the other will fit into
your USB port on your programming
computer make that that connection first
need I remind you of rule number one of
your employee training manual when
you're in space or in this case water
always make sure you're Tethered to
something we'll work by creating smaller
circuits that will stimulate your ship
systems while we create the code for
each pair then we can plug the ship
systems into the hero as each program is
completed once you have the hero board
connected we're going to need to
communicate with it that's where the
Arduino IDE comes in
start by loading up one of the example
sketches included with the Arduino IDE
select the file menu examples 01 Basics
and finally blink this will open up the
blink sketch a pre-written piece of code
that will blink a light emitting diode
or LED for short on your herob board
this shows that the hero board is
working
correctly when you start a new sketch or
load an existing sketch you first need
to configure the proper board and
indicate which port Port is connected to
your board go to the tools menu then
select board and make sure our doino Uno
is selected since your hero board is
compatible with that model next you'll
need to select the correct Port again go
to the tools menu and this time select
Port you should see a few options select
the one that refers to the Arduino Uno
if you're unsure of which one to choose
just disconnect the board and see which
one disappears then reconnect and select
that
Port speaking of LEDs your heroboard has
a number of LEDs mounted on its surface
one of which we can control LEDs are
great for debugging purposes or in our
case to ensure everything is set up
correctly all right Explorer now that
we're all set up it's time to get into
gear and bring that led on the hero
board to life we're going to compile and
upload the
blink. sketch that you've already loaded
in the IDE you will see two round
buttons with arrows in in the top left
corner of the window the first one with
the check mark checks for any spelling
or formatting mistakes also known as
syntax errors and compiles if it passes
click on that button to compile your
sketch my Diagnostics show that your
code should be error free which means
you're ready to upload it to the hero
board great job Explorer the second
round button with the right arrow is for
uploading the code click that button and
the Arduino IDE will start uploading
your sketch to the hero board
if everything is in order as it should
be the IDE will display a message that
says done uploading and this our herob
board's LED is now blinking on and off
every second how spectacular if you've
followed all my instructions precisely
then you've just successfully completed
the first part of your repair Journey
you're one blink closer to seeing the
inside of your mother ship again now
that you've got the board successfully
connect and run some rudimentary code
let's briefly go over what just happened
in a bit more detail by taking a look at
the code all right Explorer we've
uploaded our blink. IO sketch and now
we're going to decode it much like how
you might decipher alien glyphs you'll
notice grayed out text that doesn't
appear to affect the sketch those are
comments they're like the sticky notes
you leave yourself to remember why you
decided to place a carbon dioxide
scrubber next to the coffee machine at
the top of the blink sketch is an
example of a multi-line comment that
begins with SL asterisk and ends with
asterisk slash even if those characters
are on another line anything between
slash asterisk and asterisk slash is
considered a comment and will be ignored
when compiling or building the sketch
you could pin your magnum opus between
these markers and the IDE would
blissfully disregard it single line
comments start with a double slash and
are used to add helpful notes or to
temporarily disable a part of the code
anything following double slash up to
the end of the same line is also ignored
by the compiler next we have setup and
loop the synergistic pair of Arduino
programming you may think of them as the
heart and lungs of your sketch each
equally essential with its own crucial
role to play the setup function sets up
the variable definitions and initial
tasks it's a function that's run once
and only once when your program first
starts this is where you put all your
preparations initializations pin mode
declarations and opening Communications
so many as for instance if we're using
an LED we need to tell the herob board
that we've connected an LED to a
particular pin and that it should be an
output pin this would go in the setup to
assist you in better understanding
please refer to this example now Loop is
where as you'd say the magic happens
after setup finishes the program jumps
to Loop and as you might guess this
function Loops over and over again for
as long as your board is powered
repeatedly
forever so if you want to Blink an LED
turning it on and off would happen
inside the loop like this that's the
basic purpose of the setup and loop
functions the former sets the stage and
the latter keeps the show running all
clear Explorer to explain the other
functions digital right is your digital
switch it can set a digital pin on your
herob board to a specific State either
low Zer volts or High 5 volts think of
it as an onoff switch the Syntax for the
digital WR function is straightforward
digital write parenthesis pin comma
value n parenthesis pin is the number of
the pin you want to control and value is
either high or low so if you want to
turn the LED connected to pin 12 on
you'd write digital right parenthesis 12
comma high end parenthesis to turn it
off you'd write digital right
parenthesis 12 comma low end
parenthesis you might notice that in
that example blink sketch it doesn't use
a number for the pin we'll discuss a bit
more about that tomorrow but for today
just know that when you configure a
board in the Arduino IDE there are some
names defined for you in this case
ledore builtin is defined in the Arduino
id13 which is the pin that the built-in
LED is controlled by next the delay
function does just what an observant
Explorer would expect it delays
execution before continuing on to the
next statement the delay is for a
specified period of milliseconds which
is 1,000th of a second if you want the
program to do nothing for a second you'd
write delay parenthesis 1,000 n
parenthesis semicolon since 1,000
milliseconds equals 1 second in the
context of blinking an LED digital right
is used to turn the LED on or off and
delay is used to control the length of
time the LED stays on or off together
they create the perfect blinking effect
aha starting to see the light are we
well at least half the time for your
benefit let's turn to some instructional
material that I was miraculously able to
gather cached on the computer I've also
added this to our mission resources for
future reference you're
welcome well well Explorer you've
managed to make a tiny light blink how
terribly impressive the interstellar
Community is no doubt holding its breath
in awe but please let's not forget the
Minor Detail that you are sitting in
abysmal Darkness 60 M under an alien sea
while your rapidly dwindling oxygen
supply bubbles away it's imperative that
we restore that battery charging system
in order to extend your oxygen supply
and buy us some time rest assured every
passing second I'm not working on saving
your life I'll be processing how we
might avoid a similar fate the next time
your curiosity gets the better of you no
pressure it's only your invaluable life
that is at stake so tuck yourself in
dear Explorer dream of blinking LEDs and
getting out of this mess you got
yourself in we'll need your brain fully
operational tomorrow if we're to start
getting your ship systems back under
control please do try not to attract any
attention as I've detected some rather
peculiar local sea life nearby sweet
[Music]
dreams