welcome to the fourth creative day only
two left to go and that's including
today by the way so you guys are getting
very close congratulations I'm making it
to the water's surface at this point the
only device you have not used yet is the
OLED display the amount of open-ended
projects you can make now are truly vast
however here are some good prompts for
you anyways just in case you wanted to
have some ideas of some stuff that you
can work on first of all you can make a
color mixer with the RGB LED so by using
the rotary encoder you can have a dial
to adjust the RGB values to create some
custom colors I also recommend adding in
the 4x4 keypad so you can actually
select maybe a B and C are r g and B red
green and blue respectively or however
you want to have it set up maybe you do
it that way um so you can select which
color you are adjusting and then adj
just just allow the value to go between
0 and 255 to set how much of that color
you want it to be and then display on
the RGB LED what that is another good
project idea is the digital alarm clock
with the seven segment display and the
buzzer so you can create a digital clock
using those two and then even add if you
want to go above and beyond a rotary
encoder to then set the time
then you can set an alarm to go off at
perhaps a certain time or a certain
moment that is up to you I'd love to see
what creative things you can come up
with with that one finally I don't know
if you remember on day 12 specifically
the day 12a inspiration for you guys you
guys can also look into making a jukebox
with the buzzer and maybe even the 4x4
keypad where each of the buttons maybe
press you press it and then it Cycles
through various songs on the jukebox now
be warned just in case uh of a little
bit too much memory usage perhaps once
you're done be sure to share on
inventor.
i/f with the hash creative day20 looking
forward to seeing what you guys can come
up with of course if you run into any
troubles just like always your fellow
inventors are always there at
inventor. thank you guys so much
[Music]