hello everybody and welcome to our first
creative Day first let's go over what a
creative day actually is learning coding
takes more than just reading and
memorizing syntax although let's be real
most of us still look up syntax from
time to time anyway I'm basically like a
professional googler when I really think
about it but yes to get good at coding
you also need to practice entirely on
your own it doesn't matter what you code
um but just that you have some sort of
and goal in mind and this is what I've
seen with people who are successful
programmers the ones who are successful
are the ones that have the desire to go
out and make something on their own it's
something that they're passionate about
to the point where they have the energy
and desire to go make something more or
make something of their own those are
the ones who are always the most
successful and by our goal for the
creative days is to help encourage
people people to want to go out and do
things like that on their own it's
really boring listening to lectures all
day but being able to actually put that
knowledge to use is where I always see
the Sparks Shine the brightest so every
creative day we'll have a couple of
sample prompts to get the neurons warmed
up but you're also free to do whatever
you want so you don't necessarily have
to do what the sample prompts are you
don't have to pick one of them you can
do whatever you want but we do give a
couple just in case you don't have
anything you really can think of that
you want to do so far you've
accomplished using inputs and outputs
with our dip switch and LEDs currently
your ship is capable of controlling
three different
LEDs so first creative Day idea the easy
creative Day idea as you know your
ship's battery is at critical levels
let's add some additional logic that
only allows one light at a time once
you're done share on inventor. o/f with
the hashtag creative day five now the
hard creative idea is currently you are
only capable of turning on three lights
you still have more lights in your ship
such as the bathroom light and
Etc however if you turn your dip switch
into a binary counter you can turn on up
to seven that would be binary 111 lights
or six if you want the ability to turn
them all off which would be utilizing
0000 0 once you're done share on
adventure.
i/f with the # creative day5 just like
the one before and finally there's the
open-ended option as you all know come
up with your own and once you're done
share on
adventure. with # creative day5 we
really look forward to seeing what you
come up with of course if you run into
any trouble feel free to ask on the
Facebook group again inventor.
i/f it should 301 redirect direct
directly to the Facebook group we have
currently over 100,000 of you guys
100,000 inventors who have joined and I
proud to say that for the most part
we're not like stack Overflow in the
sense that uh you guys are very awesome
and helping out a lot of the beginners
and uh I really appreciate all you guys
so thank you and I look forward to
seeing what you guys come up
with
[Music]