[Music]
he
good morning Explorer here we are on the
verge of the conclusion to an odyssey
that has tested our spirit resilience
and intellect today isn't just another
day it's the culmination of every
challenge we've overcome every Star
we've wished upon and every bit of hope
that propelled us forward our home
awaits us but before the sweet Embrace
of familiarity there's a final task to
be done the docking gear needs one last
touch that certain Junu sequa that
separates success from blunt force
trauma so as the Horizon of our Galactic
home draws near let's pour pour every
ounce of our knowledge and resolve into
this final effort it's time for our
grand finale Explorer I know you won't
disappoint me all right Explorer here's
where the intricacies of our Hardware
truly shine remember our scent from that
alien ocean floor upon lining our
trajectory with our assigned Docking Bay
we need to control our rate of approach
so we don't prang a landing gear or
Worse upon arrival we will be using our
rotary encoder to control our rate of
approach come into the Docking Bay to
rapidly and we crash and burn come into
the Docking Bay to slowly and we risk
missing the window of opportunity as our
mother ship's velocity will take our
Docking Bay off our trajectory as long
as we can keep our rate of approach just
right we can enter the bay and land our
ship in our docking cradle crashing is
not on the agenda today let's utilize
yesterday's code but integrate logic for
the rotary encoder to regulate our
altitude dive too rapidly and we plummet
tragically descend too leisurely and we
risk stalling in midair equally
catastrophic so Precision is the name of
the game let's ensure our touch down is
smooth as silk let's figure out how we
plan to code this thing using the same
code as yesterday we will need to add
the
following one a variable to track our
distance from Target airlock two a
countdown sequence once the docking gear
is deployed three a function to use the
rotary encoder to carefully approach our
Mothership adjusting as needed by
following the onscreen instructions rise
when it says increase lower when it says
decrease
Etc and four a success message to
display upon docking sounds easy enough
let's take a look at the cached code on
our computer for one last time on this
Grand Adventure
[Music]
Explorer hello and welcome back to the
final day of your 30 days L and space
code explanation today is day 29 and it
is a final day where you will be guiding
your ship back to the Mother Ship now
before we begin I'm going to quickly
make a note that we're going to need
quite a few different files for this one
we're going to need to copy over
directional arrows .h small landing gear
bit maps. and ending bit maps. make sure
that they're spelled the same as they
are here and if you do misspell it of
course you can always just change it
here if you accidentally misspell it
when creating if you want to make a new
file you can
go new tab and I'm going to call this
directional
arrow. and then I'm going to take the
file that I have from the course page
and make sure that I PID B exactly
what's needed for directional arrows I'm
going to do the same thing for small
landing gear bit Maps so let's create
small underscore Landing uncore bit or
get gear underscore bit
Maps
H and finally let's go for the very last
one
and ending bit maps. and we should have
all these again make sure you copy the
information that's needed on here from
the course page um before you continue
now today is going to be a really
complicated I mean given that it's the
last day the most complicated day of all
the code you've seen thus far it has
quite a bit of stuff going on to be
blunt a lot of the calculations are
going to be a little bit redundant for
me to be explaining in in voice so I
recommend you go through all the
beautifully written comments that I have
removed from this version of the video
version of sketch and just read what
those are saying about what exact those
calculations are doing most of them are
all for the graphics library in total we
have over 500 lines of code on this file
so and that's not even including
obviously those extra files so this here
is a very very large
sketch in total we have a about eight
directional arrows I think we have up
down left right and then the Four
Corners yes that would be eight eight
directional arrows and those would be uh
indexed 0 through
7 small landing gear bit Maps if you
remember from yesterday we had the
animation that showed us being able to
push down the uh landing gear and rise
up the landing gear we have something
very similar today but it's essentially
like a mini version in the bottom right
that'll tell us if our landing gear is
deployed or not and we're using a lot of
the same logic from yesterday just
putting it in a slightly different
location on the olded display but with
that let's now go through and let's go
and try our best to explain every little
bit of code that is going on here again
some of it I'll be going over just
briefly if it's a lot of the
calculations for showing where things
are going on screen but I'll show as
much as I can and give the higher level
Concepts as heavy as I can starting off
here obviously we're using the Arduino
IDE if I don't have this it'll work the
exact same if you're using a different
ID for your own choice you might want to
have that included is I don't know for
sure if it will automatically include
the uo. H Library we now have down here
the u8 G2 lib and wire. um which are
both required for i2c communications
these are just the standard libraries
we've been
including down here we're making our
Lander display for our OLED defining it
we've talked about that before we have
the three new includes for all of our
bit Maps the eight directional arrows
the four landing gear bit maps that
we're going to make the animation with
and then we have the ending bit Maps now
when you land into the Mother Ship you
will probably end in one of four
different states you'll either have uh
missed the Mother Ship because you were
not aiming correctly using the 4x4
keypad to aim your ship correctly B you
went too quickly
into the mother ship and you crashed
into it C you made it in correctly and
you had a successful landing and you
were able to get in correctly or D um
you were just way too slow and you took
way too long and missed it so there's I
think about four different endings that
you can have and out of those four
endings they have a little ending icon
graphic that just tells you if you were
successful or not the total size of
these bit Maps is is not 128x 64 it's
actually 128x 54 leaving 10 pixels at
the top to allow us to put in some text
that might say something like
congratulations you made it or sorry try
again or something like that above the
image we have obviously here's the four
landing gears we have 1 two 3 and four
this is all stuff we had saw yesterday
but this is just going to be in the
bottom right a very a little smaller
version of what we had the day before
um the bit maps are made to be a bit
smaller we also have the calculate how
many bit Maps we have divided by the
total again this is something we talked
about yesterday we have the gear State
exact same thing from yesterday's code
so I'm just going to glance over it but
it basically tells us if for lowering
raising or
idle down here we have all the includes
necessary for our s segment display down
here we have all the code we need for
the dip switch defining those pins here
we have everything we need for our
keypad and that includes these
enumerated Lander controls and these
Lander controls are the following we
basically we want to be able to do the
following with our Lander um instead of
just saying that we're going to call it
you know 1 2 3 4 5 6 7 8 9 a b c d we
want to give them some more useful names
inside of our code one is unused that's
if the button is unused and that's case
zero and then the rest of them are the
rest of our actual use cases we have
steer up down steer left steer right
steer up right steer up left steer down
right steer down left lower gear raise
gear raise velocity lower velocity and
if you want to look to see how that's
mapped so that in the top left rows 1
two and three if you take that 3x3 area
you could think of it as a circle where
the middle button is being unused and
the top left is going to be obviously
steering and then every direction around
it is directional this is where we're
aiming our ship this is where we're
steering in that direction we also have
on the very right side originally this
was like a b c and d we have lower gear
raise gear raise velocity and lower
velocity on the right side going down
and then obviously the very about bottom
row on the fourth row is just unused
unused unused
unused we obviously make the Lander
keypad here and then finally we have the
approach State we have the approach init
pre-flight inflight final to fast and
and docked docked is where we have
successfully docked inside of our ship
and so these are all the different
states that we could be during the
approach and I guess technically the
Finish because we have a final too fast
and docked the enumerator gives us nice
fun things to look at that are easier to
read than obviously just case like one
two 3 four five um which is a lot more
confusing than actually having something
nice and cool to read such as this after
our approach State down here we then
have the basic encoder file now one
thing I'll note is that if you might
have seen what ASD was doing we've
modified this version of the code a
little bit so instead of having the
velocity get raised and lowered with the
rotary encoder the version that you guys
might be seeing in the demonstration is
either going is probably going to be
using the 4x4 keypad to raise and lower
the velocity here the reason we did that
is because since only I believe two and
three are required for the DT and clock
input it doesn't match exactly but it
works just the same so you can follow
along with the diagram that we have on
screen and the code that is provided and
it should work just fine down here we
have in setup now before I go to setup I
do kind of want to talk a little bit
about the final amount of all these
functions we we have the following
functions that I don't really want to go
over just to be completely honest with
you update encoder is one that just
simply calls a velocity control. service
that's all that does finally we have a
draw string which is a which basically
calculates where we want to draw the
string and then puts that string on the
display in those X and Y coordinates
it's just a custom little made thing for
OLED we have the liftoff state two
string which basically just grabs the
approach state that it's
in and then simply says if it's an
initialization and it if it's in
pre-flight do
pre-light we have the display final and
then when the Lander is about to land
we'll display a Final Approach display
showing the landing gear
status all this does is it calculates it
says what index are we in our Final
Approach and if it is equal to zero we
want to say drop gear if it is lower
than it we want to say lowering it
otherwise we just want to say the gear
is okay so this is in case we want in
case we're getting in about 20% of the
way left so we've made it 8 80% of the
way to the ship we don't want to drop
the landing gear too early because then
obviously we won't be able to have as
good control in speed of our ship so we
want to wait until we're right next to
the landing or to the Mother Ship um
about 20% of the way there and then if
we don't then we want to have various
display messages that say hey we should
probably raise it until we get a little
bit closer or
Etc finally we want this just calculates
a bunch of X and Y offsets to show where
we want to display it on the screen
finally we have the following display
pre-flight and display inlight and I
want to go over these functions first
just because um they're used throughout
the code in pre-flight before we have
officially started the takeoff this is
where we haven't put the Thruster
confirmation and systems lever yet this
is still in the pre-flight state so this
is once we have to put all those three
into the right position and once we
do and this is something we talked about
last day we will enter the inflight
State the inflight state is basically
going to do the following it's going to
update our display to show the rectangle
area which is going to be the mother
ship that you're trying to get into the
circle in the middle which is where your
ship is and obviously which arrows are
showing telling you which direction you
should be moving into as well as it
calculates all these things the circle
the center of the circle uh which where
the arrow is pointing and it calculates
all of those based on if you know the
mothership offset is over here or the
mothership offset over here then we want
to put the arrow over here versus over
here a lot of math I'm not going to go
through all the numbers here but given
that we have 128x 64 these were pretty
hard hardcoded in there since we know
the size of our display so that's why
you see random magic numbers like 45
27 11 etc etc this will continually
update our display as we are flying
towards the mother ship in
Flight finally let's go to setup and
loop and let's actually take a look at
all this we did also set the initial
distance to a random number of 1394 we
thought we could set it to 1,000 which
would display on 7 segment display but
it seemed more realistic to just put a
random number that wasn't
one since it seemed more realistic to
put something else you can you can
change this to be whatever you want it
to be and the program will work just
fine because the way it calculates
distances and whatever is it takes this
and divides it by whatever to get 20%
close and Etc so all those logic
statements that we have below will work
just fine if we change this number here
that's why it's nice to have a global
variable so you don't have to change
things everywhere else Max Mothership
width and Max Mothership height have
been also defined
here finally we go to setup and we have
the following we have we generate a
random seed and that random seed is
going to determine where we're going to
be going so every time we start up this
program we want to have another a random
seed to determine every time we go
through the loop which is down below
we'll be calculating is a mother ship
going to go up one down one left one one
right one where is it going to be moving
on screen and the way we can tell where
it's going to end up moving is we have
this thing called random seed and that
is going to generate a random number for
us that's dint every single time we run
the program to determine where we're
going or where it will be going finally
we have the distance display we set up
the pin modes we set up the Lander
display initializations with the fonts
we set the velocity control begin uh
which is for encoder and we also have
the attach interrupt which is where
we're going to attach an interrupt
service routine to our encoder so that
anytime that something happens on the
encoder it will break from the program
execute the following update encoder
function and then it will jump back to
where it came from in the program after
that then we have serial.println ready
just to mention that we finished the end
of setup and then down here below we
have the following which is a final and
last bit of code for day 29 and all this
is doing is simply setting a bunch of
variables here at the top initial
initialized variables and these are
static which means that they are
remembered in the next version of the
loop so if this changes so right now
it's zero is it's marked here but let's
just say after a couple times going
through Loop this is now a a three for
example it's going to remember that next
time the time after goes to Loop and
it's going to be three instead of
initially set to zero every single time
to the loop so the static is going to
keep it so it remembers what it was last
time it was in the loop and that's for
all of these we have Boolean thrust
confirm systems lever and all this does
is it just simply says is true or false
is this turned on or is this not on then
we simply calculate what state we're
supposed to be in are we supposed to be
in the depending on what state we're in
if we are in the approach and in it
State then we want to do this and check
to see if we're in pre-flight yet and if
we're not but we just continue to go in
here once we are in pre-flight well this
will change next time the loop and we'll
end up
here and then we want to check are we in
inflight yet and if we are in inflight
then we can go to the inflight
State and then once we're inlight we
have a bunch of different calculations
that we can make to determine what state
will be the next state after that and
that all depends on on how well and how
good you can fly your ship back to the
mother's ship if poorly then well you'll
probably end up with a bad ending and if
good then you'll probably end up with a
good ending and all of that calculations
for determining if we went too fast we
missed the Mother Ship we need to turn
the gear down we got a we crashed
because we didn't have any gears open
you forgot to open your landing gear
perhaps um all these different
calculations and whatever that determine
which ending you get is all calculated
here and obviously we have all these
different case statements here that also
do determine that also essentially move
the mother ship on screen realistically
it's actually moving the Mother Ship but
from a display perspective uh it looks
like you're the one moving the ship so
even though it says steer up we have the
Y offset Plus+ which again if you
remember how that works that's actually
moving it down on the Y perspective
that's why if you have a right it's it's
actually left and or for X it's uh
pluses to the right minuses to the left
and we want to make the mothership go to
the left to make it look like you're
moving to the right if that makes any
sense we also have a switch that
determines what we what button we
pressed and with
that that covers all
of what should be necessary for day
29 of the Third 30 days Lost in Space
Adventure kit code explanations but
you're not done yet um one last little
request I have of you guys is when you
guys do run the program um it will give
you an ending time it will say how long
it took you to successfully land in the
mother ship and I want to see which of
you is the fastest so if you guys can
leave your comments down below as to who
made it into their ship the fastest or
what your time was and uh you guys can
compare it to other cadetes who have
also o successfully just completed the
30 days Lost in Space challenge it's
been a wonderful time I appreciate all
of you guys and I look forward to seeing
you guys in what's
next welcome to the day 29 wiring
example video the big day has finally
arrived we're as ready as we're ever
going to be for our Final Approach and
landing at the mothership we've been
honing our hardware and software skills
leading up to to this moment so now it's
finally time to take the controls and
fly it in now not everything has gone
exactly according to plan and we've had
to make some adjustments along the way
if we were following asterids
instructions exactly we'd now be
preparing to use our rotary encoder
control to control our thrust and
approach speed however it turns out that
using the rotary encoder M causes
conflicts in our hero processor that
interfere with the use of our other
components rendering it unreliable for
this critical
operation so with time running short to
get back to the Mothership we've had to
reluctantly set aside the encoder to use
a backup plan since we have extra unused
keys on our push button keypad we'll use
those for our speed control instead it
might not be quite as smooth as the
encoder control but with a little
practice it should be good enough to get
us
home now let's quickly review our
hardware setup for
today our pre-flight system status
switches that we're familiar with are
connected to analog hero pins a 0 A1 and
A2 and those switches will need to be
placed in the off position to enable our
landing approach at the
beginning now as always our OLED display
is connected in the one way that we have
available to us and that is on pins A4
and A5 and you can look at our previous
Day projects if you need to review that
our four-digit alpha numeric display is
what we'll be using to monitor our range
from the mother ship and we'll have its
clock and Dio lines connected here to
Hero pins five and four so clock to five
and Dio to four and that should be
consistent with the specification that's
in our software sketch
both of these displays also use the
ground and power connections that we've
described previously as
well now finally we have our keypad
which will be doing the L share of the
work as we attempt to safely control our
approach the eight number
keys that form a square in the upper
left hand corner of our keypad
will correspond to the cardinal
directions to maneuver our ship so for
example Keys 2 and eight here at the top
and the bottom will be used to move our
aim up or
down and for example key3 here in the
upper right of the square would be used
to move to the upper right and key s
would be move moving to the lower left
and so on our OLED display will give us
the targeting information and the cues
that we need to know in which direction
to make Corrections with our keypad so
we'll pay attention to
that in addition to the direction Keys
we also have our landing gear and speed
controls as I mentioned
before as in our previous days projects
the a key in the upper right is used to
lower the gear for landing but it can't
be used until the Final Approach phase
when we are signaled that it's okay on
the
OLED if we need to we can also retract
the landing gear using key
B now our speed is increased and
decreased Now using the C and the D keys
in in the lower right of the keypad so C
would be to speed up and D would be to
slow down learning to use these Keys
effectively will be important because we
want to keep the speed high enough to
dock before our supplies run out but not
so high that we crash on approach so
we'll work through those scenarios
shortly now with that Hardware
description complete we're finally ready
to run through an actual
approach now on the first run through
I'm going to intentionally not control
my speed well enough and we'll see what
the result of that is and then I'll try
to do a better job and see if I can
stick The Landing At Last so let's go
ahead let's check and make sure that our
switches are in the off position and we
have all three switches 1 2 3 in the off
position so they should be ready to
go so with that we'll go ahead and
upload our sketch so uploading the
sketch
now going through the compile phase
right
now and now uploading is underway and so
in a few seconds we should see feedback
on our displays and we should be ready
to start our landing
approach okay so here we are we current
currently are in pre-flight with our
switches in the off position so in order
to proceed with our Landing we're going
to have to cycle those switches to on so
I'll go ahead and start with the first
switch and we have that
on second
switch that's on and finally the third
switch I guess I threw both of the
switches at once so we have all three
switches in the on position
so our approach will begin as soon as I
bring my speed up and start approaching
the Mother Ship so we should see our
speed rise on the indicator here when I
bring the speed up our current range to
the Mother Ship is 1394 M and so as
we're approaching if we're careful about
things when we're about halfway in say
at around 700 600 700 M or something
like that we should be wanting to reduce
our speed so that we have enough fuel
and enough thrust to bring our speed
down to a a slow speed for landing so
let's go ahead and I'm going to be a
little bit uh less than cautious on this
first approach so I'll bring my speed up
by pressing the up key and you can see
I'm raising my speed with each press and
you can see that my range is is dropping
here so I'm going to keep going up so
I'm down to a th000 MERS getting closer
and closer and I'm not paying attention
to my targeting so I better start
getting my targeting back on track here
and you can see that I'm getting pretty
close I'm within 500 meters and maybe I
should be slowing down here but I'm also
paying attention to my targeting so I'm
going to try and keep myself centered in
the in the Target window and it looks
pretty good and now I'm down to 200 100
m and if I'm not paying attention oh
look I can lower my landing gear I'll go
ahead and lower the landing gear and
slow myself
oh look at
that I I was going too fast as I
approached the landing Bay and even
though I had my Landing year down
successfully I was going too fast and so
uh that was not a good
Landing so let's go ahead uh restart the
uh hero and see if I can can do a little
bit better job on my second time around
so we'll go ahead and uh let's see I'll
I'll uh put my switches back into the
off position so that we're ready for
another
attempt and we'll reset the
hero all right so let's try this again
this time let's see if we can approach a
little bit more uh
cautiously so switch one is
on switch two is
on switch three is on and we're ready to
go all right so let's see if we can
approach a little bit more cautiously
this
time so bringing up the speed
now
okay bring my speed up let's let's bring
it up to about eight and let's start
controlling our our uh targeting a
little bit bring us a little bit
more
into range we're down to 700 M so this
might be a good time for us to start
reducing our speed a little bit let's
bring our speed down to four let's see
we're targeting is pretty good we're
down to 400 m let's see let's bring the
speed down bring the speed down to two
keep ourselves
centered looking pretty good speed is
looking pretty nice we're down to 200
M and let's bring the speed down one
more
click and we're down to under uh 200
M working pretty good bring the landing
gear down now
Landing you're down all
right and easing on
in 60
m
Keep It On Target and we made it in just
over a 100 seconds we were able to uh
land the shuttle and H keep it within
Target and on the speed and so that's
pretty
good although it's quite possible that
uh you might be able to accomplish a
landing a safe landing in less time than
that so we'll have to see just how your
how your skill Stacks up
well that was fun and so uh maybe you
could can do better than this and land
in less time than I was able to but in
any case good luck with your landing and
congratulations on making it back to the
Mother Ship we'll see you on board for
the big
celebration all right trusty space
fairer the stage is set and the
preparations are made to quote a noble
albeit fictional human I've shown you
the door you're the one that has to walk
through it I'll be guiding your descent
from my post get your ship docked with
the mother ship in one piece and you'll
have this adventure well in hand start
by engaging the three levers on your dip
switch simple enough next you'll deploy
the docking gear by pressing the a
button on your control panel take heed
Explorer there will be no turning back
ready engage
Easy Does It Explorer trust your
instruments and modify the rate of
approach accordingly don't be Hasty
now beautiful but Pride goeth before the
fall Adventure slow and steady wins this
race that's it I can practically feel
the comfort of our cold injust Docking
Bay
now you've done it Explorer they'd
surely call you the mcgyver of the 23rd
Century if that reference still held
cultural cash you've Tak taken
Antiquated repair tools Elementary
Computing and a little guidance from a
superior intelligence I won't say who
and applied them in a rather superhuman
feat of Ingenuity and problem solving I
couldn't be prouder though I never
doubted you not for a second until our
next adventure Explorer stay curious and
keep seeking New
[Music]
Horizons