[Applause]
[Music]
ah you're up hope you're ready for the
dawn of a new day in this damp tin can
that we're calling home week three
already huh seems like just yesterday
you were fumbling over the basics look
at you now power light a snazzy RGB
battery indicator all pretty impressive
I must say this week we're shifting
gears enough with the basic survival
needs it's time we brought this old ship
back to life our goal is to fix up that
control panel whose appearance looks as
if a martian tried to play tic tac toe
on it to start us off we've got a new
tool to familiarize oursel with a 4x4
keypad I know you must be thrilled do
try not to let its looks intimidate you
that's 16 whole buttons of potential
inputs at our fingertips alongside our
new hardware We've Got A New Concept to
grasp brace yourself because we're
diving into the wonderful world of
libraries today think of libraries as
your ultimate cheat sheet shortcuts that
make coating easier so Dawn your
programmer's hat take a sip of that
dehydrated coffee and let's tackle the
day ahead we've got work to do
Explorer all right let's chat about our
new piece of Hardware the 4x4 keypad
each button when pressed closes a
circuit and sends a signal that we can
detect and utilize it's similar to a
keyboard you might use on a computer but
far less
complicated these keypads are often used
in security systems door entry systems
and all sorts of devices where manual
input is necessary today we'll be using
it as a control interface for our
spaceship
the real magic happens when each button
or key is pressed a unique combination
of two connections is made one
connection from the four row pins and
one from the four column pins this
allows us to know exactly which button
was pressed without needing a separate
input pin for each button each of these
16 buttons can serve as an individual
input providing us with a wealth of
potential interaction options I can see
it now we could set a code to trigger a
certain action or assign different tasks
to different Keys the possibilities are
vast and are waiting to be explored this
also means we can reduce the amount of
input pins needed from 16 to 8 which is
important when we have limited pin real
estate on our
hero but before we dive into all of that
let's get this Mighty piece of Machinery
wired up and running shall we my that
was quite easy looks like we can skip
the breadboard entirely
today speaking of easy let's hop on to
our next coding concept and explore the
power of your new partner in crime
libraries in coding terms a library is
like a prepackaged set of code that
provide specific functionality
essentially they give you a lot of new
functions to use and make your life
easier now let's talk about the new
library you will need to install the
keypad Library this is a custom Library
designed specifically for interfacing
with keypads of various sizes like a 4x4
keypad for example how convenient it
includes functions for detecting when
keys are pressed which keys are pressed
and even some Advanced functionality
like multi- key detection by using this
keypad Library we can simplify our code
and kick our level of efficiency up a
notch because who needs more
complications when you're trying to
repair a spaceship right in order to use
our library we'll first need to install
it if my calculations are correct there
should be a link located somewhere
cached on your current computer page to
a zip file download that to your
computer and then in the Arduino IDE
navigate to tools then manage libraries
then add zip library and select the
newly downloaded zip file take all the
time you need preferably as quick as you
can I'll be here waiting patiently for
you when you return you finished
wonderful let's continue Explorer the
library allows us to accomplish another
New Practical task and that is to create
a new unique object a keypad it also
adds in functions like get key to tell
us which key is being pressed in order
for the newly installed library to help
us however we need to First provide it
with some relevant information here is
our list of to-dos we need to tell it
how many rows we have how many columns
we have the pins that we we are using
for our column pins the pins that we are
using for our row pins and finally we
need to create a key map for the
buttons that was quite a mouthful well
we know we have four rows four columns
and we can take a look at which pins
we're using by simply looking at our
wiring diagram next we have to make a
key map we can achieve this by utilizing
a pair of new data structures in
programming arrays in the realm of
programming an array is a data structure
that allows you to store multiple values
in a single variable imagine it like a
storage box with multiple compartments
you can put different items or in our
case data values in each compartment and
later access them using an index an
array is defined by the type of data it
can hold like integers Floats or
characters once an array is declared the
type of data it can hold is fixed you
aren't able to mix integers and strings
for
example each individual value in the
array is assigned an index in most
languages the first element in the array
is indexed as zero so if you have an
array of five elements they would be
indexed from 0 to
four let's discuss this further pay
close attention because this is a
stumbling block for many new programmers
even the best of them remember this like
a mantra arrays start at zero not one
zero not a nothing got it great take
look at this innocent little array
grocery list if I ask you what is that
grocery list one what would you say
here's the array for you to
ponder no no it's not milk remember the
Mantra milk is lounging at index zero so
at index one we have egg good so if our
grocery list array has three items what
do we find at grocery list
three h don't tell me you fell for that
it was a trick question Explorer there's
nothing there if you were to venture so
far out to index 3 you'd be rudely met
with an outof bounds exception a digital
slap on the wrist for trying to access
memory you were not given access to so
tread lightly and count carefully with
arrays all right Explorer if you've
gotten your head around a
one-dimensional array let's kick it up a
notch get ready for the twodimensional
array sounds Stupify do doesn't it think
of a one-dimensional array as a straight
line a single row of elements now take
that line and add more lines below it
like a grid voila you have a
two-dimensional array think of a matrix
such as a chess or
checkerboard so if you had a 2d array
like this you could access egg from
Monday's list with weekly grocery list
01 remember our Mantra arrays start at
zero
be mindful not to lose yourself in the
matrix it's all too easy to get an out
of bounds exception if you're not
careful stay vigilant now let's take a
step back and try writing up our key map
for example in the context of our 4x4
keypad we could have an array that looks
like
this this two-dimensional array has four
rows and four columns to represent the
layout of our keypad look similar to
anything here's a photo of a different
for 4x4 keypad with equivalent
functionality as ours from a small
company's Adventure kit 2 from around
the same era as our hero board was
produced well we're not just going to
stare at our spanking new 4x4 keypad are
we we want to see it in action but how
do we read the button presses you ask
time to bring out the heavy artillery
our keypad Library it's got a Nifty
function tucked away in its folds called
get key get key does exactly what it
sounds like it fetches the key that's
been pressed quite ingenious
really what do you say we cut to some
instructional material that I was able
to gather cash on the computer I've also
added this to your mission resources for
future reference you're welcome as
always hello and welcome back to day 11
of the code explanations for the 30 days
Lost in Space Adventure kit today we're
going to be taking a look at the
following new Concepts you should
hopefully have your 4x4 keypad all wired
up we're going to be looking at the new
idea of what a library is we're going to
be looking at character types and we're
going to be looking at arrays both
onedimensional and we're actually going
to jump straight to two-dimensional for
today as well now I'm sure you guys
already know that at the top of every
single program we have this hashtag or
pound sign include
uo. we explicit ly put this at the top
for the reason of when we get to day 11
which is today you guys should already
be familiar with the idea of including
libraries at the top technically this is
a weird exception because the Arduino
IDE the program that we're looking at
right now automatically includes that
whether you have it at the top or not so
if you don't have it it will
automatically added in for you so this
is kind of the weird exception however
what happens when you want to add more
libraries in that now let's remember
what a library is let's take a step back
and remember what a library is a library
is essentially a bunch of extra code and
functionality that you can add to your
program with little to no effort
basically you're taking somebody else's
pre-written code in functions and just
adding a pound include to basically get
access to all the functions and cool
stuff that they've already written and
hopefully debugged in this case we need
additional functionality to get our 4x4
keypad that we've just wired up today
working so in order to do that we're
going to be downloading a library called
keypad. what keypad. H is is it's a
library that's used for any variety it
could be 4x4 it could be 8 by 8 it could
be a 12x 12 it could be 2x two it
doesn't matter but the keypad library is
a dynamically used library for multiple
types of keypad inputs now to download
this you're going to want to go to
inventor. i/ libraries you're going to
want to go down to the adventure kit
section and you're going to want to make
sure you download the 4x4 keypad library
and it should install a zip file
somewhere on your machine next you're
going to want to go to sketch include
library and you're going to click the
add. zip library and you're going to
select the file that you just downloaded
after you've successfully installed that
Library if you were to hit compile
hopefully you should not be seeing any
errors that look like
this if you don't have the file you
would see something normally that says
fatal error keypad. no such file or
directory compilation is terminated and
it won't compile your program because it
doesn't know where to find the required
stuff that you said is going to be
included in thish file so if you've
downloaded it you should be able to go
sketch glude Library at. zip library and
let me just select it from my downloads
folder now I've successfully installed
the library hero 4x4 keypad. zip and if
I were to try this once
again you'll see it compiles with no
issues
whatsoever now this keypad library has
its own required information if we take
a look we can actually see what the code
inside of this library is doing by going
to if we highlight over it we can see
exactly where it's
located so I've now opened up the key.
file um in another editor and this is
the library that is the open source
library for
keypad. the header file contains mostly
information that is all more indepth in
the C++ file but you can go and let's
just jump here for example to the C++
file and as you can see it has a ton of
code throughout all of here that
basically grabs a whole bunch of
information and gives us a whole bunch
of stuff and I don't want to go through
any of this because that's the point of
a library a library is the fact that
this should all hopefully be working
somebody else's code that gives us
additional functionality to do a whole
bunch of stuff for example there's this
get keys function that does all this
stuff but in our code if we want to call
get keys or we want to define a key
keypad all we need to do to do the exact
same functionality since we all this is
in the code here all we need to do is
have the number of rows the number of
columns and we want to define the keypad
we just simply say keypad calling from
that Library we're going to call ours in
this code hero keypad equals
keypad make keymap with the
buttons and we're going to say the rows
and columns and column Vin but we have
all this in just one
line versus this exact same function if
we wanted to Define and make a keypad is
obviously all of this and requires a
functionality from all of this here so
this is just a simple way of doing all
that extra code but just by using
somebody else's pre-existing solution
solution instead of Reinventing the
wheel as programmers sometimes like to
be lazy and we can actually just use
somebody else's solution to save time on
our code now that means that at the top
of any file where we're going to be
using the key had library or any other
library for example we need to make sure
that we include that so that's what this
is here include keypad. and we put those
in the Syntax for it is to do pound
include and then the greater than sign
less than sign and then inside we you
can just have the header file keypad. H
which is inside of that zip file that
we've installed next I want to go down
and I want to talk about the rest of the
requirements for the keypad library in
order to Define what the keypad is and
what it's going to be doing we need to
have a little bit of information first
of all we need to know how many rows
there's going to be and we need to know
how many columns there's going to be in
this case rows and columns are both four
because we have a 4x4 keypad so this
it's pretty easy I'm just keeping these
at the top so that later on in the code
they should be hopefully very easy to
add in next we need to know what pins
are we talking to on the herob board
well in this case if you follow the
wiring diagram that we have the row pins
are going to be pins 5 4 3 and two and
the pins for the column are going to be
6 7 8 and 9 if you change up the wiring
diagram in any way whatsoever this will
probably no longer work so make sure
that you follow the code and wiring
diagram that we've provided very closely
if you're going to be making any
changes however let's take a step back
you probably have not seen this format
before this format is completely new and
this introduces A New Concept in the
programming languages this is called an
array this is a constant array that
contains the PIN connected to the
keypads rows and columns now let's take
a moment to explain what an array
actually is I want you to think of a
list in this case let's say it's a
grocery list and this grocery list is
going to be let's have an array an array
of length three so there's going to be
three things on your grocery list that
you need to pick up today we're going to
have the following milk eggs and butter
so to do this let's use this the data
type
string
grocery list and we're going to have it
be a length
three
equals and then what are all the items
we just
mentioned
eggs
milk and butter and then obviously go
like this now this is how you would make
an array of length three an array at the
end of the day is mostly just a list
this can be a list of anything you want
it can be strings it can be in this case
up here we have them being bytes it can
be integers it can be floats it can be
objects it can be whatever you want it
to be inside of there but they all need
to be the same type that is a
requirement for a lists so you can't
have you need milk uh eggs milk and
instead of butter you have 42 that won't
work because 42 is not a string so what
you need to do is you need to make sure
that they are all of the same
type like so now another thing I need to
mention is that arrays even though it is
of length three let's just say you want
to find if I were to ask a question now
grab me the third element on the list to
do so you might think and this is a new
syntax you would grab do something along
the lines
of you might think you want to do
something like this to get the third
element you should just print the
element at the index of three right nope
that is actually wrong if you try to get
the element at index of three you'll be
accessing what would should have been in
this spot here but there's nothing here
so how do you do that and why is it that
way since arrays will always start and
us as programmers always like to start
at index of zero so if you were wanting
to grab the third element it's confusing
and I know it's a little bit hard for
new programmers you'd want to grab this
if you said this this would print butter
if you said one you would not be getting
the first element you'd be getting milk
which is the second element and if you
said zero because again arrays always
start at
zero this would be printing eggs so eggs
if you want to print milk if you wanted
to print butter this is how you would do
so but at the end of the day arrays is
just a data structure that allows us to
keep things in a nice organized list and
we can access what's on the list by
using syntax such as that now that we
know what an array is at least hopefully
in a little bit more detail we can
actually jump down to here where we're
going to be introducing another concept
called a twodimensional array think of
this is like a list but it's
two-dimensional so in in my opinion I
would like to think of this actually
more as like a spreadsheet if you've
ever used something like Microsoft Excel
or Google Sheets let's just say you want
to access Row 2 column 3 remember that
everything starts at zero so you'd go
row 0 1 2 and then you'd want column 3
which would be 0 1 2 3 and that would be
this here the character C so the way to
access data in a 2d array is actually
very similar to how you would access it
into a onedimensional array it's just
that you need to also specify the not
only the index but the index of the
column as well so think of it kind of
like an Excel sheet and that's um how I
would generally think of it is it's a
little bit easier to remember that way
now the reason we're doing a
two-dimensional array to Define what
each of the buttons will stand for is
because well as you can see let's
actually hold up maybe you can even hold
it up right to your monitor go ahead and
hold up your keypad right to where the
4x4 2D array is on your monitor you
might notice that it lines up ever so
perfectly the top left button will be
one then two then three then the
character a four 56 the character B 789
the character C star zero pound and then
the character D now I'm sure that in the
past you've seen before various things
such as strings obviously if you're
going to use a print statement and you
want to say battery level you know and
then and then print what the battery
level is battery level in double quotes
double quotes being looking like this
and
this
string obviously this isn't pile but
this is what a string would look like it
would be something inside of Double
quote such as that is generally how
strings are represented now you'll
notice that these are kind of like
strings a b c and d but they're in
single quotes now why are they in single
quotations well fun fact did you know
that the data type of string is quite
literally just an array of characters
and characters or chars is just an
additional data type so fun fact little
did you know you've been using arrays
this entire time so for example I just
want to give you a good example of what
I'm talking about here if you say
something like and I'm just going to put
this in a little comment block string
let's just say you use a
string string name
equals hello
world did you know that this is quite
literally just an array of characters
what the compiler will do is it will
string together all of these individual
characters and then compile it into an
array of length well in this case the
compiler will automatically do 1 2 3 4 5
6 7 8 9 10 11 12 anytime you've ever
used string the compiler will
automatically convert it when you hit
verify and compile it would
automatically convert it to an an array
of characters such as this it' be Char
string name of length 12 cuz that's
what's in here H comma e comma l dot dot
dot Etc so this entire time you've
actually already been using aace and
it's just a list of what characters
we're going to be using so a character
at the end of the day is just a much
simpler form of the string because it's
obviously instead of needing an array
for a string it's just the actual data
type itself called a
Char in this case all of these values
are chars even the one the one is not an
integer it is a character it is a
character asky of of one it is not the
number integer of one this is the asy
character of two this is obviously a c
this is the asy of a hashtag or pound
symbol and this is the ash key of a star
now the reason we're using characters is
because our goal for today is to be able
to print out all of these characters and
to make sure that our keypad is wired up
correctly once we have all of this
information we made the map we've made
the bytes for the pinouts or the arrays
to show what pins we're going to be
using and we've told them how many pins
and columns we have we can then finally
construct our keypad now this seems like
a lot of work however given the fact
that we have our library that does most
of the work for us you can actually as
you can as you remember it's actually
not all that much work Let's ignore all
this and let's say thank goodness we
didn't have to do any of that we can R
say just down to this now that we have
this we now have a keypad that we can
call those functions from now we've
called it hero
keypad anytime we want to call a
function that's included in the library
for example we have get keys we have
Scan Keys we have all these other
functions anytime we want to call those
functionalities and be able to do those
things on our keypad that they allowed
us to we can do something like this hero
keypad. 4 key like this and this will
call the function that was included in
here to let us use on our keypad that we
finally defined
however we don't actually need to do all
that much here we only have hero keypad.
wait4 key and all this does is it just
simply Waits until a button is pressed
as soon as a button is pressed it will
save whatever character read off the
keypad into Char pressed button and then
finally we will serial. print print Ln
whatever button we pressed and it will
print that to the serial monitor at B
rate 9600 that we defined in setup one
last thing I want to mention is you
don't have to set all of these as
outputs in any way shape or form on here
and the reason we don't have to is
because as the library already takes
care of it for us it already has
functionality to set the pin modes
inside of the library so we don't have
to worry about doing it here in
setup therefore our setup is actually
very simple and just has us start the
serial. begin assuming you have
everything wired up correctly and all is
good to go you should be able to just
hit serial monitor read off B 9600 and
then start pressing buttons and
hopefully you can start seeing as you go
through each of the buttons everything
will be printing
correctly and with that that's the end
of the code for today I will see you
again
tomorrow welcome to the day 11 wiring
example video actually today there
really isn't any breadboard wiring at
all for us to discuss we'll just be
exploring the use of our 4x4 keypad
input device and so the only wiring
involves connecting it directly to the
hero input pins the only output we'll
have at at least for now will be the
characters that are sent to the serial
monitor
console now you can see here that we've
connected our keypads eight lines eight
lines there are four each for four rows
and four Columns of buttons on our
keypad we're connecting them to the
input pins on the hero numbered 2
through 9 now to keep the wiring need
and and organized we've used a multic
connector or a multiconductor
ribbon cable for this purpose and the
ribbon cable has color coding that helps
us to sort of keep the connections
straight and keep from confusing the
proper connections your Ribbon cable
might actually have different colors
from these but that's not important
because what's really important is
having the correct connection between
the keyboard the the the keypad and the
hero pins by the way you might notice
that my ribbon cable here just happens
to have black as one of its colors and I
guess that's kind of unfortunate because
we've tried as much as possible to only
use black for ground connections but in
this case it was impossible for me to
include the ribbon cable without having
to either use a red or a black wire as
part of the signal bundle so I just
decided to go ahead and use black in
this case for pin
n but kept in mind to remember that in
this particular case black is not a
ground wire um so we've made an
exception this time now when we read
through the software sketch for today we
see that each row and column combination
for a pressed button so we press a
particular button that belongs to a row
or a column is assigned to one of 16
different output characters which I've
identified on this guide card right here
for our
reference the keypad rows and columns
are numbered with the origin in the
upper left so they number from upper
left to lower right so for example the
character that has the lowest numbered
row and column in our sketch is the
number one and so that should map to the
upper left hand button on our keypad
likewise the highest number row and
column in our sketch corresponds to the
character D which we have mapped to the
lower right hand corner of our cued and
so on so if we've correctly wired up the
keypad here consistent with what's in
our sketch all that really remains for
us to do is to load the sketch and then
watch the serial monitor as we press the
buttons and see that we get the output
that we expect so let's go ahead and do
that let's move over to the
IDE sketch is loading
and sketch is now running so let's go
ahead now and let's say press the upper
left hand key we get one as expected
press the lower right key we get the
character D good and we can go across
the rows and columns so for example if I
go across the second row there's four
five 6 B and go to the bottom row here
asterisk
Zer pound sign D and so on so it appears
that we have correctly lined up our
software sketch with the wiring of our
keypad and we're ready to go on to more
difficult things so that's pretty much
all for today's task once you've
completely understood what's going on
here then we'll be ready for the next
step and we'll connect the keypad input
to other output functions in circuitry
so we'll see you
then hi you've been busy today getting
to grips with our 4x4 keypad is no small
feat but you've done splendidly you're
now able to read button presses with the
deafness of a seasoned space fairer I
hope you're starting to see the
potential here you are after all
building a control system bit by bit and
this is just the beginning now allow me
to entice you with a hint of what's to
come tomorrow I'm running a diet
agnostic
on compartment 16 is taking on water
I've got it don't
panic I don't understand the warning
light should have been clearly visible
and you didn't pick up on it okay
Explorer we can't risk another Hull
breach we need to find a way to keep you
aware of potential problems no matter
where you're looking I'll first aid the
compartment and you think about
alerts and now the alarm systems failed
I guess we've got our work cut out for
us
[Music]
tomorrow