[Music]
good morning Explorer or is it evening
oh who knows under this ocean blanket
now let's wipe that tax look off your
face oh well that is your face oops get
ready to tackle our next big task we
can't ignore this any longer our battery
levels are going critical our hero
experiments and shipboard lighting
barely draw anything but what's killing
us is just keeping things warm I've had
to shut down section C to F so no more
jelly parkour I'm
afraid our solo array which normally
bathes in glorious sunlight to charge
our batteries is as inactive as a frozen
Comet it's imperative that we restore it
luckily our kit is equipped with
materials that have been waiting oh so
patiently to be introduced photo
resistors for our training purposes it's
enough to know that photo resistors also
react to light like solar panels but in
a different way photo resistors react to
light like summer flowers when the Sun
rises flowers open When the Sun Goes
Down flowers close with photo resistors
when they receive light their resistance
decreases allowing more current to pass
or higher signal levels as red in
darkness resistance increases choking
current lowering signal levels we can
use this to simulate our solar panels
receiving sunlight so brace yourself
dear Explorer day six begins and we have
a solar system to fix let's get to know
our newest shining star shall we this
little device is also known as a light
dependent resistor or ldr for short the
resistance of a photo resistor decreases
with increasing incident light
intensity in simpler terms when there's
more light the flow of electrons becomes
easier when there's less light the flow
becomes harder think of it as an
electrical component throwing a more
light more fun party photo resistors are
made of high resistant semiconductor
material whe try saying that five times
fast when light hits the device it
absorbs the light photons this
absorption process provides energy to
the electrons which makes them jump from
their veence band of orbits to the
conduction band this leap means the
electrons are free to move thus reducing
the material's resistance it's like
magic only its scientific nature is
backed up by empirical evidence and
testable explanations essentially a
photo resistor is a sensor that allows
us to detect light in the way that a
solar panel uses it to generate power
they are the key component we need to
simulate and fix our solar array today
remember they are small and sensitive
treat them well and they'll return the
favor in kind Explorer moving right
along let's delve into the slightly more
complex topic the concept of analog and
digital signals do bear with me Explorer
as this will be vital for us to
understand our photo resistor
readings all right analog signals these
are continuous signals imagine a dimmer
switch connected to a light bulb the
dimmer can be adjusted to any level
between on and off providing an infinite
number of positions of brightness this
is like an analog signal where the
values can fall anywhere within a
certain
range in terms of microcontrollers they
are a bit more complex to handle due to
their nature of being prone to
degradation and noise interference what
this complexity does however is allow
them to represent numerous amounts of
information with the potential to
provide more accurate and refined data
unlike analog signals digital signals
are discret and can only be in one of
two states which are usually represented
by either zeros or ones meaning low and
high picture a staircase each step you
take is a definite value there are no
inet
while they might not be as smooth or
precise as their analog counterparts
digital signals are highly resistant to
noise and easy to work with in terms of
programming most of our microcontroller
functions like digital write and digital
read work with digital signals so where
do our photo resistors fit in I'm glad
you asked the value they provide based
on light intensity is an analog signal
it can theoretically be an infinite
number of values that's why to read
these values we need to use a different
set of functions that can handle this
variety The Analog functions but more on
that when we dive into the code in
summary remember analog is like a dimmer
continuous and smooth while digital is
like stairs definite and distinct got it
great all right Explorer I know you've
been wondering why of all the many pins
we specifically chose the a zero pin on
the hero board for our photo resistor
well let me break it down for you
you see a z is an analog pin now our
photo resistor isn't just a simple light
or no light type of device no it's much
more refined than
that it measures how much light there is
it's like the difference between asking
if there's food at a party and asking
how much food is there I mean a few
crumbs of chips don't really count do
they anyway because we want a wide range
of values and not just a zero or one we
need an analog pin hence a z
it's really as simple as that analog
pins for Analog Devices digital pins for
digital devices well done Explorer
you've digested all that analog and
digital chitchat pretty well now let's
shift our attention to the programming
part of our task and what do you know
we've got another new tool in our kit to
introduce the Arduino serial monitor the
serial monitor is one of the most useful
tools we have at our disposal when
programming with the Arduino IDE think
of it as a window through which your
computer can have a conversation with
the microcontroller in this case our
herob board with the serial monitor we
can send data to the hero board and
receive data from it it can also be used
to examine the state of variables to
debug which is the act of finding and
removing bugs in our code or like we'll
be doing today to monitor the readings
from our photo resistors to access it
we'll need to start by including some
code in our sketch to establish a Serial
communication then when we want to take
a peek at the data being sent from the
herob board to the computer we simply
click on the serial monitor option in
the tools menu in the Arduino ID ready
to give it a shot Explorer let's dive
into the code and start using the serial
monitor to get a sense of what our photo
resistor is telling us about our power
situation we're going to start using
some new commands today starting with
analog read this function allows our
hero board to read analog input signals
which is just what we need for our photo
resistors
analog read measures the voltage between
zero which represents z v and 1,23 which
represents 5 V and returns a
corresponding value in essence when we
use analog read we're asking the herob
board to take a voltage reading from a
specific analog pin and translate it
into a number we can use in our code
reading and writing are two fundamental
operations in hero programming or any
programming for that matter when when we
read we're taking data or information in
when we write we're sending data or
information out in our doino terms
reading is often associated with sensors
or inputs like our determined photo
resistors they read or gather
information from the physical world
which is used to make decisions in our
code on the other hand writing is
generally associated with actuators or
outputs like LEDs or Motors we write to
them to control their behavior based on
the logic in our code
all right Explorer are you ready to put
this into practice let's start with
analog read and see what we can learn
from our photo
resistors it's about that time let's
turn to some instructional material that
I was able to gather cached on the
computer I've also added this to your
mission resources for future reference
hurry on
now welcome back to day six of the 30
days Lost in Space Adventure kit let's
start by doing the very obvious which is
collapsing a bunch of these comments
that the code becomes a little bit less
daunting boom boom boom boom boom boom
now that we've collapsed all the
comments it should hopefully be slightly
less daunting to look at from the looks
of it it seems as if that your battery
is currently in a very very rough
position right now I don't know exactly
why or how you got it to be as bad as it
is but it's currently in a very very bad
position I'm on top of that we do have
solar panels on board your ship which
you can deploy to the surface of the
water to start getting some charge on to
your battery back however the problem is
if we deploy it and there's not enough
charge to pull it back in because
something was wired up incorrectly I
don't know if you're ever going to get
that charge back or those solar panels
back so we need to make sure that before
we send it out it's wired up correctly
or else we're going to have definitely a
bit of a problem later on as we won't be
able to pull it back to fix it and you
will be stuck at the bottom of the ocean
forever so let's start by
simulating this using a new type of
device called a photo resistor before we
deploy our solar panels up to the
surface a photo resistor is similar to a
solar panel in the way that it reacts to
light it is an analog device it is not a
digital device so it's not like the
switches that you saw on day three and
four these are completely different in
the fact that they are analog they are
not on or off they are well you can
think of it as how on or how off they
are I guess is like a better way to
think about it it's essentially going to
give us a value somewhere between 0 and
255 and where 255 will be the greatest
number that it is and uh zero will be
the lowest number that it can represent
depending on how much light is shining
on it this is very similar to a solar
panel in which if you get a lot of
sunlight it's going to charge very
quickly versus if you don't have a lot
of sunlight it's going to charge very
slowly so we can simulate that using
this let's start off by first obviously
we have the include Arin no. I'm just
going to delete that just to show that
it's not actually necessary but if you
want to keep it it won't hurt next we
have constant bite photo resistor pin
equals a0 you might be thinking that a0
is is not a number as you've seen in the
past before with previous defined
statements from last previous weeks
however a z can be used to talk about
the analog zero pin which is exactly
what we want it to do we want this to be
an input on our analog pin because it's
not going to be on or off which means we
can't use our digital pins it's going to
be how on or how off therefore we're
going to be using an analog pin as a
very quick recap the difference between
analog and dig are as follows an analog
device isn't quite as simple an analog
device can be very much so on or very
much so off or it can be somewhere in
between it's essentially a giant range
of values it's not zero or one it's 0 1
2 3 4 5 all the way up until whatever
you want to define the top limit as in
this case 255 now how we're going to
simulate this is we're going to have two
different blinking speeds those two
different blinking speeds that we're
going to have are going to be a very
fast blink and a very short blink and
depending on the light value that the
photo resistor is reading it's going to
either be a very quick or very slow
blink if it has a lot of light on it it
should be very quick and if it has a
very low amount of light perhaps if you
place your finger on top of it or
similar it might go and be a very slow
blink to show that the charging rate is
slower these are are defined at the top
and these are going to be in
milliseconds as you know the delay
function that we will be using for these
later is in milliseconds so this is
going to be 1/10th of a second and this
is going to be 1/2 of a second the
reason we represent these up above is
because you're also free to change these
if you so desire you want to and you
don't have to edit it down below in the
code you can just edit it once up above
and it'll change it everywhere you want
going forward we're going to go to our
onetime setup this is the very first
thing that the Arduino ID hits every
single time it goes into the
code now as I'm sure you've seen before
this is old but we'll go over it one
more time we have the pin mode for the
LED we're going to be setting the LED as
an output and we're going to be setting
the photo resistor as an input and that
is on of course analog pin zero now
here's where we get to something new
serial. begin 9600 what is serial cal.
let me introduce to you A New Concept in
the uino IDE known as the serial monitor
this serial monitor is a wonderful place
where you can read print statements off
of your hero board this is useful for
bazillion trillion different things such
as debugging it's wonderful for just
checking values as it executes
throughout the code it's wonderful for
just getting feedback on a whole variety
of different things in this case we're
going to want to be printing a lot of
debug statement ments something like the
light value that we're currently reading
off of the analog pin or the delay value
that we've chosen based on that light
value that it's reading now the 9600
that you see is the bits per second when
you open up the serial monitor you're
going to want to go and you're going to
want want to make sure that you have
selected the correct B rate if you don't
have the select B rate let's say you
select something that's a different
number than the one you have there it
will end up being quite a lot of
gibberish and it will not be easily
readable at all in fact it won't even
sometimes be even proper asky text it's
just going to be quite literally broken
text you're going to be reading a stream
of data that it doesn't know how to read
so make sure that whatever number you
put here is the exact same number that
you select in that drop down 9600 should
be good enough for most use cases so
that's what we're going to use in this
scenario after the setup is run and
we've begin talking over the over the
serial monitor at the B rate
9600 we will jump down down to the loop
function where we are going to do the
following first we're going to do
something very similar to what we did
previously with digital read with a new
function this function is called analog
read and analog read is a very similar
to what digital read is except for
Analog
Devices instead we're going to read off
the value and it's going to be a light
value from 0 to
10,24 I may have mentioned up here at
some point that this is 255 but that was
wrong because I was talking about the
max that a bite can represent so where
zero is going to be it's completely dark
and 1024 is if you're flashing the
brightest flashlight on Earth directly
on top of it and we're going to be
saving whatever it reads off of that
analog pin and we're going to be saving
it into an unsigned int called light
value finally right below this statement
as soon as we read that and we saved
whatever we read off the pin into this
value we're going to do a serial print
which is going to pop up in our serial
monitor once we run our code on our
board it will be serial.print light
value and then we're going to print what
the light value was now the next block
of
code is designed so that we can
calibrate the lights based on the
environment you're working in not
everybody who's running this code is
working in the exact same environment
for example I'm here in my very bright
bright office here at the inventure Corp
office and you are it seems stuck at the
bottom of an ocean in the middle of
nowhere on a foreign Planet way way
below the ocean surface I have a bright
environment you have a dark environment
and so in order to test our environments
all we need to do is we need to have a
little area to calibrate to make sure
that based on the average ranges in your
room and the average ranges in my room
the code should still work either way so
as you as you see here when the first
time we run through we're going to set
the darkest and brightest light to be
simply equal to the light value we read
off the pin right now the darkest and
the brightest are going to be the exact
same for the very first time we run
through the
loop however the next times we go
through the loop we're going to have the
next is thing is going to be checked and
that is going to be if the light value
is less than the darkest light value
that it's red then we're going to set
the new darkest light is equal to that
value and if the light value is brighter
than the very first time we went through
the loop then we're going to set the
brightest light is equal to that value
basically changing our ranges
dynamically as we go through so that
every time we go through the loop we can
basically reset our range for the high
and the low based on our current
environment now we have a slightly
interesting problem as our voltage
reading goes up we want the LED to Blink
faster in thus meaning a smaller delay
in addition we need to adjust the blink
rate in a noticeable way so we have one
range of numbers darkest to Brightest
values from our light
sensor that we wish to convert to a
different range that goes from Max delay
down to M
delay while we could for example just
put in uh delay and we could put in for
example what the value of the light is
the issue with that is that it kind of
is inverted from what we want it to be
able to do if we did that then the
longer it took between blanks would mean
it's more charged and the shorter
between blanks would mean it's less
charged and that's sort of an inverse of
what we wanted it to achieve
so the Arduino language provides a neat
function named map that was created just
for this situation it takes a value from
one range and Maps it to a desired range
so if for example we wanted to say we
could say what is the charge rate from 0
to 1024 if we knew those are the max
readable values but we want it to be
between one and 100 for example which is
an interesting way to do it we could use
something like
map the other case is exactly what we're
doing today now as you saw we defined up
here the minimum delay is 50 and the
maximum delay is 500 that means the
quickest it can possibly blink is is 50
milliseconds with is a 50 millisecond
delay between each blink the shortest it
can go is 500 milliseconds so at its
worst if it is a very very very dark
room it should be about 500 if it's a
very very very bright room it should be
about
50 however we can have any range of
values in between using the map function
so we can have 125 we can have 236 we
can have whatever number we want it to
be based off that value
and what we do is by using this map
function the very first thing is we're
taking the light value and we're going
to take what the light value is that
it's currently reading we're going to
take the darkest light and the brightest
light so as it goes through here it's
going to take what the darkest it's red
in the room is and the brightest it's
red in your current environment and it's
going to map it so that it matches the
range of between 50 and
500 and based on this light value
wherever this place is in between here
so let's just say that the darkest light
was 100 and the brightest light that it
read was 300 and the light value it's
currently
reading was 200 right directly smack dab
in the middle what that will do is it
will make the delay value that it wants
to be setting here we're going to be
setting it so that it is exactly smack
dab in the middle of what these are if
it's 50 and 500 then we can calculate it
to be
about
225 if it was smack dab in the middle
but let's just say it was got slightly
brighter maybe it changes to be 200
maybe it changes to be 125 but that's
the maximum it could be for this value
is going to be the maximum value it
could be was is set by the map function
is 500 and the minimum it could be would
be 50 once we calculate the value we'll
then print it using the serial Monitor
and it will print Down Below in our
serial Monitor and it will say delay
value and it will tell us what that is
finally we'll blink our built-in LED
using our delay value that we finally
calculated and as you know I'm sure
you've seen this blink function plenty
times before digital right the LED
built-in High delay by whatever we
calculated digital right low delay by
whatever we calculated and you can go
ahead if you run this on your board you
can see it print on the ser Monitor and
you can test it I recommend taking a
flashlight and your thumb and trying to
turn it on and off making it blink
faster and slower using those two items
and then obviously have it just take a
look and compare it to the room that
you're currently sitting in as well and
see how it Compares between the other
options of flashlight and
thumb now assuming that all this works
and all and you were able to upload this
successfully to the board and it can see
the wiring we should be good simulation
wise to get ready to send up the solar
panels back up to the surface and
hopefully save you from the dire
situation that you are currently in and
with that I'll see you on day
seven welcome to the wiring example
video for day
six since the circuit setup will be the
same on day seven this also serves as a
hardware introduction for that day as
well the main new hardware element that
we'll be dealing with on both days six
and seven is a sensor device called a
photo resistor as its name suggests it
functions like the resistors we've
already been using to regulate current
flow in our circuits but with a crucial
difference the resistance value of a
photo resistor changes depending upon
the intensity of light that's falling on
it and because of this property it can
be a useful device for monitoring the
brightness of say solar illumination or
some other source of light energy we
have a photo resistor right here as well
as another photo resistor hooked up to
our breadboard and so we'll spend a
little bit of time now discussing it we
can quickly demonstrate this variable
resistance property of a photo resistor
by simply hooking it up to a resistance
meter we have a multimeter right here
connected to this photo
resistor so we'll go ahead and measure
its resistance under different lighting
conditions we can see that if we cover
the photo resistor up and place it in
darkness with this black cloth we can
see that the resistance becomes
extremely high right now it's reading
over a half a million ohms that's.
55. 54 megaohms were about
500,000 ohms so that's a quite High
Resistance compared to the ones that
we've been dealing with in our circuits
so far but if I remove the black cloth
and allow light to fall on it we can see
that the resistance Falls rather
dramatically as a matter of fact if I
take a little U flashlight and I
illuminate the photo resistor brightly I
can get the resistance to drop even more
all the way down just a few hundred ohms
down to a value that's comparable to the
220 ohms that we've commonly been using
in our circuits to limit current and so
um that's good to know that we can vary
the resistance simply by changing the
light all the way from hundreds of
thousands of ohms down to just a few
hundred so this gives us a clue as to
how we might go about using this in a
circuit if we turn our attention to the
breadboard right here you'll notice that
we have a photo resistor that's part of
a circuit we're passing current through
our photo resistor by starting with the
5vt supply coming in on our red wire the
current passes through the photo
resistor and then in series it passes
again through a 220 arm resistor before
connecting with this black wire back to
ground to complete the circuit
now let's suppose that the photo
resistor has enough light falling on it
that it just happens to have a
resistance that's equal to that of the
220 Ohm resistor if that was the case
then we would expect that of the total
5vt difference between the supply side
of this circuit and ground of that total
5vt drop we would expect to see exactly
half of it or 2.5 volts be the voltage
difference across the photo resistor and
2.5 volts across the 220 Ohm resistor
because they would be equivalent
resistances on the other hand if the
photo resistor were in the dark say I
were to covered up with the black cloth
and it had an extremely high resistance
very high compared to 220 ohms then we'd
expect to see almost all of the 5V drop
across the photo resistor and very
little little or nearly zero voltage
drop across the 220
ohm this suggests to us a strategy for
measuring light because if we were to
monitor the voltage across the 220 Ohm
resistor it would serve as a kind of
proxy for the light intensity because
that voltage reading would be relatively
High when the light falling on the photo
resistor was bright and it would be a
low voltage when the photo resistor was
in the
dark so if you understand that principle
this will basically be the basis for our
project today and also on day
seven now we can go a little bit further
and before we actually run our circuit
here we can quickly check that our
understanding of this voltage drop
principle is correct by actually
directly measuring the voltage drop
across our our 220 Ohm resistor and
that'll verify that we've analyzed
things correctly so in order to do that
let's go ahead and
disconnect this photo resistor and set
it
aside so we'll set that photo resistor
aside we'll take our
multimeter and we'll hook it up as a
voltmeter to the two points on the high
side and on the low side of our 22 20
Ohm resistor so I'll go ahead and do
that right
now connecting using these two jumper
wires that just give us access to the
two sides of the 220 Ohm resistor right
there in our circuit so we'll go ahead
and turn this on to uh to volts and we
can see now that there will be a
difference in the voltage measured
across this resistor depending upon how
much light is reaching the photo
resistor so if I once again take my
black cloth and cover it up we can see
that the voltage across that resistor
drops to a very small level right now
we're on the molt scale so this is only
12 Mill volts so that's uh just a small
fraction of a volt so that agrees with
what we'd expect and if I remove the
cloth the voltage increases we're now up
to about a third of a volt about 300
molts and once again if I turn on my
flashlight and really illuminate that
photo resistor well you see I can get
the voltage up to over 1 and A2 volts at
this point so we can see that this is
acting about as we'd expect it to and in
fact that voltage that we're measuring
right now with the voltmeter is giving
us a measure of how bright the light is
that's falling on the photo
resistor all right let's go ahead then
and allow the hero to take over the job
of measuring this analog voltage for us
because that's really what the point of
today's project is so I will turn off
the
multimeter and we won't be needing it
anymore because the hero will be doing
all the measuring for us
and I'll go ahead and remove these
jumper wires just so that they're not
obscuring our view or confusing what's
going on here so we'll just get those
jumper wires out of the way so that now
all we really have in our circuit here
is what's essential for the hero to
measure our analog voltages now you'll
notice that we have connected to our
breadboard a blue wire that we haven't
yet discussed and that blue wire is
connected on the breadboard to the high
voltage side
of the 220 Ohm resistor so the voltage
between that blue wire and the black
wire ground is our measurement voltage
and you'll see that the blue wire is
connected to the hero up here in this
upper row of pins and it's connected to
analog input pin
a0 and you may recall that that is the
pin that we are programming in our
software sketch for day six this is an
analog input and the her interprets the
voltage that is measured on that analog
input pin and takes actions as
programmed in the sketch that we uh have
provided for this project so if we go
ahead and run the day six sketch which
we will do shortly we will anticipate
that the hero will be producing two
forms of user feedback for us one of
them is visible right here on hero
itself because the logic in our sketch
has been designed so that the builtin
LED on the hero will flash at a rate
that's determined by the intensity of
the light in fact the way our logic
works is that the LED will flash at a
faster rate the brighter the light is
and it'll flash at a at a more slow rate
if the light becomes dim now also we'll
be looking not only at what's happening
on the LED but we'll also be sending
information to the serial monitor screen
which is a part of the IDE that we use
to uh watch and control the hero and uh
look at the information that it's
providing so we'll be looking both at
the LED and we'll be looking at the
serial monitor as we go ahead and load
the sketch so at this point since we
think we understand what what this
circuit is doing we'll go ahead and move
over to the IDE and load the sketch and
see what we get so loading the sketch
now and we can see that we are getting
blinking of the LED here on on the uh on
the hero we're also seeing light value
figures reported over
here in the serial monitor screen now at
this point the uh hero is expecting us
to give it a low light intensity and a
highlight intensity so that it can scale
appropriately so we'll go ahead and do
that first thing we'll do is we'll cover
up the photo resistor to give it a dark
value so now you we can see that the
serial mon is reporting a light value of
one and it's giving a long delay so
there's a a long blinking now if I
uncover it we can see that the blinking
rate will go up a lot it's blinking
quite rapidly because it's reporting a
light value of 67 but we can make the
high limit even higher by shining this
flashlight on it and now we can see that
uh the high value is now corresponding
to something over 200
so now if I remove the light we can see
that the ambient light here now is is an
intermediate value and we can see that
the LED is blinking at an intermediate
rate but we now have what we were
looking for and that is uh feedback both
in the form of a flashing LED and
numbers on the serial monitor which
reflect a low light level with a slow
rate of
Flash and a high light
level with a more rapid rate of
flash you should make sure that you
understand this logic carefully study
the sketch and the wiring and make sure
that this makes sense and if you're
watching this video in support of day7
as well the circuit setup here will be
identical although the design of the
software sketch for day seven is a bit
more
complicated and it turns out that if we
run the day seven sketch we won't be
getting feedback on the hero LEDs
anymore but the sketch will be sending
more detailed information uh more
numbers on the serial monitor which will
simulate the uh display of a battery
charging circuit and so you'll want to
carefully study that sketch as well but
we'll defer further discussion of that
until the day seven
demonstration but for now good luck
right now in mastering this new device
that we've just
introduced once we've finished with days
six and day seven then we'll be ready to
introduce yet another new component that
we'll be able to interface with our hero
and uh get on to uh even bigger and
better things but until then good luck
and good inventing
job well done Explorer you've taken a
significant step towards survival today
the photo resistor is successfully
reading light levels meaning our battery
is now charging thus improving our power
and oxygen situation exponentially it's
impressive what a motivated human can
accomplish when faced with a little
adversity don't get too comfortable
however just because you've bought us
more time doesn't mean you can take a
break just yet while it's nice to
breathe without worry remember we're
still sitting under an ocean with a
multitude of broken systems on our hands
getting our spaceship back to the
surface and launching back into orbit is
still a Herculean task still today's
success should bring some optimism
tomorrow we'll gather some better
analytics of our charging rate by adding
some additional code to our sketch for
now power down and rest up you've earned
it explore until the next sunrise that
is bye for now
[Music]