[Music]
rise and shine Explorer day eight has
dawned upon us and has left us with no
time to waste today we're stepping up
our game we're going to add a dash of
color to your monotonous existence by
using a Nifty piece of Hardware called
an RGB L allow me to explain RGB LED
stands for red green blue light emitting
diode what this led does is allow us to
produce virtually any color on the
Spectrum by controlling the intensity of
the three colored diodes it's like your
own personal rainbow producer we're also
going to cover a new function today
analog WR it allows us to send an analog
output signal on a digital pin yes I
know what you're thinking didn't we just
discuss how digital and analog are
separate entities we sure did let me
however introduce you to the world of
pulse width modulation or pwm this Savvy
little trick allows us to fake an analog
output on a digital pin pretty neat
wouldn't you agree nonetheless that's
enough jabber for now rest assured all
this and more will be covered as the day
progresses brace yourself in Explorer
we've got colors to mix in a spaceship
to
fix an RGB LED is unlike your usual kind
of LED explos
it's like a three-in-one special inside
that tiny package you'll find three
separate LEDs one red one green and one
blue as these are the primary colors of
light in a regular LED you apply power
and it emits a pre-programmed specific
color in an RGB LED however you have the
ability to control each of the three
colors individually you can turn on the
red LED the green led the blue LED or
any combination of the three so why is
this exciting because by varying the
intensity of each of these colors you
have the power to create virtually any
color you want right at your fingertips
How Deeply thrilling need a soothing
aquamarine glow to relax easy want to
flash a warning and bright alarming red
ask and you shall receive in essence
with an RGB LED you're not just getting
one color you're getting the whole
Spectrum enjoy the possibilities
Explorer okay Explorer let's into two
intertwined Concepts analog right and
pulse width modulation or pwm which are
critical for controlling our RGB LED
analog right is a function in Arduino
that helps us generate pwm signals
despite its name oddly enough analog
right doesn't really deal with analog
signals it's a bit of a misnomer which
could be a source of confusion have no
fear Explorer it'll all piece together
soon enough moving on to pwm pulse width
modulation is a technique used to create
a kind of fake analog effect using
digital means by rapidly switching a
signal or power source on and off and
changing the proportion of the time it
is on versus the time it is off we can
vary the intensity of power that is
received this is important for our RGB
LED because it allows us to control the
intensity of each of the red green and
blue LEDs which in turn lets us mix our
colors imagine pwm is a fast flickering
light if it flickers so fast that your
eyes can't catch it turning on and off
the light will appear dimmer or brighter
based on the ratio of on time versus off
time if it's on more than it's off it
appears brighter if it's off more than
it's on it appears dimmer in terms of
our rgbl LED we'll use analog W to send
pwm signals to each of the red blue and
green LEDs by changing the duty cycle of
the pwm signal that's the on time we can
control the brightness of each led by
mixing different levels of brightness
across the red green and blue LEDs we
create the color we want you're in for
quite a treat Explorer the trajectory of
your future will soon become a lot
brighter quite
literally it appears we've talked the
talk now let's walk the walk Explorer
our task today is to light up our RGB
LED and give it a whirl remember with
pulse width modulation we can Tinker
with intensity of each color from a
meager zero to a dazzling
255 talk about a spectrum now one way to
control our RGB LED would be to
separately Define the red green and blue
values every single time we want to
change a color but frankly that's like
choosing to walk across the Galaxy when
you have a perfectly good spaceship it's
slow and it'll leave your code looking
like a debris field of supernova let's
be smarter shall we what do you say we
build a function to streamline the
process something catchy and memorable
like set RGB red level green level blue
level you'll see those three bite
variables nestled inside the parentheses
separated by commas these are parameters
and we'll be handing them over to our
function like instructions to a
well-trained robot Butler we don't have
a lot of memory so since max value
doesn't need to be anything higher than
255 anyway remember pulsewidth
modulation a bite is perfect since its
max value just so happens to be
255 using something like an integer for
an unsigned number less than or equal to
255 is just a waste of memory once we're
inside the function it's time to put
those parameters to work we'll use
analog WR to set the value for each of
our three color pins efficient and tidy
just the way I like it in our main loop
it's testing time we'll call our snazzy
new function in a variety of ways to
make sure our RGB LED isn't just sitting
there like a lump of plastic once we're
confident everything's Ship Shape we'll
beam it up to our board and enjoy the
show let's get to it Explorer lights
camera code now for what you've been
waiting oh so patiently for let's turn
to some instructional material that I
was able to gather cached on the
computer I've also added this to your
mission resources for future reference
see you
soon hello everybody and welcome back to
day eight of the code explanations for
the 30 days Lost in Space Adventure kit
today we're going to be introducing a
couple of new Concepts now that you have
an RGB LED hopefully wired up on your
breadboard today the concepts we're
going to be introducing are going to be
analog right and pulse with modulation
which allows us to give a variable
intensity over a pin and then we're also
going to be looking into a new idea
which is yesterday we learned about
functions and today we're going to be
learning about passing variables into
said functions and so with that let's
get started by first simply removing a
few of these extra comments so that it's
a little bit less daunting to look at
explicitly we included Arduino but again
since we're using the Arduino IDE if
this was removed it's not going to
affect anything so I'm just going to for
example sake completely delete it and
show you that it still works next we're
going to Define each of the pins on our
RGB LED now remember that the r it
stands for red G stands for green and b
stands for blue and all of these are
pulse withth modulation compatible
meaning if we send more intensity on
that line essentially sending More
Voltage onto it we're going to light
that red one either higher or lower so
we're going to get more red or less red
we're going to get more or less green
and we're going going to get more or
less blue the pins that we're going to
be using for this example are going to
be 11 10 and 9 please note however that
if you do change your pins you have to
be careful about it on the hero board
only pins 3 5 6 9 10 and 11 support
pulse with modulation which is indicated
on the board by proceeding those pins
with a till day character and only those
pins can support pulse with modulation
and use analog right if you try to use
any other pins they will not work
because those are digital pins and they
do not support pulse with modulation
once we're done defining our pin outs
we're going to go down and we're going
to define a set of constants to
represent four different brightness
levels for our RGB LED using pulse with
modulation pins and analog L right pulse
withs
modulation can set values ranging from
anywhere from0 to
255 which we will simply demonstrate by
adding 64 or approximately 1/4 of that
range to each preceding
value so we can start by saying that off
is essentially the equivalent of a value
of
zero then we can say that dim is maybe
something like 64 brighter is going to
be
64 plus dim which is 64 so this would be
about
128 so as you can see we're getting a
little bit higher and higher and higher
up until we reach 255 and we're going
about 1/4 each time so we have dim
brighter bright and
brightest and each time we just go a
little bit higher than the last
one next we have another constant down
below and this constant is simply just
going to say how long we want to to
display each color and we're going to
change this as a global variable so if
you ever want to change it in the future
we can change it in one spot instead of
a bazillion places down below so if we
wanted to change it to one second we can
add we can do that here or whatever but
I'm going to keep it 500 just for
example purposes now we're going to hop
down to setup and as you know setup is
pretty similar to every other day we're
just going to be simply setting all
these pins as outputs
and that's it we're not going to be
reading off a Serial monitor today
unless of course you want to for any
debugging purposes but for our purposes
we can remove that and we don't have to
worry about it for right
now then once setup is completed you
guessed it we go straight to Loop that
is simply how the Arduino language
works now before I get into everything
that's going on in Loop let me just tell
you a general gist of what this is doing
because I do need to explain one other
thing first right here we're simply
showing and we're just kind of rotating
through various colors and we're
rotating through them in a way that
allows us to turn red green and blue and
show off how pulse withth modulation
actually works that's kind of the point
of this program but you'll notice that
there's a function being called in a lot
of places called display color this is
not one that was built into the arino
IDE this is not one that is given to us
by default this is a function that we
actually have defined ourselves below
display color is a function that accepts
three parameters representing the
desired intensity for each of the LEDs
in the RGB LED so display color is a
very short-handed way of saying what
color we want to set it to by setting
the red intensity the green intensity
and the blue intensity that allows us to
display almost any color in
existence by simply having those three
at a certain variable and you can have
them anywhere from 0 to
255 the way that this is written is
exactly the same as yesterday we have a
void because it's not going to be
returning anything it's simply just
going to be executing display color and
in the difference is inside of these
parentheses we have parameters This Is A
New Concept for today we have parameters
and we have the red intensity the green
intensity and the blue intensity and
these can be anywhere from 0 to 255 and
they're separated by commas now I want
to reiterate that this can actually be
changed in terms of how this is written
the reason it was written on multiple
lines is simply because our ability or
our desire to add comments so that you
can understand what everything is going
on made it so so let's actually just
quickly go like this and I can show you
that you can actually do this all on one
line and personally if you wouldn't
weren't commenting everything I'd prefer
to all be on one line and here it's a
little bit cleaner so void display color
red comma green intensity comma blue
intensity so you need to have all of
these every single time you call this
function you need to send in three
parameters and that would be what you
want to said red green and blue to then
when it hops into the function we're
going to Simply do another function
called analog write I'm sure you've
heard of analog read well analog write
is the exact same is instead of reading
off of a pin we're going to be writing
to a pin but we're not going to be
writing whether it's on or off we're
going to be writing how on or how off we
want it to be in this case we're going
to be setting red to a number between 0
and 255 green to a number between 0 and
255 and blue to a number between 0 and
255 and we do this every time we display
the color now if we want to do that we
can go up here and we can show exactly
us doing that that let's first display
the color is off off and off this is
setting all three red green and blue to
0 0 0 this will turn our RGB LED
off we won't be displaying anything on
there at all next we're going to delay
by half a second which is what we've
defined up here as color delay then
we're going to set the red to dim and
we're going to keep green and blue off
then we're going to delay by that same
time and then we're going to set red to
brighter and again keep everything off
then we're going to delay send a little
bit more voltage to red and then we're
going to delay and send a little bit
more voltage on that red line right here
at the brightest where we displayed at
full intensity at the end the reason
we're doing this here is we're going to
be demonstrating how pulse withth
modulation can work you can send a whole
variety of different signals on the same
exact pin using analog right down here
and it can display a whole different
variety of different values this is
really really helpful in cases like this
where we want to have various versions
of red or maybe just some different
colors maybe you need more red and less
blue or more green and less red for
various different colors on the color
spectrum to help us display a whole
variety of colors next after we're done
showing off how pulse with modulation
Works using the red LED we're going to
display our other two LED colors at half
intensity we'll first flash on the green
LED and then we'll flash on the blue LED
so you can see that those are also there
and working finally we'll hop down to
show a bunch of various colors for
example you can display Yellow by mixing
Red and green LEDs bright bright you can
display cyan by mixing the green and
blue LEDs and keeping red off and then
you can also display magenta by doing
red and blue and of course keeping green
completely off finally we're going to if
we display Everything at Once bright
bright bright you'll get this color of
white and that's simply science and how
light works so with that we should have
a completed simulation of how pulse with
modulation Works using the RGB LED and
how you can set up whole variety of
different colors using just very very
simple amounts of code so with that that
should be about the end of our code
explanation for day eight I will see you
again
tomorrow welcome to the day eight wiring
example video in today's project we'll
introduce a new component and a new
programming method the new component is
a three color red green blue or RGB LED
and the new method that we'll use to
control it is called pulse width
modulation or pwm for short let's dive
into today's circuit and see how these
things actually work we have a
three-color LED right here just for us
to look at we have another one that's
actually plugged into the circuit on our
breadboard we can see just by looking at
it that the three-c color LED is
different from the conventional LEDs
that we've used so far the three-color
LED has four leads instead of two and
you'll notice that one of the leads is
longer than the others this one right
here is longer than the others and that
one long lead serves as the ground
connection for all three colors that are
incorporated into the RGB led the
remaining three shorter leads provide
the positive connections for the red
green and blue channels and you may
notice that this is actually a reversal
of our usual convention in which the
long lead of the LED is the positive one
well it's backwards here and we're just
going to have to get used to this
inconsistency as a matter of fact to
make things even worse sometimes you may
get a color LED in which the long Common
lead is positive rather than ground and
if you happen to get one of these
so-called common anode LEDs you'll need
to use an alternate circuit and sketch
design that reverses the direction of
current flow so that the LED will
function properly but for now we'll
focus on what we have here in our
circuit here we see that the LEDs three
positive leads are each fed by the hero
from a separate pin a separate digital
pin on the hero in this case we have our
three channels the red channel the green
Channel and the blue Channel fed by
these three pins right here blue is nine
green is 10
and red is
now one of our goals in this project
will be to control the relative
brightness of the three colors but at
first glance it would seem that using
digital output pins would be a bad
choice for this job since a digital
output is either on or off it's not an
analog output but it turns out that pins
9 10 and 11 are three of the special
output pins that can be programmed with
pulse width modulation that is they can
be programmed to rapidly pulse on and
off with the fraction of the time spent
on determining how bright the perceived
light is so for example if we programmed
the pulse width such that it was on half
the time and off half the time that
would give us a 50% brightness and so on
for other brightness levels now the rest
of our circuit here should be fairly
familiar To Us by now we have three 220
ohm current limiting resistors one for
each of the three color channels the red
green and blue and we also have a single
black wire right here which connects
from the ground pin of the led up to the
hero ground completing our circuit so um
this is all relatively straightforward
for us and so the next thing for us to
do is to run the day eight sketch to
demonstrate how these features work
together now before we actually run it
let's read through the sketch and see
what is expected to happen if we look
through the sketch we immediately see
that the loop function is repeatedly
Illuminating the three channels in a
specific
sequence first in the loop function we
see that only the red channels turned on
at
25% then after a time delay that is
increased to 50% on red followed then by
75% and then finally full illumination
or 100% on the red
Channel next in the sequence inside the
Li function we turn off the red Channel
and turn on the green at 50% so we'll
look for that following the green
illumination then we turn that off and
turn on Blue at 50% so we should expect
to see red followed by Green followed by
Blue next in the sequence we're going to
demonstrate the ability to produce other
colors by mixing different amounts of
RGB so in our next step in the sequence
we display Yellow by turning on red and
green at
50% after another
delay we next produce cyan with equal
amounts of green and blue and then we
produce magenta magenta is displayed
with a mix of red and blue channels on
our LED finally to conclude the loop
function we turn on all three LEDs
together at 100% and that should produce
a bright white light this sequence then
will repeat as the loop function runs
over and over as long as our sketch
continues to run so at this point since
we know what to expect let's go ahead
upload the sketch and watch to see that
uh the sequence is executed as we
expect for this demo I've set the color
delay time to, 1500 milliseconds or 1.5
seconds so hopefully that'll give us
enough time to be able to uh see all the
steps of the sequence as they
execute so uploading now we should look
for the red LED to come on there it is
dim brighter brighter yet and brightest
followed by Green there's our blue
there's yellow there's cyan there's
magenta and finally bright white
then the cycle just repeats over and
over again and so we can watch this go
through its cycle as often as we
want that just about covers all the new
ideas that we've introduced for today's
project but you might want to experiment
with some of the sketch parameters for
example you might want to see how good
you are at producing other colors or
produce different timing effects have
fun with this and next time we'll see
how to use our newly acquired knowledge
to further contribute to our repair
Mission well explor I must say I'm
impressed you've wired up the RGB LED
and successfully programmed it to show
different colors based on given values
your code is no longer a maze of
repeated color values it's streamlined
and efficient like the inner workings of
a cuttingedge spaceship and our hero
board is sparkling with colors just the
kind of bright glimmer of hope you need
in the depths of an Underwater World now
don't get too cozy in your success
tomorrow we'll take another momentous
Leap Forward I see a dashboard display
in our future it's time to start getting
some visual feedback from our various
ship systems on a display yes indeed
just because we're marooned in an alien
sea doesn't mean we can't have a bit of
style right so rest up Explorer we have
many more lines of code to write and
much more Hardware to Wrangle before our
ship can once again break free from the
watery prison but for now bask in the
glory of your multicolored Triumph
tomorrow
[Music]
awaits