welcome to day 15 the third creative Day
first of all I want to give you guys a
round of applause on making it halfway
through the course yes you guys are 50%
of the way through the 30 days loss of
space adventure kit congratulations I'm
making it halfway you've got only well
50% more to go I've decided to mix
today's creative day up a bit normally I
would give an easy and a hard example or
hard project but today I'm going to go
back to the lesson from day 14 I have a
wonderful project for you guys to work
on do you remember the bu validate pin
function from yesterday on day 14
currently there's a small security flaw
with it as soon as an incorrect button
is pressed it will exit the function and
return an error well that makes it
really easy now to guess which of the uh
numers that was pressed or which part of
the pin is wrong WR so you just can
guess 1 through n until it goes through
to the second pin and then you can know
okay so the first pin is in this case
four or whatever you want it to be and
then the second pin is up eror up error
up oh the second pin's six well that's
easy now so it makes it really easy to
brute force that makes it a pretty
insecure system even though we've added
in this additional security system so
what we want to make it do is instead we
should make it so it doesn't print an
error and till all four numbers are
typed in so they don't know which number
was bad of course you're also open to do
your own project if you so desire that
is totally absolutely always on the
table once you're done share on
inventor.
i/f with the hash creative
day15 I am once again looking forward to
seeing what you come up with and if you
rent any issues hit up your fellow
inventors in the Facebook group at
inventor. i/f
thank you
[Music]
guys