[Applause]
[Music]
rise and shine Explorer the cruel March
of time has ushered in yet another day
and our oxygen clock continues to tick
don't you just love the thrill of a life
or death situation first thing in the
morning today's topic of choice is LEDs
yes those delightful little lights that
we're going to employ to illuminate your
currently very dark and dank cabin we'll
be getting to know our humble breadboard
quite intimately today this remarkable
piece of technology will allow us to
construct a prototype circuit a
miniaturized version of your Ship's
Cabin lights as for our trusty herob
board we're going to use it to control
our led simulating the operation of the
cabin lights oh and one more thing today
the day we suit up and dive head first
first into the wonderful world of
programming we'll start with baby steps
don't worry I'll be virtually by your
side every step of the way providing my
usual blend of encouragement and biting
sarcasm all right Explorer let's begin
with a crash course in electronics 101
don't worry it'll be less painful than
the actual crash hopefully a breadboard
my we're diving right into the classic
era of DIY Electronics wonderful a
breadboard at its core is a rectangular
board with a bunch of holes in it it's a
sort of sandbox for electronics where
you can experiment with circuits without
any soldering it's perfect for testing
circuit designs and for well stranded
spaceship Pilots trying to keep their
craft from becoming their casket these
holes are not random they are highly
organized and connected in a specific
way the board is typically divided into
two sections the terminal strip and the
bus strip the terminal strip the large
larger section in the middle is
typically divided down the middle by a
ravine each side of this Ravine contains
Columns of interconnected holes these
are perfect for connecting components
like LEDs resistors and as you may have
guessed even your herob board the bus
strips run in rows along the top and
bottom edges of the breadboard these are
generally used for power supply
connections on most breadboards the red
line indicates a connection to our
positive voltage and the blue or black
ground you can plug your components and
wires into these holes to create
circuits because the holes are connected
electricity can flow from one component
to another just as it would on a
soldered circuit board the advantage of
a breadboard of course is that you can
reposition your components and wires
easily without having to desolder and
resolder connections ideal for
prototyping or in this case spacecraft
repair so what do you say explore are
you ready to Plug and Play not that you
have much of a choice to begin please
select an LED bulb from your repair kit
any color of your choosing an LED or
light emitting diode is like the bread
and butter of electronics they're simple
they're reliable and they emit light
which makes them visually captivating
and let's face it when you're stranded
underwater in a strange unfamiliar
treacherous alien world anything that
emits light is bound to lift the spirits
right or attract
predators in technical terms an LED is a
type of diode that emits light when an
electric current passes through it in
One Direction it allows the current to
flow and it emits light in the opposite
direction it blocks the current that's
why it's called a diode D meaning two
and OD meaning path two paths one for
current to flow and one to block it all
diodes including LEDs have a positive
side called the anode and a negative
side called the cathode
usually the longer lead is the anode and
the shorter lead is the cathode if the
leads have been trimmed you can also
identify the anode and cathode by the
flat Edge on the side of the LED's bulb
the flat Edge indicates the cathode LEDs
are used in a multitude of applications
due to their low energy consumption long
lifespan small size and low heat
production in your current predicament
we'll be using them to Blink signals and
illuminate your cabin it's important to
remember that LEDs do however need a
resistor in series to limit the current
passing through them or they might burn
out my purpose is to ensure that you see
the light at the end of the tunnel
Explorer but you won't get there with
burnt out LEDs which brings us to the
final piece of equipment for today a
resistor is the unsung hero of
electronics a critically thinking mind
would rightfully assume that they do
what their name suggests they resist
more specifically they resist the flow
of electric current you could think of
them as traffic control for
electrons just like a narrow road slows
down the traffic a resistor slows down
the flow of electricity the amount of
resistance is measured in units called
ohms symbolized by the Greek letter
Omega the higher the ohm value the more
it resists the current resistors come in
different shapes and sizes but the ones
you're most likely to encounter have two
wires or leads and a series of colored
bands these colors aren't for Aesthetics
my oxygen dependent friend they function
as a code that communicates the resistor
value in ohms in your situation we'll
use a 220 Ohm resistor to ensure that we
don't fry your LEDs and plunge you back
into darkness I suspect that you wish
you'd paid more attention to Oh's law
during training wait they never taught
you 's law I must say explore how
fortunate you are to have me if you wish
to learn more about that I've added the
resources to your mission resources tab
you can view VI it now that's the end of
today's Hardware lesson remember explore
knowledge is power in this case it's
electric power and currently you lack
both who needs a captive audience when
you crack yourself up ah now that you've
mastered the intricacies of LEDs
resistors and the venerable breadboard I
think it's time to step into the digital
realm don't you agree enough of the
circuits and solder let's dive into a
univers constructed purely from logic a
universe of ones and zeros a universe
that would feel like home to me if my
programming allowed me to well feel our
next task involves turning our hardware
setup into a functional lighting system
and to do that we're going to need to
talk about code fear not for though this
universe may seem complex and
intimidating it abides by a set of rules
and structures as precise as any
hardware component and I'm here to guide
you through it ready to swap your
multimeter for a keyboard let's dive
into the world of programming or dip our
toes in at least moving on to another
Cornerstone of programming variables a
variable in programming is like a small
box where you can store information you
give this box a unique name and fill it
with a specific type of information and
then you can use that information by
referring to the Box's name it's like
labeling your food in the refrigerator
so no one else eats your leftover pizza
variables can store different types of
information in C++ the language you're
currently wrestling with we have
different variable types for different
kinds of
information it's a bit like having
different types of storage containers
for different types of food you wouldn't
store your cereal in a water bottle
would you one such type is an integer
often abbreviated as int an integer can
store whole numbers both positive and
negative such as 1 5 -42 or zero the
syntax to declare an integer variable in
your code looks like
this here int is the data type my
variable is the variable name and 10 is
the value that we're storing in the
variable the equal sign is how we assign
a value to a variable now every time we
use my variable in our code it
represents the value 10 variable names
cannot start with a number contain
spaces or use any characters like dollar
signs or hashtags keep in mind the name
my variable is up to you you could name
it spacecat or oxygen level or number of
aliens I've met the important thing is
that the name should be meaningful in
the context of your program the point is
variables help us write flexible and
reusable code you'll see when we need to
pull out our dip switch tomorrow we'll
be using this variable to denote the pin
of our LED I suppose you can name this
variable anything your creative human
mind wishes to but let's not get carried
away something like light one or cabin
lights should do the trick it gives an
air of professionalism and Clarity next
we'll need to make some changes to our
digital WR functions in the setup
instead of hardcoding the pin number
we'll now be using this Sumptuous new
variable we just created see we're being
resourceful and efficient this is the
kind of stuff that Will Keep Us Alive
down here explor
since it seemed to help you out
yesterday let's cut to some
instructional material that I was able
to gather cached on the computer I've
again added this to your mission
resources for future
reference now let's take a look at the
code that we'll be using to control our
hero board the first sketch that we'll
be using has very little actual code but
that's because our first sketch our
engineer David has added a lot of extra
comments to explain each feature of the
Arduino language when we use it for the
first time the first thing we'll discuss
is something that doesn't affect our
running code at all but serves a very
important part of any computer program
those are comments as you can see here
we have a lot of comments in the code
now it looks really daunting it looks
really long but guess what if you just
grab all those and you hit delete on
them your code is going to work the
exact same the only thing that all this
grade out code is for is for you and
other Developers who want to read the
code later to see exactly what you're
doing think of it as just jotting down
some notes so that when you come back to
it later on you can actually know what
the heck you wrote way back when now
there are two different types of
comments depending on whether the
comment is either a single line or
whether the comment spans multiple lines
so let's explain those first the
multi-line comment begins with a special
two character sequence consisting of a
slash character immediately follow
followed by an aster with no space
between them in our sketch we can see
those two characters at the very
beginning of our sketch those characters
and any text following them is totally
ignored by the IDE until the multi-line
comment is ended with the closing
sequence consisting of the reverse of
the starting sequence so you start it
with a slash asri and you end it with an
asct slash with no spaces on top of that
to make these comments more readable art
developer has started each line with an
asct as well just to mention that this
isn't the same block of comments but
there is no need to do this it's just to
format it to make the comment look nice
in this very first block comment we give
some information about our sketch and
each sketch in our course will have
similar comments that you can identify
and know exactly what it is the Arduino
ID provides a nice trick for hiding
longer comments after we've read them if
you move your mouse between the line
number and the first character of the
line you can see a special down pointer
Arrow appear on the line where the
multi-line comment begins when I click
that down pointer the Arduino IDE will
hide the comment and any blank lines
that follow and the pointer will point
to the right we can do that for all of
these comments and then you'll notice
that our code gets a lot more simple see
now isn't this just a tiny bit less
daunting we've included a lot of
comments in these sketches but you're
free to look at them as you'd like but
I'm going to be collapsing most of them
for the video section now here's a
coding secret for you programmers almost
never write all the code that they use
we depend on mountains of code written
by other programmers and made available
for our use in order to use this code we
include it in our sketches by adding it
above to do so we can do the pound
include and then tell which header file
we want to include functions from
another thing I should mention is that
I've added it in this case but the
Arduino IDE automatically includes a
file called
Arduino for you so if I were to go here
and totally erase
Arduino and the include thing at the top
it would work the exact same the Arduino
ID adds this in for us so we don't have
to ourselves again the only reason we
have it up here is just to remind us
that that code is automatically being
included just like we saw with the LED
builtin name the ardino ID gives us the
ability to give names for values we use
in our sketches a common way to do this
is to use pound Define since this is a
variable that will not change our
engineer has put the variable names in
all caps that's just his way of
signifying that something is not going
to be changing as you can see other
variables in later sketches will use a
combination of capital letters and
lowercase letters since this is not
going to be a changing value since it's
on a specific pin we're simply L
mentioning it using all capital letters
in this sketch we'll create a constant
for the pin that will control our lights
and our Lander since our lights are
external to the herob board we can't use
the built-in LED so we'll wire pin 12 to
our external LED on our breadboard that
represents our cabin lights and then set
the cabin lights pin define statement to
pin 12 the wonderful part about having
defined statements is that instead of
putting 12 in
down here in setup and everywhere that
it's mentioned you can have a variable
that makes a little bit more sense cabin
lights pin cabin lights pin and cabin
lights pin otherwise you just have a
random 12 and it would be harder one to
read and two to bug fix in case anything
ever went wrong now we're finally ready
to execute some code if you remember
from your onboard ship AI explanation
setup is called once when our sketch
begins executing and is typically used
to do onetime initialization in the
setup function we configure our cabin
lights pin as an output since we're
outputting a current on to the lights to
turn it on or off a pin on a herob board
can be used for either an input or
output and we use pin mode to let the
hero know which way the pin will be used
it is important to configure each pin in
your sketch using pin mode before it is
used and these pin mode commands are
typically found in the setup function
how do we know what par ERS to use for
these statements and in what order
should they occur the Arduino ID has
another neat quick to quickly remind you
how each function works in the Arduino
IDE you can simply hover your mouse
pointer over something like pin mode and
a popup will appear this pop-up shows
the name of the function at the top the
next piece of information is what value
if any is returned by the function in
this case the pin mode function does not
return anything indicated by the word
void the popup then shows the parameters
expected for each character we can see
what data type the parameter is
expecting followed by the name the
function will use for this value if your
value is of a different data type it can
often be converted automatically which
is the case in this occasion with our
define statement in the pin mode command
we use our cabin lights pin con and we
defined order for that PIN number right
now we're not putting cabin lights pin
we're putting the number 12 so remember
that when you find it everywhere you put
it it's actually as as far as the
computer cares all of these are just 12
if you want to see everywhere that this
variable is used you can simply use the
Arduino IDE double click it and it
should highlight everywhere that it is
currently inside of the code now you
might be wondering where all of these
things are being defined like where is
output why is this here where is this
actually being defined where is pin mode
where is this function I don't see this
function how are you getting
these random variables high low output
pin mode delay setup Loop where are
these written I don't understand and
that's a good question I want you to
remember that in the
Arduino Library it includes a lot of
necessary functionality that you will
need in order to run code on your hero
board instead of rewriting and
recreating the entire wheel um they've
given you all the necessary resources so
instead of writing everything for
turning on and setting a PIN to go on to
high you can just simply use a function
and make your life a lot easier after
setup is completed and our pin mode is
set as an output we will then go down to
the loop function where we will be
executing the code inside of this
bracket and this bracket until the end
of time over and over and over and over
and over again and those functions that
we're going to be calling are as follows
starting on the very first line and
going sequentially down we will first
start by turning the LED on right now
after this is done executing the LED on
our breadboard will be bright lit up and
glowing very very bright then we will
delay for 1 second Arduino gives us a
fancy way of doing that by having a
delay function with a parameter of how
many milliseconds you want to pause the
program for in this case 1,000
milliseconds is 1 second the other
function that we just had previously is
called digital right digital right
simply turn sets a pin as either High
which is equivalent to on or one or low
which is the opposite that it can be set
to which is zero or off so if you say
digital right and you want to set that
PIN to be high that means you're going
to send a 5 vol signal onto in this case
pin 12 thereby turning the light on if
you were to say low instead you'd be
sending ground thereby on to pin 12
thereby turning it off and that's
exactly what we do after 1 second of
delaying we're going to jump and we're
going to turn what was already on we're
going to turn it off now we have another
delay here so let me ask you this
question why do we have this delay well
remember that Loop goes back over and
over over and over and over again and it
replays the same code over and over if
we didn't have this delay here there
would be an error what would that error
be it would be that it would look as if
the LED had never actually turned off
and the reason why that is is because
even though the herob board is an
overall a fairly low powered device it
is actually very very quick and very
powerful after if this line of code was
not here it would immediately jump to
the beginning of Loop and and then set
it back to high again and it would do it
so quickly that you wouldn't even be
able to notice that it was turning off
by adding a delay here we give it a
moment so that we can actually notice
that it's been turned off and then after
it executes this it's going to jump like
you guessed right back to beginning Loop
and turn it back on with this code if we
hit upload we should be able to see the
board blinking on and off and on and off
just like it did with our onboard LED
except this time we're doing it as an
output as we progress to the course our
engineer will use longer comments when a
new feature is introduced features that
have been previously described in detail
we'll still get comments but they'll be
much shorter to help you understand how
the command is used in each sketch thank
you
guys welcome to this wiring example
video for the day two project what we'll
be trying to do in these example videos
is provide you with some Hands-On tips
and instructions s which might be
helpful particularly if you haven't
worked extensively with circuits before
we'll try to point out ideas and
recommended practices for constructing
and organizing your circuits as they
grow and become increasingly complex
over the days ahead today's example will
be very simple and basic but before we
jump into it let's just say a few words
about our
workstation generally speaking we'll
assembling our analog circuit components
on this white plastic
breadboard the internal electrical
connections along the numbered Columns
of the middle part of the breadboard
provide a convenient framework for
quickly connecting components to each
other and by using jumper wires like
this connecting to our hero digital
controller which is up here above
and the use of a breadboard makes it
easy to modify and experiment with our
circuits and change them around in a way
that we couldn't easily if we connected
them permanently Say by soldering your
hero and breadboard may just be sitting
on your desk or workbench next to your
computer and that's fine in my case I've
made a 3D printed holder for them that
keeps things neatly in place and will be
helpful for organization later on as our
projects get more complex and the
breadboard gets more crowded you should
feel free to use your own Ingenuity to
create a working environment that's
effective for you now first off let's
connect our hero to the computer with
the USB
cable here we go this provides our
project with power as well as allowing
the hero to receive instructions through
the code that we'll be writing for it
now let's turn our attention here to the
breadboard our first task today is going
to be to Simply turn on an LED or light
emitting diode that's what this
component is right here to do this we
need to construct a complete electrical
circuit that sends the right amount of
current in the correct direction through
through this
led the hero is able to provide a
voltage of plus 5 volts and it also
provides a Zer volts or ground level on
the corresponding labeled pins you'll
see that there's a five volt pin up here
in the upper row on the hero and there's
also a ground pin down here Below on the
on the hero now naturally current will
flow from five volts to ground that is
from high to low if we were to connect a
wire between them however we don't want
to do that because if we did that the
current level that would flow would be
very high and probably damaging to our
devices this is what's called a short
circuit in order to limit the current to
a safe level we must include a resistor
in the circuit this is an example right
here of a resist resistor in this case
our resistor has a value of 220 ohms 220
ohms 5 Vols divided by 220 ohms using
ohms law yields a current flow of
023 amp or in other words 23
milliamps which turns out to be a safe
amount of current for the LED that we're
using the LED actually does off offers
some resistance to current flow on its
own but it can be dangerously easy to
provide too much current to an LED and
burn it out and so this is why we'll
always pair our LEDs in series with a
limiting resistor which will more or
less guarantee that the LED current
can't exceed the maximum allowed by the
limit resistor now in fact this
discussion isn't exclusive just to LEDs
anytime we have current in a circuit
driven by a fixed voltage we will make
it a strict practice to always include
current limiting resistors to keep all
currents within appropriate safe limits
looking at our LED we see that it is
particular about the direction of
current flow required to turn electrical
energy into light you see that there's a
long lead here on the left and a short
lead on the right the long lead of the
LED should be connected to the positive
or high voltage side of the circuit in
order to function correctly so then the
the current flow would be in through the
long lead and out through the short lead
and so we'll construct our circuit to
make sure that that's the case at this
point we are ready to assemble our
circuit and we will be using a very
important convention throughout our
projects and that is we'll use a red
wire here to denote the fixed high or
5vt Supply and we'll use a black wire
here to denote the Zer volts or ground
connection of our circuit so I should
point out of course that the colors of
the wires really have no bearing on how
they function but getting used to using
a consistent practice in labeling our
circuit and in in using colors will help
us later on when things start to get
more complex and harder to follow it
will be very helpful if we adhere to
this kind of a
convention so let's Trace through our
our simple circuit from the 5vt
connection that we'll get from the red
wire will go from 5 volts across this
connection on the breadboard to this 220
Ohm resistor the 220 Ohm resistor
bridges over the Gap here in the
breadboard so that we can connect
something to the lower end of the
resistor on this other side so we're
going to go ahead and connect the high
side that is the positive side of the
LED to that column that connects
to the resistor as we've plannned that
means that in the adjoining column to
the right here the low side or the
negative side of the LED is now
connected in that vertical column to
this black wire and the black wire
connects back to the hero ground pin and
so we will have a complete circuit from
positive to negative from 5 volts to
ground once we go ahead and complete the
connection of this red wire to 5 volts
so let's go ahead and connect it and
what we would expect to see is the light
come on SO connecting it up there we go
it works so that's gratifying but this
isn't really quite all that we want to
accomplish today the hero is really much
more than just a power supply for us it
has the ability to control the voltage
on its various pins in accordance with
the coding instructions that we send it
when we write a sketch so we will
connect the positive side of our LED not
to the 5vt pin on the hero but instead
we're going to connect it to pin 12 pin
12 is located down here in the lower row
on the hero as we have it mounted here
this is the pin that we have programmed
our sketch to control and so that's why
we're going to connect it up to pin 12
it's tempting at this point to just go
ahead and take our red wire and use that
to connect over here to pin 12 but that
really wouldn't conform with our
practice of using red wires only for the
fixed 5vt Supply so we're going to be uh
a little bit more careful about things
here so I'm going to disconnect the red
wire and actually remove it and instead
I'm going to use a different colored
wire in this case I'll use an orange
wire and I'm going to make the
connection between the positive
side of our of our LED and the current
limiting resistor and over here to pin
12 so that's pin 12 right there we'll
plug it
in okay and we see that at the moment
there is no activity on the LED and
that's as expected but now we'll upload
the code for day two that we um have
written and we'll upload that to the
hero so so I go over to
the
console and I upload the code take just
a second to do
that and voila so we've just taken our
first small step towards being able to
control an electronic system using the
capabilities of the hero you should
experiment with this and make sure that
you understand the concepts and uh how
we've accomplished this and very soon
we'll be moving ahead to bigger
[Music]
things