[Music]
rise and shine Explorer today the day
we've been working towards we're finally
ready to ascend from the ocean depths
and glide our spaceship back up to the
watery surface I hope you're as thrilled
as I am the past few weeks have been a
test of your courage determination and
your ability to think on your feet and I
must say you've handled every challenge
with intelligence and tenacity you're
proving to be a true Explorer in every
sense but remember there is still much
work to be done today we will put
everything we've learned to the ultimate
test all of your wiring coating and
problem solving skills are going to play
a crucial part in our Endeavor today so
take a deep breath clear your mind and
prepare yourself today you're more than
an Explorer and an engineer you're a
brave Starship Commander navigating
tenaciously through the unknown strap in
Explorer it's going to be a thrilling
ride are you
ready it appears we're all set to make
our careful Ascent back up to the water
surface it's critical we do this
gradually to prevent our shuttle from
popping like a balloon under the change
and pressure do you recall our trusty
sidekick the passive buzzer I'd suggest
we reintroduce him into our circuit as
an additional safety measure he'll be
our alarm Bell warning us if we're
ascending too quickly don't fret I've
got you covered with all the guidance
you'll need conveniently located in your
mission resources and guess what they're
ready for playback right now beginning
playback hello everybody and welcome
back to day 19 of the 30 days loss in
space adventure kit code explanations
now a lot of this code that we put in is
from day 18 I'm not going to be going
over that code
from day 18 so what we can do we can
simplify a lot of this by removing a lot
tough comments and going down and
explaining what's already known
obviously we have these functions at the
bottom nothing's changed there we have a
lot of new functionality inside of our
Loop but besides
that there's actually not a whole lot of
new things this is all the same from
setup from yesterday I could actually
just go
ploop close that up not necessary we
also have the constant bite done but
we've also got nope and then we also
have a new one for today called hold and
as you can guess it works the exact same
way as the other two so I'm just going
to close that down and that's going to
be another one that we can show off
later on once we show off our code we
have the keys make sure you have these
in here if you don't it will not work
same as up
above the only new thing that we have up
above for this entire top part is we
have the constant bite buzzer pin is
going to be equal to
10 today we're going to be introducing a
buzzer so that we can have additional
alert sounds whenever we hit certain
depths so that we know not to rise too
quickly back up to the
surface now what we can do is we can
actually instead of using those
variables like we had yesterday we can
actually use percentages so we know that
we're going to have to stop at about 50%
of the way and 75% of the way so we want
to alert the user when we have risen to
50 and 75% of the way up so instead of
before we had -20 and -40 we're going to
be using this instead this is the same
we also have a constant unsigned int
Loop delay equals 200 which is 200
milliseconds that we're going to add as
a small little buffer for our interrupts
between the loop
executions inside of the loop we have
the following static in previous depth
is equal to initial depth and this is
just going to give us our depth from our
previous Loop now if there was a change
obviously this is similar same thing as
yesterday if there was a change in the
depth level meaning you turn that rotary
encoder at some amount and resist us at
least a little bit probably just one if
there was any change in that we're going
to go through this
Loop grabbing the current depth just
like yesterday and then we're going to
compute our
percentage of the way up now yesterday
we were saying what the depth level was
but instead we're going to give us a
percentage from zero to 100 in order to
calculate that we can take the current
depth time 100 divided by the initial
depth and do 100 minus that entire total
that will give us the percentage of the
way to the surface that we've gone so
far now Rising too quickly could stress
the whole of our Lander because of this
we will play an alert if the Lander is
instructed to rise faster than one meter
every time through our Loop we need to
be sure that we're not going too quickly
so let's just say you went through the
loop and you spun it really quick and so
you went from one to four all that one
second hey we're going to have a buzzer
pin go off that tells us that we need to
chill out for just a minute you're going
a little too fast this is the same logic
as before which simply just says if the
current depth is less than the initial
depth don't try going down because Mr
wise guy we then have the the function
to show that number whatever the depth
is on our s segment
display and then we finally have the
same thing as before if we've hit the
very first 50% Mark or the 75% Mark of
our way up to the surface we want to
display our depth is a little blink on
the display and finally we're going to
display done assuming that it's you make
it all the way up to the surface the
only thing that we're doing here we're
going to play a little Tada tune on our
buzzer that's that there and that's the
only new feature that's being added that
we haven't already had from yesterday
and with that that is now the end of day
19 I wish you the best of luck today on
the way up to the ocean surface light
speed welcome to the day 19 wiring
example video well the big day has
finally arrived D all of our designing
testing and practicing has been leading
up to this crucial step in getting home
raising our craft to the ocean
surface based on the day 18 project we
now have a design that adds an audio
warning buzzer to the encoder and
display systems that we've previously
worked out looking at our breadboard we
can see that the only Hardware change
from day
18 is this buzzer right here and we can
see that the buzzer is connected to the
hero at output pin 10 so pin 10 should
be the pin in our sketch that drives the
buzzer function and so you can check
that and make sure that that's the case
and you'll also see that our buzzer has
to have a ground connection and we're
just using the same Common Ground bus
connection right here on the bottom side
of our breadboard that's already being
used by the encoder and the display the
really substantial changes
today mostly involve the software
sketch last time when we were simulating
and practicing we could afford to make
mistakes and then just go back and try
again until we got it right but this
time we'll need to be extra careful not
to irreversibly damage our crafts Drive
systems and Hull and hopefully get it
right on the first try because of this
the importance of this particular day
project our sketch has warning logic
built in that is intended to alert us
both audibly and Visually if we are
ascending too fast and it will also tell
us when there are planned pause points
in the ascent that we've reached now
I'll go ahead and run my simulation of
the real thing so that as you're
watching you'll know just what to expect
when it's go time for your run to the
surface so let's go ahead load up the
sketch and see how it goes so I'm going
over to the IDE
now loading up the uh the sketch in just
a moment we should be
running and there we are okay so our
sketch is running and our display is
indicating that we are currently at a
depth of 60 M and we've got to get up to
the surface when our uh depth meter
reaches zero so if everything's ready to
go let's go ahead put our hands on the
controls and see what happens so as I
start to rotate the encoder you can see
that I'm decreasing the the depth I'm
rising up in other words and if I go a
little too fast I get my my fingers
slapped a little bit because going up
too fast is putting too much stress on
my
drive okay that was too
fast still going
up okay I've reached a hold Point all
right so I I've reached a hold point I
was still going a little fast there
because you can see I overshot the hold
point if I wanted to I could go back
down a little bit but let's keep going
up and see what happens as I okay that
was too
fast and anytime now there I've reached
another hold point at 15 M okay after
pausing at the hold Point let's keep
rising up up
up and we should be close enough to the
surface now oh that was too fast we're
almost there 5 4 3 2
1 and we did it we've reached the
surface so of course that was just a
simulation of what you're going to do
for real but it's just as simple as that
so I wish you good luck and we will see
you top side after you've made your way
out of the depths and then you'll be
ready to prepare for the next part of
the journey home see you
then okay Explorer the time has come all
our preparations have led us to this
point our Ascent out of the murky deep
and back to the surface of this
Uncharted ocean we will slowly ascend
from our current depth at altitude zero
to the ocean surface of altitude 100 the
key word is slowly we must proceed
cautiously to prevent an explosion which
will surely put a hasty end to our
journey on my mark Explorer start
turning the rotary encoder and let's
begin our Ascent to the surface slow and
steady
engage all system status clear keeping
tabs on gyroscopic thrusters pressure
values well within acceptable limits
steady on
Explorer 50% slow your rooll Explorer
the ship's pressure is reaching its
limits we need to stop for a moment
occupy your mind with thoughts of the
world Beyond this frighteningly vast
ocean a world filled with more
breathable air and fewer leviathans
pressure is within optimal levels please
continue to turn our encoder and
continue the
ascent 75% you're three4 to the top
Explorer but don't lose your patience
halt your dial turning for another few
moments we're almost there sensors
indicate light is coming through much
more clearly now okay pressure dropping
Crank That encoder
Cadet you've done it Explorer you've
reached the ocean
surface I'm an awe Explorer what an
extraordinary achievement today we've
navigated our way from the murky depth
to the Magnificent spectacle of a sky
teeming with distant Stars
the view is simply mesmerizing isn't it
our Collective efforts have truly paid
off and look at that the communications
with the Mother Ship have stabilized I
can almost feel the stream of signals
pulsating through the system each beep
echoing the missed inquiries from
headquarters they must be on tenter
hooks awaiting an update from you eager
to hear that you're safe and sound it's
time to let them in on our Victory to
share the wave of hope that's been
washing over us take a moment relish
this feeling and then let's send a
reassuring Beacon back home oh I could
just leap with joy Explorer what a day
what a Triumph light speed to you and
remember every Star in the cosmos is a
destination waiting to be
[Music]
explored