[Music]
wakey wakey Explorer the dawn of day
three is upon us and as much as I'd love
to let you Slumber in peace we have an
Ocean's depth of work to tackle do you
recall our incessantly blinking LED from
yesterday well today we're going to show
those painstaking glimmers of light
who's boss enter the dip switch this
Nifty little piece of Hardware will
allow us to control the blinking at our
will it's going to be the Relentless
leash of our overzealous LED of course
to make this happen we're going to need
more than just some physical wiring this
is where things get cerebral we're going
to be introducing some conditional logic
into our code a touch of if this then
that all right then a flashy switch and
some smart code are on our Horizon rest
assured by the end of the day we'll have
our blinking light under control so
whenever you're ready explorer though
regardless of your Readiness we must
begin right let's not dilly dally our
main character today is the dip switch
this fellow might look simple with its
array of tiny switches but oh can it
wield a great deal of power you see dip
stands for dual inline package it's
essentially a ual electric switch that's
packaged with others in a group the
switches are all housed in a single box
and can be toggled on or off
independently you may think of this like
a tiny panel of light switches each
controlling a separate room in a
miniature
dollhouse each position of the
individual switches in a dip switch
represents a binary condition which
simply means either on or off high or
low one or zero yes or no the magic lies
in the fact that you can manipulate
these switches to control different
parts of a
circuit in our case the part of the
circuit we're so Keen to dominate is
that perpetually blinking
LED by the end of today that led will be
blinking only when we want it to the
power of control is within our grasp
Explorer so let's grab
it allow me to introduce some vital
elements the ground or gnd D and voltage
or VCC they are you could say the
lifeblood and nervous system of our
Electronics ground my friend is the
common point of reference for all
voltage sources in a circuit it's our
zero voltage reference line the
foundation on which all other voltages
are built without it our circuits would
be aimlessly wandering in the wild
uncertain about where the bottom of the
voltage range lies it also provides a
path for our electric currents to return
to their Source after their exciting
journey through our circuits now let's
talk about VCC this little gem is the
primary source of power to our heroboard
it stands for voltage at the common
collector in plain language it's the
positive Supply voltage if gnd D is the
foundation then VCC is the engine that
powers the machine the fuel that keeps
the circuits alive and kicking you see
in a system like ours having a common
ground such as gnd and a common power
supply such as VCC is essential it
allows different components of the
system to communicate effectively each
understanding what the zero and full
points of voltage are this way when
signals or power move between different
parts of the system they all understand
the language of voltage in the same way
it's like our own language really if we
didn't have common reference points and
shared meanings we'd be unable to
communicate and collaborate and we know
that wouldn't end well would it
Explorer moving on the the extra
resistor a keen Observer aren't you
Explorer you see the extra resistor
we're talking about is what we call a
pull down resistor its job is to make
sure our circuit behaves properly when
the switch is off without it our switch
being in the off position could cause
our circuit to get all wonky imagine it
like a crowd of electricity not knowing
where to go and causing a ruckus we
certainly don't need more chaos around
here what the pull down resistor does is
finish the circuit and acts like a form
of crowd control when the switch is off
it guides the confused electricity
safely away down to the ground this way
our circuit stays composed and organized
just the way we like it remember
Explorer every brick in a building plays
a vital role in keeping it standing
similarly every small component in a
system is crucial to its overall
functionality and success now let's
return to our task at
hand now that we've solved the mystery
of the pul down resistor let's turn our
attention to something absolutely
fundamental in electronics the concept
of inputs and outputs think of our
system as a living organism it needs to
inhale data inputs to process and exhale
data outputs as a result an input is
essentially a message received by our
herob board it could be from a sensor a
button or in our case today a dip switch
these inputs tell the board what's
happening out in the world in this
instance whether our dip switch is on or
off or high or
low on the other hand outputs are
signals sent out by the herob board
outputs could be triggered by code
conditions or other sensor readings like
the position of a switch examples
include spinning a motor sounding a
buzzer or making an LED blink or stay
solid today our dip switch is the input
telling the board whether the switch is
on or high or off or low the LED is the
output responding to this input by
either blinking or staying
off ah great we're done playing with our
hardware for now Explorer don't look so
relieved the fun is far from over you
already know what's next programming our
newly created circuit so grab another
gulp of that precious oxygen and brace
yourself for a thrilling journey into
the intricacies of code let's power
through explore the sooner we do this
the sooner you can get some lights on in
here and stop groping around in the
dark well Explorer you've stumbled upon
a fairly straightforward piece of code
here let's dissect it together shall
we first we're defining two variables
one for our LED and one for our dip
switch these numbers are currently
configured to represent the PIN numbers
on the hero board where your switch and
led are connected in the setup function
we're telling the hero board how to
treat the two pins we defined earlier
the pin mode parenthesis function is
used for this we will make the LED an
output meaning we want to send out a
signal from this pin to control the LED
we will make the dip switch an input
meaning we expect to receive a signal
from the switch to this
pin next we move to the loop function
the heart of our hero code that as you
know runs continuously and repeatedly
inside loop we have a new kind of
statement an if statement I can see from
the look on your face that Cadet
training never taught you about
conditional logic humans are such
ineffectual creatures all right time for
a bit of theory fear not explore it
won't
bite conditional logic involves creating
rules within your code based on certain
conditions much like deciding to wear a
space suit before you step out into the
vacuum of space simple would you agree
the main tools for this in C+ plus
language are if else if and else
statements let's break them down if this
is the primary decision making tool in
your code if a certain condition is true
then some code will run for example if
oxygen levels are less than critical we
initiate emergency procedures this only
happens if the condition is true if the
oxygen levels are measured to be fine
the code within the if statement is
ignored else if this comes into play
when you have more than one condition to
check it's like saying if the first
condition isn't true and doesn't apply
we'll evaluate the next one it's
important to note that an else if always
follows an if or another else if else
this is the last resort if none of the
previous if or else if conditions are
true then the code in the else block
will run it's like saying if nothing
else works out let's do this here's a
quick
example you'll notice that we always
indent everything inside sets of curly
brackets this simply allows for better
readability of the code in this code the
ship checks the oxygen level and
responds appropriately based on the
conditions we've set I hope this brings
some light into the murky depths of
conditional Logic for you let's see if
we can apply this to our switch
situation next when the switch is on
digital right is executed turning the
LED on or high as you could say this
sends current to the LED if the switch
is off the else block is executed
instead here digital right is run which
grounds the LED's circuit turning it off
so this code is continuously checking
the state of your switch and turning the
LED on or off accordingly quite easy
don't you think now let's try this out
on your end
Explorer oh my I'll give you credit you
have a Keen Eye good on you for noticing
that you stumbled upon one of the
classic conundrums of programming
Explorer the taale of two equals they
might look similar but they have
different roles in the programming
Universe let's clear up the confusion
shall we in programming a single equal
sign is known as the assignment operator
it's used when you want to assign a
value to a variable think of it as the
word is in English for example int my
variable equals 10 semicolon is like
saying my variable is 10 now a double
equal sign is a complet completely
different Beast this is the equality
operator and it's used to compare two
values to see if they're equal if they
are the comparison returns true if
they're not it returns false this is
used a lot in conditional statements
like if statements here's an
example so remember one equal sign is
for assignment and double equal sign is
for comparison it's crucial not to mix
these up trust me it'll save you a lot
of headache in the future ah it seems to
be that time where we cut to the
instructional material I was able to
gather cast on the computer like the
exceptional AI that I am I've also added
this to your mission resources for
future
reference welcome back Explorer so far
we've only used our heroboard to blink
our onboard LED and as of yesterday
we've also added the breadboard LED to
Blink on and off however um this doesn't
really show us all of the capabilities
of what our hero can do in fact it only
really scratches the surface not to
mention a light that is always on is
always going to be draining power even
when we're asleep and that can't be good
for your battery levels one of the
largest strengths of a computer is the
ability to examine inputs make decisions
and then modify the outputs based on
those decisions each of the pins on our
hero can not only produce outputs they
can also be used as inputs allowing the
hero to read the current condition on a
pin I want you to think of the herob
board as a mini computer which it
technically actually is and realize how
it compares to the computer that you're
using right now right now you're using a
keyboard and a mouse as inputs or
potentially depending on what kind of
device you're using potentially it might
be a touchscreen or similar as an input
device on your computer when you click
something or you type something in and
press enter that information is sent as
an input into your computer your
computer then does the exact same thing
I mentioned before makes some
calculations and then outputs the
calculations on the screen using your
graphics display drivers and you will
visually be able to see them on your
monitor your monitor is an output device
your keyboard and your mouse are input
devices and you can think of your
computer is the equivalent of our herob
board however in the case of a heroboard
we're going to be simplifying this
instead of complex Mouse movements and
large operating system calc calculations
we'll be just be using a simple switch
if a switch is on and you flip the
switch on you can think of that as
pressing a button on a keyboard the hero
or the computer is going to then
calculate that it needs to do something
and then it's going to send as an output
onto another pin in this case it's going
to be the LED and then turn it on so
tldr our sketch today will use another
hero pin as an input to detect whether
our switch is set to on or off once we
read if it's supposed to be on or off
we're going to turn the light on or off
let's start by opening the sketch for
day three as with all of our sketches
the first multi-line comment just gives
a lot of information about the sketch
and if you are worried about it and it
looks daunting poop you can close it
just like that down below is a few
additional Concepts that are going to be
taught in this lesson we're going to be
learning about the if statement the else
control structure comparison operators
and digital read as well as we're just
going to talk a little bit about dip
switches and resistors and if that's
daunting to you too many words don't
scared of it close it up you don't have
to worry about it I should also mention
that there is a few more comment blocks
throughout here if you just want to go
here close close close once you've
collapsed all the comments if you so
desire you want to what you can do now
is you can include the
uo. which contains all the convenient
definitions for our selected board in
this case we have selected the Arduino
Uno as that was compatible with our hero
board if you don't want to include this
and you're using the Arduino IDE which
is what I'm going to be using in this
example you can technically hit delete
and if you were to do something like
that then you don't have to worry it
will include it automatically so if you
don't have it that's fine as long as
you're using the uino IDE otherwise feel
free to keep it it doesn't hurt anything
anyway
just as in our day two sketch we then
need to define a constant to refer to
the pin attached to our LED in this case
we're going to be naming it cabin lights
pin and we're going to connect it in our
case to pin 12 on our hero board then
we're going to have another one that
we're going to be defining and it's
going to be the PIN for the switch the
input device the cabin lights switch pin
and we're going to connect that to the
switch pin on pin two
for our onetime setup this is where this
is only run once we need to set up each
of the pins to use as either an input or
an output as you recall the lights the
LED in this case is going to be an
output and the switch is going to be an
input so here's a switch that we're
going to have that's going to be the
input talk to the herob board and then
it's going to calculate and determine
that we need to then turn off the LED on
pin in this case 12 is an output after
setup is run we will jump immediately to
loop as the Arduino IDE and program
language automatically does for us so we
will jump into the loop function and in
here we have a few different versions
and this is where we have commented out
because we wanted to show you
iteratively how we got to this here this
here is the commented out we won't be
using it the first version of our Loop
it works but it could be shorter more
efficient and more understandable we
commented it out just to show you how we
can incrementally improve our
code here we have the bite switch
setting which is just simply going to
save if it is on or off into a variable
name if first we're going to say that
the switch setting is equal to whatever
we read off of the digital read on the
cabin lights switch pin and this is
where we can read the state of light and
we're going to save it into a variable
digital read is a function that quite
literally does exactly as it says it
reads the digital signal off of a
specific pin and in this case we're
going to be saving that whatever it
returns into a variable
here so if it is turned on it should be
a one and if it is turned in the off
position it will have a zero
that is all that this function does it
just simply determines is it reading A1
or is it reading a zero is there
something being read on the pen or is
there
not and so when we save that to this
here it will either have a one or a zero
so let's just say if the switch setting
is equal to high or in this case that's
equal to one meaning that it's turned
on if the switch if the switch is in the
on position then we want to digital
right to the LED High basically turning
it
on what digital right is doing here as
we explained yesterday is it's simply
sending a 5vt signal if it's high onto
the pin or it's sending a ground signal
if you set it to low which is exactly
what we do here if on the other case it
reads a signal on the pin and it the
signal was low then we want to set the
then we want to set it down to
low that's the first way we can do it an
improved version that is slightly better
is we can remove an extra statement up
here and we can actually add an if El
statement so instead of using two if
statements we can actually use an if
else so we have bite switch setting
equals digital read cabin lights switch
pin this is the exact same as we were
doing before just a little bit on
condensed into one more line if the
switch setting is equal to
high then we can turn it on and then
else you'll notice there's no else
switch setting equal equal low because
the only other condition it could be if
it's not high in a digital setting is
it's only can be low so we can actually
remove that and simplify it ever so
slightly here and even then with the if
El statement
Boop we can actually ignore that as well
because there's actually technically a
final version and this is the one where
we're going to be using because it's
probably the most simple way that we can
Implement what was above we can
literally have it as just one if El
statement if digital read cabin lights
switch pin is equal to
high and in this case we're not using an
additional variable because there's no
reason to have an extra variable that's
saved in memory if digital read cabin
lights switch pin is equal to high then
we're going to turn it on to high
otherwise if it's
not high then we're going to going to
turn it to low and we're going to keep
the light off and this is probably the
most simple form of what we can get from
the above so with this you should have
all the code that is needed for day
three with this new functionality you
should be able to turn on and off the
LED on your ship with only the time that
you need it so that you're not wasting
any battery in your critical condition
that you are currently in best of luck
and we'll see you again on day four
welcome to the wiring example video for
day three last time we saw how to use
the Hero controller to raise the voltage
on an output pin in order to turn on an
LED today we want to build further on
that idea with the aim of being able to
turn the light on and off at will
without needing to reload the software
sketch the key to this is that in
addition to using pin 12 12 as an output
from the hero we will use pin two of the
hero as an
input according to the coding that we've
provided in our sketch when pin two
reads a high say or 5V potential or when
it reads Low that is Zer volts the hero
takes different actions on the output
pin
12 there are two new points for us to
understand here on the digital side the
hero is repeatedly executing code in the
loop routine and every time the loop is
executed pin 12 is repeatedly tested and
the status of pin 12 may or may not be
changed the second point for us to to
think about has to do with how we are
going to provide a selectable high or
low voltage state to pin 2 now in order
to do this we've set up a small circuit
on the left side here of our breadboard
that runs from 5
Vols through an onoff switch which is
this red component right here then
through a high value resistor in this
case the resistor has a value of 10,000
ohms or 10 kiloohms which will limit the
current flowing through it to less than
a milliamp and then finally back to
ground to complete the circuit a quick
note this switch is called a dip switch
dip is an acronym for dual inline
package and this is a new component for
us this is actually three switches in
one package uh but we'll only be using
one switch number one the one on the
left in today's project although in
future projects will'll have occasion to
use more than just one now reiterate
ating our 5 volts is supplied to one
side of the dip switch through this red
wire that's connected to 5 volts on the
hero now the switch in turn is connected
to the high side of our 10 kilohm
resistor and then that finally completes
the uh circuit back to ground at the end
now let's understand how this is
actually going to work if the switch is
in the on
position then current will flow through
the circuit and through our resistor the
amount of current will be small but it
will be an amount of current
commensurate with a 5V potential
difference between ground and this upper
side of the
resistor if we
connect this point at the upper side of
the resistor using this brown jumper
wire if we connect it to pin two on the
hero pin two will now read a high a 5vt
high reading if current is flowing
through the
circuit on the other hand if we were to
throw this switch into the off position
breaking the circuit then no current
would be flowing through and according
to Ohm's law there would be no voltage
difference across the resistor between
its ground side and its upper side so
both of those would be at zero volts and
in that condition pin two connected by
this brown wire to this point in the
circuit would read a low so this is how
by flipping the switch between on and
off we can toggle the voltage at Pin two
between being high and low now I I want
to make a quick note here before we move
on our selection here to use a brown
wire was completely arbitrary depending
upon what colors you have available in
your parts kit you might choose to use a
different color apart from trying to
adhere to the rule of using red for
positive Supply and black for ground you
should feel free to use any combination
of Jumper wire colors that best help you
organize and understand your circuits
there's Just One Last Detail to mention
here before we go ahead and test this
new circuit because we have more than
one current Loop operating on our
breadboard here we have need for more
than one set of supply and ground
connections and this is a situation
that'll happen quite frequently and
rather than providing separate
connections for our two Loops here our
two
subcircuits will'll set up shared common
lines or buses that can be tapped by any
subcircuit on the breadboard that needs
to you'll notice that the two rows along
the top side and also along the bottom
side of the breadboard are labeled with
red and blue lines and they're special
because they are connected
horizontally all the way across rather
than vertically like the columns in the
main part of the
breadboard and since they do connect
horizontally all the way across they
provide uh convenient access to any
components that may need to access them
from the main part of the breadboard
notice that in this case we've really
only used the blue bus right here on the
top side of the breadboard and we've
used that to distribute ground to our
two subcircuits so what we have right
now is a black wire connected from hero
ground to one end of this ground bus and
then we have two places where it's being
used where it's being tapped off so we
have a black wire connecting from this
ground line to the lower end the low
side of our LED so this is the ground
side of the LED and we're also using the
same ground line right here to connect
to the bottom side the low voltage side
of our logic resistor that's being used
to provide a signal to go to pin 2 so
finally we're ready to go ahead and test
our day three circuit now now we're
starting right now with switch one in
the off position and so we'll upload our
software sketch and it'll start to run
but we would expect nothing to happen
until we move the switch from open to
close so let's go ahead and do that
we'll go ahead go over to the console
and upload the day3 script so it's
loading all right the script is loaded
now and it's running and we don't see
any change of status until we go ahead
and move the switch from open to close
and so what we'd expect to happen when
we do that is that pin two will go high
the hero will detect that and turn pin
12 High to light the yell so let's go
ahead and give that a try moving the
switch to close and that works as
expected and realize now that because
the program is constantly polling pin
2's status over and over again we can
turn it on and off as often as we like
so I can turn the switch to off and the
LED goes off and it will
respond to any changes in the status of
pin
2 so this uh all appears to be working
correctly and this is just another small
step but we're making significant
progress next time we'll build even
further on this and get even more
complex control over our lighting
[Music]
circuits