[Music]
ah welcome my Intrepid Explorer to the
grand finale of week one or as some
might call it day four I must confess
you've perform surprisingly well for a
human that is today we're going to add a
touch more complexity and a Dash more
Brilliance to your drowning NightLight
we're fixing the storage room and
cockpit lights so you won't have to
grope around like a lost mle rat any
longer we're still under an ocean you're
getting cold and the night is dark and
full of
scampy we have a problem yes another one
the hydroponic system that filters your
breathable atmosphere needs more light
to photosynthesize soak up your bad
breath and turn it into O2 we need to
get the rest of these dip switch
circuits operating before whatever out
there starts looking at us like a can of
spaghetti first things first the
hardware notice how we've added a couple
of LEDs and some extra wires for our dip
switch don't start flipping switches
just yet though without proper
instructions in your code they'll just
stare back at you with the cold lifeless
gaze of purposeless tech and that brings
us to our code our all important guide
to technological obedience we're
defining six new variables that will
tell us which pins are pulling their
weight in the circuit
in the setup function we'll use the pin
mode function to designate switches as
inputs and LEDs as outputs finally we'll
March into the loop function and create
three if statements our conditional
Knights and shining armor they'll relay
the status of the three dip switches so
my Brave Explorer are you ready to turn
our ship bright enough to lure all
manner of prey and predators in this
unexplored ocean I know I'm excited too
once you finished wiring upload your new
code to the hero and let there be light
you know the drill let's turn to some
instructional material I was able to
gather cast on the computer and you
guessed it I've also added this to your
mission resources for future reference
I'll see you
soon hello and welcome back to day four
of the 30 days Lost in Space Adventure
kit yesterday we were able to
successfully connect one of our lights
to an LED using the dip switch module
however we still have it seems two more
lights within the ship that need to be
controlled with on and off in order to
fully fix all the lighting in our
spacecraft So today we're going to be
taking what we did yesterday and we're
just going to be adding on additional
Logic for the additional lights that we
had from yesterday most of the logic
that we have is pretty similar to what
we have done in previous days from
yesterday we're just kind of doing it
for a couple more pins and a couple more
LED outputs so that's all we're going to
do today starting off let's do what we
normally do we have all these comments
if they're daunting you can feel free to
close them down and you don't have to
look at them now you'll notice that
there's one other thing that we've done
as well if we scroll down to where we
usually Define our pinouts today I'm
going to be showing you another way to
do the exact same thing and this is the
way that we're going to be doing it
going forward in the past in previous
days we used a pound define statement to
share what pins we are going to be using
for our inputs and outputs at the top of
our code this is a good way to do it um
this is the way that a lot of code has
been using it for a lot of time at this
point however the way that that is done
is currently depreciated in the the
Arduino IDE in the Arduino programming
language what this means depreciation in
code means that it is currently not best
practice to continue using it it means
that they're no longer going to be
supporting that method of doing
something and in this case the pound
Define has been depreciated it still
works it doesn't seem like it will break
in any time shape or form in a long long
time however if you hover over type
Alias bite which is a
uint8 type you can Define the pins using
a constant meaning it's not going to
change bite which is a data type of type
uint 8or T and we can say that this is
going to be 10 so here's the old way of
doing it and here's the way that we're
going to be doing it going forward if
you still want to do pound defines you
can and it will work however for good
programming sake we're going to be using
using the non- depreciated method which
is going to be using bytes which is of
Type U int 8or T you're wondering what
the heck that is don't worry too much
about it it's simply a data type of what
you would think would be 8 Bits And the
reason why it we want to use a bite of
this is because if you go to pin mode
and you go into this function here and
you hover over it you'll see that the
input it wants is of type uint 8 _ t pin
and you int 8or T
mode what that means is we're simply
just giving this function when it calls
it what it wants so there's no confusion
with the compiler it doesn't have to do
any unnecessary conversions and Etc so
if you use Define I believe it does the
exact same thing and there should be no
issues but just for to keep for
depreciation sake we're gonna be going
forward and so if you see const bite and
then whatever pin we're defining up at
the top of our code in future videos you
can think of it as the exact same thing
functionality wise is doing a pound
defined statement now with that out of
the way let's go out of let's make sure
that we close all these extra comment
blocks just to make sure that there's no
additional confusion we also have at the
top the included libraries if you're
using the Arduino ID and you just
accidentally happen to erase that
nothing will change as the AR we know
IDE automatically adds that anyway but
it's good just to have it anyway so you
know that it's being added automatically
if we go down here we can go to our very
first line of code and the very first
bit of code that we have is defining our
pinouts now instead of using the pound
Define we're going to be doing const
bite cabin lights pin is equal to 10 and
now we have two additional ones for each
of the extra two lights we have the
lights for our storage Bay and our
cockpit light lights so we have constant
constant simply means that it is exactly
that it is constant it will not change
if you try to change this variable let's
just say you go down to the loop and you
want to write something like storage
lights pin equals storage lights pin
plus one and you want to add one to it
essentially trying to make it 12 or
whatever this constant will throw out an
error and it will say hey buddy you
can't do that it's a constant it's got
to stay the same
by putting constant it just enforces and
makes sure that this is not going to
change and we don't want it to because
this is how we're wiring it up down here
below once we go down to the dip switch
pins the first pin on the dip switch the
second pin on the dip switch and the
third pin on the dip switch and we're
wiring it to pin two 3 and four
respectively you'll notice that this is
very very much the same we've just added
this here for the extra two switches and
we've added these here too for the extra
two lights you'll notice the same same
is going down for the most of the code
Below in the setup we simply say that
the cabin lights are going to be an
output the storage lights are going to
be an output and now the cockpit lights
are also going to be an output we just
added two more outputs down here and
then we have the following we have cabin
lights is going to be the input on the
dip switch and then we just added the
simple um storage light and cockpit
lights is going to be the additional
inputs for the extra two pins that we're
going to be wiring up today if you go
down to void Loop you'll notice that we
have remember the exact same code as
yesterday but instead of written once
it's written three times so if the first
switch is in the on position then we
want to turn that corresponding light on
else we want to keep it off same exact
scenario for the second pin and same
same exact scenario for the third pin
and with that we have the finished code
for day four simply taking what we did
yesterday and writing it a couple extra
times for the extra pins and that's
about
it welcome to the wiring example video
for day four today we'll be expanding on
what we built on day three using mostly
the same ideas but increasing our
capability to be able to handle three
independent lighting circuits since we
are pretty closely repeating what we did
last time there's not a lot that is new
to explain
as before our breadboard contains two
separate circuit areas that are used to
handle on the leand side the hero input
and on the right hand side the LED
output functions the difference here
being that now each of these two areas
now includes three separate channels
rather than just one we can see that on
the input side here on the left we are
now using all three channels of the dip
switch
module we also now have a common 5V bus
that is being used along the the lower
red line here being used to supply 5
volts to each of the three channels of
the dip switch each of those channels
feeds through to its respective 10
kilohm limit resistor here before each
of those resistors then connects to a
Common Ground
bus supplied by this black wire from the
hero each of those three channels in
addition to feeding through the 10
kiloohm resistor connects with a
separate wire to each of the input pins
on the hero so now we have three of
these signal wires a brown wire a white
wire and a yellow wire which in turn
connect to pins 2 3 and four as those
are the pins specified as input in our
software
sketch switching over to the output side
we now have three output LEDs a red a
blue and a green and those will be
controlled by our three switches 1 two
and
three each LED is connected on its low
side to this common ground bus that we
provided and we're using uh on the on
the input side we can see that there are
three black jumper wires connected from
ground to the low side of our three
LEDs finally our red blue and green LEDs
are
connected to each of the three output
pins on the hero so we have an orange
wire connected here to the red LED we
have a blue wire connected on its
positive side on the positive side of
the LED also to the hero and finally a
green wire and those are connected to
pins 10 11 and 12 also consistent with
what's in our software sketch so that
pretty much completes our setup for the
day three circuit so let's go ahead and
upload the sketch and try it out
so we'll load the
sketch and now that the sketch is loaded
it should be running we have all of the
switches in the off position right now
so we wouldn't expect to see anything so
we'll go ahead and we'll uh put switch
one into the on position and sure enough
just as we had expected from day three
the red LED comes on but now I can have
any combination of the three switches on
or off so for example I could put switch
three into on and get green to come on
or I can have all three of them on
together or I can turn number one off
and so on so as you play around with
this you'll be able to confirm that the
logic in our software sketch and the
wiring that we've put together here with
the hero and our breadboard uh agree
with one another and have the desired
functionality so uh that's all for
today's
exploration next after we take a day off
for our creative activity we'll be
returning on day six to introduce a new
type of sensor component into our
repertoire and so we'll see you
then ah you're back that was barely
enough time to even begin missing you
well congratulations dear Explorer on
Surviving in the first week of your
unanticipated yet thoroughly avoidable
Sea Adventure you've turned this sunken
wreck from a murky cave into a well-lit
tin can you're proving quite resourceful
for an oxygen breather Bravo or whatever
it is your kind
says now that you have your lights it
seems that I can see into your storage
Bay with Newfound Clarity my sensors are
picking up a solar array that was
previously hidden in the murkiness I
must admit I didn't notice it earlier
but then again was darker than the
depths of a super massive black hole in
there let's hold on to that glimmer of
hope the hydroponic system is getting up
to speed and I've altered the
resistances on the new lights so wiring
up an LED doesn't turn this ship into
the largest underwater Fireball in
history rest up Explorer you've done
some great work and it looks like we're
out of immediate
[Music]
damage