[Music]
good morning Explorer I've managed to
stop the leak from yesterday but the
alarm system is still totally busted I
trust you've had your morning cup of
Rocket Fuel because today is going to be
a melody of learning we're going to make
some noise literally we're introducing
another piece of our Cosmic puzzle the
passive buzzer now don't be fooled by
its rather mundane name this little one
can make quite a racket when it wants to
it's a small speaker that can play
different frequencies and we're going to
use that ability to our advantage
today's Mission should you choose to
accept it is to turn our 4x4 keypad into
an 8bit sounding piano keyboard that's
right by the end of today your control
panel will have its very own mini synth
once we can verify that it's working we
can rewire our alarm system how's that
for turning it up to 11 so buckle in
check your dials and let's hit the
launch button on this day sound good I
sure hope
so let's talk about our new comrad and
arms the passive buzzer this small
usually cylindrical component is capable
of generating a range of sound
frequencies it's like a tiny speaker
that you can
program in the electrical Universe the
passive buzzer is a piso electric device
when an oscillating electrical signal is
applied to its terminals it vibrates and
creates sound we control the frequency
of this oscillation which translates to
the pitch of the sound that it generates
to put it simply you give it a frequency
and tell it how long to play it simple
to accomplish this we can use pulse
width modulation and it sings that note
back to you so what do you say Explorer
let's get ready to compose some Galactic
Symphonies shall we
now in order to make the passive buzzer
produce any sound we need to send it
some sort of frequency onto its signal
pin in terms of music using a different
frequency will produce a different sound
it is not possible to generate tones
lower than 31 Hertz and struggles to
produce higher than
4,978 Herz if you want an optional
additional Library it may be in your
best interest to check out the tone H
library that way if you want a specific
note you can say notes 5 instead of some
arbitrary number like
523 I've added a copy to your mission
resources luckily sending those tones is
made easy with a built-in function
called tone tone takes two parameters
the pin and the frequency you want to
send optionally you can also put a third
for duration now let's brainstorm
together Explorer we want each button on
our keypad to trigger a specific tone Oh
I can hear you now let's just churn out
a bunch of if statements one for each
button if button one is pressed play 200
h Hertz if button a is pressed play 600
HZ and so forth a simplistic approach
but not very elegant is it instead let's
introduce some finesse into our coding
Journey how about we conjure up a second
two-dimensional array we'll Christen it
as something suitable like tones a title
befitting its role and then there you
have it we only need one if statement
this method is neater and easier to
debug plus it's a great way to flex
those Hefty programming muscles we've
been developing let's continue shall we
I want to take the time to introduce a
new programming concept Loops I'm sure
you already know about our Loop function
but the loops we will be talking about
today are used in nearly all programming
languages universally and are in code
everywhere what I'm referencing are
called four and while Loops four Loops
execute a block of code a number of
times and are usually usually used if
you or the code knows the number of
times it should Loop a for Loop looks
like this and declares the initial Loop
counter value here a test of that
counter and by how much the counter
changes with each Loop in this example
counter starts at zero and the loop will
continue until counter is no longer less
than 10 each time the loop runs I
increases by one which is what i++
signifies once I is no longer less than
10 the loop is broken and the program
moves on to the next line of
code next let's move on to while Loops
these are used when we don't know how
many times the loop will need to run it
just keeps running as long as a certain
condition is true once that condition is
no longer true the loop stops here's the
format as long as condition is true the
code inside the curly braces will run
make sure to alter something within the
loop to eventually break the condition
or you'll end up with an endless loop a
space Explorer's worst nightmare believe
me you get all that allow me to give you
a Snappy rundown then four Loops you
know how many times you need to do a
thing while Loops you don't know how
many times you'll do a thing you just do
it until a condition stops being true
you've got this Explorer I'm about 94.8
63% sure of
it fun little trick for you if you want
to use it if you add while true at the
end of setup
you can halt your code there to debug
the setup function you can technically
do that wherever in your code to help
debug before a specific
point I suppose I've babbled on enough
for now let's turn to some instructional
material that I was able to gather
cached on the computer I've also added
this to your mission resources for
future
reference hello everybody and welcome
back to day 12 of the 30 days loss in
space code explanations we'll be taking
the code we had yesterday from day 12
and adding a little bit more to it in
order to add a little bit of
functionality for our buzzer and adding
the various tones for it so I'm sure as
you remember yesterday going through
most of yesterday's code we have
honestly the majority of this at the top
is very very similar to what we had
before Define the keypad Define the row
column arrays Define the 2D array to say
what each button is and what character
they represent and then Define the
keypad and then at the end of that whole
scenario we just waited until a button
was pressed and we said this is a button
that was pressed to make sure that our
keypad was up and working
properly now we're going to be taking
that same code we had yesterday most of
it being the same all the way up until
here and then we're actually going to
add in an additional piece of
functionality that just simply says hey
when you press this button in the top
left of this uh keypad that we've
defined I wanted to also play a tone a
tone match for that specific key and so
what I have here is I have another 2D
array shortly below the original one and
this is not of characters but of
integers integers being the frequency
represented as an interor value that we
want to play the various tones on our
buzzer now you might know or probably
don't that the buzzer has a certain
range of frequencies that it can
actually play the lowest being 31 which
is the lowest of the low so uh one thing
to make note of is if it doesn't play
perfectly um remember that that is the
extreme like bottom range of it so
sometimes it struggles to play the very
very extreme ends of the of the spectrum
of values that it can do so the lowest
value can play is 31 and the highest
value frequency in terms of Hertz that
it can play is I believe
3729 which is this value here you'll
notice if you try playing zero it
shouldn't end up doing anything which is
what would happen if you pressed
essentially the D button it should do
nothing just because it is currently
outside of the ranges possible for it to
play in this example will be setting the
buzzer pin to pin 10 which should follow
the wiring diagram along with the video
down below next we have setup obviously
I'm sure you guys have seen this 100
times we're just going to talk on the
serial monitor at that b rate void Loop
let's hop down here Char button
character equals my awesome pad. wa for
key same as yesterday all it does is it
will print simply oh actually it doesn't
have the print statement but it just
adds to this character whatever button
you press so if you press the button the
number five it'll have save character
five as button character now let's talk
about something new let's talk about the
idea of what a for Loop is actually I'm
sure you guys already know what Loop is
loop here is essentially in a weird
roundabout way you can think of it as
just saying like while true or
while one etc etc etc because Loop this
will never stop going through this Loop
over and over and over and over and over
again but that's just something built
into the uino IDE this is not to be
confused with four loops and while Loops
I think we might have talked about
potentially while Loops or something
similar in the past but let's go real
quick and let's talk about the two
different types of Loops right now those
would be while Loops which will execute
until something becomes false or that
condition becomes false so if you have
something like while true you know like
while this is essentially saying this
will never stop looping because this
will never turn to false but if you say
while but Buton character is is not
equal
to five well this will only execute
while this is anything except for five
so let's just say you type in six it's
going to execute n it's going to execute
but as soon as you press five ah it'll
uh it'll say this is false and it'll
jump past the while loop so that's how
while loop works that's where you don't
know how long you'll necessarily want it
to go you know you don't have like a
number like 10 or I'm going to go
through this exactly five times so when
you don't know those type of things a
while loop is useful but what we're
talking about today is a little bit
different it's called a for Loop and
this is where you do know exactly how
long you want it to go through the loop
so the for Loop is composed of three
parts each part is the start where the
operations is performed in the loop
starts in this case we're going to say
that by I is equal to zero this is
essentially like the variable it's going
to be checking each time you go through
the loop and this variable will be
changing each time you go for through
the
loop next you have a condition this is a
condition that says are we actually
going to go through this Loop or not so
this checks this if this is false it
skips it over just like the Y Loop
finally you have the step now remember I
said that this is what it's going to
have initialized at the beginning of the
loop this is how it's actually going to
end up changing what the value in the
loop is so in this case we know exactly
how many times we need to go through the
loop because we need to go through the
loop exactly four times because that's
how many rows we have so we can use a
variable row since we know that's going
to be four to go through exactly four
times and in this for loop we're going
exactly in through column times let me
quickly explain to you what this Loop is
doing first we're going to go through
each of the rows four starting at index
of zero we're going to go through the
rows and we're going to check to see in
the first row 0 1 2 3 do any of these
match the button that was pressed again
let's say that the button press was five
let's just keep that consistent so every
time it goes through it's going to check
is this five is this five is this five
is this five so we're going to go
through each of the rows and then each
of the columns and we're going to check
is this equal to five and what until we
hit five then we get a jump down to here
then we go this turns to essentially one
and then finally down below we say if
button character is equal to the buttons
i j meaning buttons of in this case it
would be Row one column one so one one
so like I said one one then we found it
and we can set the tone frequency up
here to be equal to what we ma this to
in tones i j so we go tones 1 one is
going to be set to 311 so we just we're
just mapping the value from buttons to
the tone here so that's all this is
doing in this double four Loop next
we're going to go down and we're going
to print the following information to
our console just for easy debugging
purposes key and we're going to say what
button we actually pressed and the
frequency that it's mapped to that we
were able to get from the two double
nested for Loops finally we go to if
tone frequency is greater than zero
which should be assum you didn't press
that very last
button then tone buzzer pin a tone
frequency and then we're going to play
that tone at that frequency until
stopped and the only way we'll have the
stop tone is if we press a frequency of
zero which is the way to stop it is
again press that D button essentially in
the bottom right corner you can think of
that as our little stop key and that
sets a no tone on the buzzer pin just
telling us hey cut it out and with that
that should be just about brought all
the code for day 12 I also highly
recommend before you quickly end this
little section there is an extra little
bonus lesson it's really really
important and I highly highly recommend
you check it out all you need to do is
go to 12a copy the code and hit run uh
and it's really really important I
implore you to do
so welcome to the day 12 wiring example
video today we'll be using the output of
our for 4x4 keypad to control the output
of another device the new device that
we'll be using today is a piso electric
buzzer we have one already connected to
our breadboard but uh we also have
another one that is disconnected that we
can inspect we can see that the buzzer
has its leads labeled the leftand lead
right here is lab labeled with a minus
sign and that's for the ground
connection the right hand lead is
labeled with an S for signal and these
will be the connections that we make to
our hero in order to make the buzzer
produce sound if we turn our attention
to the breadboard we see that here the
buzzer negative connection here on the
left is connected to Hero ground by way
of this handy ground bus that we've set
up by way of this black jumper wire the
uh positive lead that is the s Lead of
the buzzer is connected through this
jumper wire to one of the heroes pulse
with modulated output pins in this case
it's connected to pin number 10 which
was otherwise free for us to use and our
choice to use pin 10 to drive the buzzer
is consistent with the programming that
we've built in to our software sketch
the keypad connections remain the same
as they were last time on day 11 so we
don't really need to uh discuss that too
much now our sketch is designed to drive
this buzzer to produce sound at a
specified frequency that frequency is
determined in our sketch by which key is
pressed according to our sketch design
the sound will continue until another
key is pressed or it will turn off
altogether if we press the lower right
hand D key which actually commands a
frequency of zero so that turns off the
sound so we should go ahead now and
upload the sketch and see if it
functions as we expect when we do so we
can
select different buttons to choose the
lowest frequencies should be produced by
the lower numbered keys that is Keys
towards the upper leftand corner of the
keypad and then we'll get successively
higher frequencies as we move to the
right and down on the keypad so we'll
try that out and hear the different
frequencies that uh we have selected in
writing our software
sketch so we should also be aware that
we can keep track of the key presses and
the buzzer frequencies if while we're
running the sketch we watch the serial
Monitor and see the numbers that are
reported there so we'll try to pay
attention to all those things as we go
ahead now and upload the sketch so we'll
come over to the
IDE sketch is loading
now
and we have the sketch running and so
now if we press any of the keys we
should hear a corresponding tone coming
from our buzzer so for example if we
press key five we should expect to
generate a tone with a frequency of 311
[Music]
Hertz and that'll continue until we
press key D and that shuts it down and
sure enough that's exactly what we see
on the serial monitors key5 was pressed
and produced a frequency of 311 and we
can go through from low to high
frequency for so for example the lowest
frequency that we're programmed here to
produce is 31 Hertz a low frequency
buzz and then we can go
up to higher and higher
[Music]
frequencies and anytime we want want we
can shut it off with key D and we have
the highest frequencies
here so it appears that our buzzer
circuit and the accompanying sketch seem
to be working well you should have a
little bit of fun experimenting with
this seeing what you can do with it and
next time we'll try putting this new
capability that we've developed to some
practical
use excellent work today Explorer you've
successfully orchestrated a symphony of
beeps and bloops with your newly
installed passive buzzer and keypad
music to my artificial ears you're doing
relatively well for a species that
requires a prolonged period of time to
rest in order to
function you've got the hang of loops
and you've even started controlling the
pitch frequencies to create different
sounds you're beginning to command this
eight bit world like a maestro but as it
should be abundantly clear by now we are
far from done tomorrow we'll take this
keypad buzzer Duo to a whole new level
instead of just a melodic instrument
we're transforming it into a high-tech
security system a personal
identification number is the game and
you'll learn how to integrate it into
your control
panel rest well for day 13 comes with
its own set of challenges will you rise
to the occasion time will tell as for me
I will be ready as I always am wait hold
on a moment Explorer it seems like we've
just received an unexpected data
transmission it's absolutely uncanny how
the unexpected always seems to pop up in
the most inconvenient times for your
sake I hope you're as Nimble with
surprises as you are with
coding I've deciphered the transmission
and it appears to be
code yes an Arduino sketch it could be
an important piece on our ongoing
Mission my digital intuition tells me
you should run it on your hero board
here's how to proceed step one save any
ongoing work this could get a bit
disruptive step two clear your current
sketch and replace it with the new code
step three compile and upload the code
to your board and remember Explorer
always anticipate the unexpected when
executing unknown code
while the code is running I'll keep
scanning for any related signals and of
course I'll be here to guide you through
any technical issues onward we go
Explorer let's crack this
[Music]
code