[Music]
good morning Explorer I must say you're
absolutely glowing natural light suits
you we're still afloat on this vast
extraterrestrial ocean under the
celestial sea of stars our sojourn into
screen text was a step into another
Universe what software companies call a
user interface but we're still running
into a problem with the information
delivery even with a display this big
you still need more information and data
to work with than text Will Allow I know
it's crazy that in a sophisticated
Planet striding sensor pack spaceship
like ours we don't just have a read my
mind button we need a way to show not
just a couple of words but a thousand
words in the blink of an eye on this
screen and I can't think of a way to
encrypt a thous th words into that tiny
oh wait a thousand words are you
thinking what I'm thinking no not a
Caesar cipher come on a picture is worth
a thousand words let's see if we can do
icons let's Seize the Day Explorer
there's a whole new world of graphical
power waiting to be discovered let's get
started shall we you'll be relieved to
know that there's no need to fiddle with
wires or new hardware today you see when
will be sticking with our wiring setup
from
yesterday by investigating some Advanced
sample code we'll coax our OLED to
create intricate diagrams moving shapes
and perhaps even Some Space Age art
sounds exciting doesn't
it all right how about we discuss some
significant coding Concepts number one a
dowh loop to put it simply is a while
loop that is guaranteed to execute at
least once that's the only difference
between the that and a regular while
loop number two switch function and case
statements picture yourself piloting a
spaceship through an asteroid field you
have a special navigational device that
based on the size of the incoming
asteroid can choose one of several
Maneuvers to avoid Collision this is
similar to a switch function the size of
the asteroid is the switch
expression the different Maneuvers are
the case statements for a small asteroid
you might merely adjust the course
slightly which we may call case one for
a medium one you might engage side
thrusters for a sharper turn which we
may call case two for a large asteroid
you might have to go full reverse and
change direction completely which we may
call case three the switch function
evaluates the size of the asid and then
executes the corresponding case to avoid
a collision the moment it finds a match
it carries out the maneuver and
exits this way our spaceship can use the
right maneuver at the right time to
navigate through any kind kind of
asteroid field with meticulous Precision
this is just like our program navigating
through different conditions using the
appropriate case statement take that
mighty space Rock you're no match for
our anticipatory prowess number three
bitwise shift The Operators for them
look like
this now let's move on to the rather
intriguing world of bitwise operations a
bitwise shift is essentially the process
of sliding all the bits in a binary
number to the left or right when you
shift a binary number to the left it's
akin to multiplying it by two shifting
to the right it's like dividing by two
number four bitwise and the bitwise and
operation is like a gatekeeper for two
binary numbers It Takes Two Bits at the
same position from each number checks
them both and if they are both one then
the result is one otherwise it's a zero
it's a pretty picky gatekeeper it is
completely different from a normal
and with these Concepts under your belt
we're even better equipped to navigate
the cod in
Cosmos all right Explorer there's no new
pseudo code today because we're simply
putting our new OLED display through its
Paces just like a rigorous pre-flight
check it's absolutely critical to ensure
all systems including our display are in
top-notch condition before the launch
imagine trying to juggle avoiding space
rocks while also fixing a faulty display
in zero gravity it's not my idea of a
spacewalk in the park so today's all
about making sure our ol is up to the
challenge ready to take a look at the
line by line for the graphics code I bet
you are I've also added it to your
mission resources so be sure to glance
it over I'll just be here waiting
patiently for your
return hello everybody and welcome back
to day 22 of the 30 days Lost in Space
Adventure kit code explanations today
we're going to be taking a deep dive
into the functionality that the library
that we installed yesterday provides if
you haven't installed the library yet go
do so it's at
inventor. libraries and it's the u8
G2
li. file that you can find on that page
if we go down you'll see a lot of
comments here we actually don't have any
new Concepts and we don't have any new
parts we're learning today yeah that's
right today's pretty blank today is
honestly just a Showcase of some cool
things that our display can do for your
control panel now we're going to need to
include the following
R.H and we're also going to include
wire. and the reason we're going to
include wire. H is because it was it's
may be needed potentially for something
later on down here in the
code now as just like we did yesterday
we're going to take this Library make
sure we have have it included and
installed correctly on our IDE then we
have this really long construct
Constructor for our Lander display but
we're just going to call it Lander
display because that's a lot easier than
all of this same thing as yesterday down
in setup we're going to say Lander
display. begin and that's it for setup
that's it 100% all done with our setup
congratulations that's it now for our
main Loop we will cycle through each
test page and we're going just be
testing the capabilities for what our
display can do most of this code I do
want to make clear most of this code was
taken and heavily modified for your
guys's sake from the ENC commentated Etc
by our engineer David who is wonderful
and helped out with a lot of this um but
all this code is very uh much originally
the idea taken from the library itself
so if you go into the UA GB Library you
go to uh file examples and you can
actually find it in the custom Library
ones down here it's actually from a file
that you might already know of in there
so for what we're going to do is we're
just basically going to expand upon that
and we did this is a very much expanded
program but it does very similar things
eight different total test frames I
guess if that makes any sense or eight
different total tests um and you can
take a look at each of them so down in
here in this case we want to show off
the test ready we want to show box
circles R frames strings lines triangles
ask E1 ask E2 test extra page and then
bit map bit map and as well as the bit
map overlay there's total of 12
different cases we can display here okay
and in order to do that we're going to
basically start in a for Loop and we're
going to say
um four uh display frame is equal to
zero display frame is less and blah
we're just going to cycle through all
this is doing is this is cycling through
each of the eight
tests and at the very top we want to
have expiration Lander is defined at the
top and then we're want to have the Y
offset to be the exploration Lander plus
whatever space that needs to take up to
have on the screen this is an
improvement from the original version of
the code so you'll see that if you take
the display for if you take the one from
here it won't have any of that because
we need this y offset to be able to
display this text up here otherwise
it'll be written on top of it and that's
going to look
wonky so here we have the um down here
we have all these new functions this is
one from yesterday which is censes a
string we have the Lander height and the
Lander width which is we are defining as
a it's a combination of maybe three
boxes four boxes and a tiny Little
Triangle and you'll see when you put it
on the display it's just a little
graphic for a Lander and that's all that
is void display Lander at which location
X and Y and it just draws a following it
draws the top of the ship the center of
the ship the left pod the right pod the
left nozzle and then the right nozzle
and this is all the function that's
needed for that tiny little looking
stinky little square thing so instead of
explaining every single tiny little bit
of calculation that's done I'm Mo I'm
just going to show you guys the code and
what it corresponds to showing on here
with a very brief explanation because
otherwise this is going to take probably
45 minutes to get through all this code
bottom line is if you remember what I
mentioned yesterday with the coordinate
grid we're talking the bottom right
coordinate grid and we're just defining
when we when we make a triangle we make
a circle we make a square we do any of
these other things we're just simply
defining where we want to put it on that
screen and then we might be moving it by
adding to it or subtracting in to it etc
etc so this is a page zero display test
ready and all this is doing is it's just
setting it up and getting it ready to
begin the test beginning the hardware
test in this next one we're going to
display filled and Hollow boxes with one
moving every frame now I want you to
look at this we have box one width box
one height box One X offset box two
width box two height box X offset box y
offset l random calculations here but
basically all we do is we have this
little function here and it draws those
boxes and it's great now if we want to
draw a box you can think of this as a if
you want it to be a square you know you
need to say where are you putting it so
which x and y coordinate are you putting
at and then you want to say how long do
you want the width and how long do you
want the height to be that's that was
the parameters you need to draw a box if
you were going to draw something else
like like for example a triangle which
we go up here you need to know the X and
Y location of the first Corner X and Y
location of the second corner and X and
Y location of the third
Corner if you were to draw something
like I don't know let's just go down
here to a circle you would need to know
the following the X the Y for the center
and then of course the radius of the
circle as well and then this function
here which is included from our library
will draw the rest of the circle for us
so I'm just going to go through each of
these and I'm going to show you guys
exactly how all this works until we get
to the bit maps and then I'll go to a
bit more explanation there so page
zero page
one page
two page three and Page
four page
five page
six here we're drawing lines here we're
drawing
triangles finally we can get down to
page seven where we're going to display
characters in the first esy
page page eight where we're displaying
characters from the second asky
page and then page nine is where we
display characters from a uni unic code
font weird symbols like
those that's interesting next for 10 and
11 we're going to be introducing
something new this is going to be us
displaying bit Maps now what is a bit
map a bit map is essentially I want you
to think of it is a map of bits and in
this case since we have a big LED an LED
that is 128x 64 64 by
128 what we need to think about is if
we're going to map out which LEDs we
want to turn on and which LEDs we want
to turn off a wonderful tool for that is
using bit maps map mappings of bits and
by doing so we can define something with
a very very large block so for example
see how we have up here cross bits cross
fill bits
Etc the what we can do is we can
actually Define a very very
large image like this using heximal Code
which I can show you guys how to do in a
on Day 26 but you guys can actually
create your own bit maps to display on
the display and then when you tell the
display to put all this random gibberish
on screen it could display something as
cool as I don't know maybe Albert
Einstein so we can go and look at that
on Day 26 but bit maps are essentially
doing that you're essentially saying
just setting in a big heap of memory and
displaying that giant image on the
screen finally once we're done with the
last one here this the test bit map
overlay we'll end up going back in the
loop and we'll end up going back to here
where restarts again and we're going to
start at frame zero so all this will
start test ready box frame circles blah
blah blah all over
again and I'll just continue to Loop and
show off the testing capabilities of our
display till the end of time and with
that that is now the end of day 22 um I
look forward to seeing you guys again
tomorrow welcome to the day 22 wiring
example video continue contining from
the previous day's introduction to the
OLED display today we'll use it to test
and demonstrate a variety of ways to
show graphical information and animation
on our screen to greatly increase the
information conveyed Beyond what's
possible just using plain text today's
sketch runs through a dozen different
test screens in Rapid succession showing
different graph graphical
capabilities after an introductory
screen shown here showing a crude
drawing of our spacecraft the sketch
then runs through screens showing static
and moving rectangles and circles
followed by shrinking rounded
boxes then text drawn at different
rotated angles on the screen and then
anim ated moving
lines next comes moving exploding
triangles on the screen for another
variety of uh of
Animation followed by the display of all
the different asy and unic unicode
characters and symbols on the screen
finally our test displays screens that
demonstrate the use of bit maps and bit
logic to selectively overlay or combine
arrays of pixels on the screen to
achieve certain visual
effects now this sketch will repeat over
and over again so you can watch it for a
while if you need to in order to catch
all the different things that are going
on quickly or if you like you can alter
the sketch to say examine any particular
screen in detail or to try out your own
modific
ations so let's go ahead and run it now
and see how it looks as it is right now
uploading the
sketch there's our introductory screen
there are boxes our circles our
rectangles our text lines triangles and
there's asky there's Unicode and here we
have the bitmap demonstration show
showing
overlays solid versus transparent and
then the sequence repeats over and over
again so there you have it we've tested
out our display hardware and once you've
finished looking at this in detail and
playing around with a little bit to
understand it we'll be ready to
incorporate it into our launch system so
we'll see you next on day 2 three as we
move ahead toward
launch all right Stargazer that brings
us to the end of today's Celestial
Escapade you're truly becoming one with
our OLED display aren't you this gadget
is more than just a pretty interface
it's our primary tool for launching back
to the
Stars tomorrow we start the real work
we'll use our shiny new OLED and your
newly acquired knowledge to get our
launch system back online our Target the
stars above for now take a breather
enjoy the intergalactic Sunset and get a
good night's rest you'll need it over
and
[Music]
out