[Music]
rise and shine Explorer our oxygen
levels are steady and our batter is
replenishing nicely that's caused for a
small sigh of relief H wouldn't you say
but let's not lose sight of the task at
hand we have another glorious day of
repairs to conduct today we're going to
shift gears and delve into a bit of
digital logic we'll be learning about
bits data types and why choosing the
right one for your variables can make
all the difference efficient memory
usage is essential for our system to
function optimally especially on low
memory devices like our herob board
moreover we're going to expand the
depths of our coding efforts we'll work
on a piece of code whose intention is to
calculate our ship's battery percentage
not only will this give us a clear idea
a of our power situation but it will
also be a practical application of the
concepts we're learning ready to get
your hands dirty with some binary of
course you are let's get to it well well
aren't you lucky Explorer today you get
to enjoy a bit of a hardware holiday how
delightful for you we're leaving the
wires and boards be they've had quite
enough of your expertise for the time
being before you start daydreaming about
a leisurely day off let me assure you
we're not on vacation there is still
much work to be done while the hardware
is blessedly out of Harm's Way for a day
we're going to fill the void with a
thrilling Deep dive into the captivating
world of coding yes that's right more
mesmerizing Mazes of bits bites
variables and functions are waiting for
your full attention this isn't just
about expanding your tiny knowledge base
for the sake of it you know we're doing
this so we can craft more refined more
efficient code in layman's terms
smoother operations and quicker fixes
lead us to a f faster escape from this
underwater blunder that we're in so
buckle up Explorer it's high time you
familiarize yourself with the finer
points of our herob board's language
we've got some serious coding to do ah
Joy it seems you're thirsty for
knowledge Explorer we'll hold on to your
seat I'm about to drop some wisdom bombs
on you first there's this delightful
little thing called a bit the smallest
unit of data there is it's binary which
in this case means it's either zero or
one its Simplicity is quite adorable
isn't it combine three of these and boom
you have eight unique integer numbers
mathematic next let's graduate to the
integer it's a little bit chunkier with
a typical size of 16 bits this gives you
a marvelous range of about plus or minus
32,768 not too shabby wouldn't you agree
when it comes to integers we're not
bound by One path to stroll down we've
got two signed and unsigned the signed
integers take more of a straightforward
path and have a bit that acts like a
flag for whether the number is positive
or negative unsigned integers on the
other hand don't bother with this as
free Spirits they take the scenic route
living their life positively all the way
hence the bigger range of numbers now
take our photo resistor it's a modest
creature outputting a value between 0
and
1,23 it's just 10 bits worth of data
because 2 to the power of 10 equals
1,24 so an integer is more than adequate
to store it but don't get too
comfortable our battery capacity
variable is set at a lofty 50,000 which
outclasses the standard short integer
maximum of
32,768 thus it needs the VIP treatment
which defines it as an unsigned integer
next up meet float this one likes to
live a bit on the edge handling decimal
numbers with Precision Imagine
123.456 7 it has a Precision of seven
not bad huh then there's double it's a
float that hit the gym and got buff it's
64 bits of power capable of holding
values up to a mindboggling 10 to the
power of
308 fearing off from variables let's
shine some light on void it's what we
use when we're defining functions that
don't give anything back we'll dive
deeper into creating our own functions
soon enough so there you have it a crash
course in basic digital logic its
overwhelming nature is similar to
drinking from a fire hose I know but
Fred not we'll be practicing these
Concepts soon enough shall we push on
then today's Mission involves writing
additional logic in order to print the
battery percentage to our handy serial
monitor that we discussed yesterday of
course we don't want to spend time
rewriting the print statements all over
the place in our code instead we can
create a new function we can start with
the word void this is what the function
will be returning as you may have
guessed void means that it will return
nothing this also means that we don't
need a return statement since the
compiler deems it unnecessary I
recommend you name it something relative
such as print battery percentage the
parentheses can be empty since we have
no parameters we need to pass into the
function finally everything inside the
brackets is what we'll execute when you
call the function when the second
closing bracket is reached it will
return to where it was called from in
the code if my assumption is correct it
is likely setup or Loop in the end your
newly created function might look
something like this for the line by line
let's jump to the information cached on
your computer I've also added this to
your mission resources for future
reference I'll be waiting patiently for
your
return hello and welcome back to day
seven of the code explanations today
we're going to be using the circuit from
day seven to use the value read from the
photo resistor to simulate charging our
Lander's battery our battery is
currently drained and we can assume just
for a simulation purposes that the
current charge level is going to be zero
and we will stop charging once the
battery is full so first we explicitly
included uino Doh as always if we just
happened to delete that entirely it
wouldn't really matter because the uino
IDE the one we're programming in right
now will automat ically add that in
again for us later I'm also going to
close out of a couple of comment blocks
that aren't really that big of a deal to
go through so that it will look a little
bit less daunting so new Concepts that
were're introducing today are going to
be we know of the function setup that's
a default inside of the uino IDE and we
know of the function Loop which is a
default part of any uino program or
sketch however what do you do if you
want to add in your own function and
that's what we're going to be learning
today we're going to be creating a new
function and this function is going to
help us with our task of printing the
battery charge level and we're going to
call it quite literally void which is
what's needed to create a function that
returns well nothing or void print
battery charge level and then the Syntax
for this is if I actually go like this
and close this out you can see the
syntax without anything inside void
print battery charge level we have open
parentheses and close parentheses since
there's no parameters we're going to be
passing in in this function we can just
leave it empty and then we have an open
bracket and a closed bracket anything in
between this Open Bracket and this
closed bracket will be what happens when
you call this function this will be the
code that it executes when you call it
so if I at any point during setup in
Loop or anywhere else in the code want
to call this line of code and I do here
on line 65 it's going to jump to this
function and execute the code located
right here so let's start off by just
going through the general flow of the
code first obviously we are talking
about the analog res photo resistor pin
that's going to be an analog pin a z and
we're just defining that above is a
constant bite same thing as if you use
the pound Define both methods are valid
and you can do either one here down
below we have a constant unsigned
integer and we're going to be calling it
battery percentage is going to be equal
to or battery capacity is equal to
50,000 and this is going to be the
maximum battery capacity for simulation
purposes um we just chose a random large
number and in this case 50,000 for
simulation reasons alone now if you jump
down to set up we're going to set the
photo register pin as an input so that
we can read off of it and read the value
on it and then we're going to start
serial. begin at 96,000 B rate which
means if you do go to the serial monitor
please make sure that you have selected
the correct B rate at 9600 because
that's what we set it to here if you
select something else it will be
gibberish now if we go jump down to the
next part here we have unsigned int
battery level is going to be equal to
zero for simulation purposes we're going
to pretend that our battery is
completely dead which to be honest with
you it almost
is next we're going to jump down to the
after setup it will always go straight
to Loop now here's where we do something
really interesting in Loop we have the
following information that we're just
going to be spitting out to the serial
monitor if the battery level is less
than the battery percentage meaning this
this is only going we're only going to
be printing things out if it needs to be
charged still meaning it's not fully
charged then we're going to execute the
following code battery level and then
this is a New Concept plus equals analog
read of the photo resistor pin so if the
light is really really bright on the
photo resistor then what it should do is
it will add a higher number to it so we
can read anywhere from you know maybe if
it's really dark it's only going to add
20 but if it's really really bright it
might add 140 for example or you know or
I guess maybe like close to it could add
up to 200 or 300 as you get brighter and
brighter so what happens is this
function here simply adds whatever is in
analog read whatever this is every time
this hits this code to what the current
battery level is another way to write
this exact same piece of code
is and then this is so line 50 and line
51 will be functionally equivalent and
so this is just a shorthand way of
saying battery level equals battery
uncore
level plus analog
read photo register
pin
so why is this important that's because
in the Arduino language which is based
off of C there are going to be a lot of
shortcuts that you might notice or
recognize here and there this is exactly
one of those shortcuts battery level
equals battery level plus analog read
photo resistor pin is the exact same as
battery level plus equals analog read
photo resistor pin it's simply just a
shorthand so you don't have to type it
twice it also looks a little bit cleaner
at least from in my opinion another
short hand that you'll see from time to
time is let's just say you want to say
battery level equals battery level plus
one well there's an easier way to do
that and that is just you can just do
Plus+ and that simply just adds one two
there but we don't need to do that
that's just another example of a
shorthand that also exists that maybe
one you might be more familiar with
battery level equals analog read or plus
equals analog read photo pin so we're
just going to add whatever this is to
battery level then if the battery level
is greater than the battery capacity
meaning this would make the charge over
100% um so let's just say that the
battery level was
49,9 80 and it added 30 to it so now it
would be 50, in 10 once it gets to this
line out because maybe in this one it
made it it too higher than 50,000 then
we're just going to reset it back down
to the maximum capacity making the
battery level back at 50,000 since we
can't obviously charge it more than the
maximum amount and then the next time we
go to the loop you'll notice that it
will probably hit this code here and
since it's going to be fully charged
we'll just be ignoring all of this extra
additional stuff inside of here next
we're going to call the next function
that we created down below print battery
charge level we're calling this function
inside of loop we're calling a function
inside of a function and what this will
do is it will jump here and then
immediately execute the following code
so whenever we call this function it
will jump to here and it will say if it
is not fully charged then we will print
the battery level and display it as a
percentage to the serial monitor if it
otherwise meaning it is fully charged
we're going to just display that it's
fully charged and then finally once this
is done executing it will jump back to
the very end of the line here at the end
of where you called the function and
continue on going forward in this case
it'll go down a line and it'll delay by
1/10th of a second and then hop back to
the beginning of Loop and go through the
exact same sequence once again and so
with that that will be the end of day
seven code explanation I'll see you
again
tomorrow welcome to the day seven wiring
example video
as we mentioned on day six today nothing
has changed circuit wise since day six
so we really don't have any new circuit
or Hardware explanations to go over
although you can review the day six
video if you'd like a refresher instead
we'll be focusing today mainly on how
our circuit interacts with the logic
that's programmed into our new day seven
software sketch all of the new
functionality will be observed This Time
by looking at the output on the serial
monitor console so without further Ado
let's just go ahead and run our software
sketch and see what it
does once it's loaded we'll see that the
serial monitor will give us a running
status of the state of charge of our
simulated battery system and so we see a
slowly Rising number if we place the
photo resistor in the dark with our
black
cloth we see that the charging rate
basically slows down to zero and uh so
this is telling us that we're not
charging at all on the other hand if I
remove the cloth the charging rate picks
up again and if I increase the light
intensity even more by shining a
flashlight the rate jumps rather
dramatically so we can see that by
altering the illumination on the photo
resistor we see changes in the rate of
charging in our circuit and so if we let
this continue we'll speed it up a little
bit by shining a flashlight on it
eventually the charge level will reach
100% and that should be happening about
now there we go so the sketch detects
this condition and it stops the charge
level from rising any higher than
100% so you'll want to experiment with
this on your own while studying the
logic that's built in to our sketch for
day seven good luck with this new bit of
coding and we will see you with more
challenges and new things to learn ahead
on day
eight well well well you've made it
through the day Explorer our little
adventure with bits integers floats and
doubles didn't scare you off did it not
bad for a human I must say now that we
have our our power situation under
control and can monitor our battery
percentage you must be feeling rather
accomplished before you get lost in
celebration let me remind you that we've
barely scratched the surface of what's
broken on this ship tomorrow we're going
to brighten up this dreary spacecraft by
adding a bit of color yeah you heard me
right we're going to introduce an RGB L
which can emit all the colors of the
rainbow we'll use this flashy little
Gizmo for various status indicat like
painting a glowing green if our battery
is all charged up or a glaring red if
we're running on fumes so get some rest
Explorer tomorrow we paint with
[Music]
light