[Music]
good morning Explorer good sleep that's
great sleeping yeah all right okay we're
screwed again I swear this whole mission
is cursed it's like this space big
Mothership small I can get in General
vicinity but we'll have to get there in
lots of hops that's going to take
forever we need finer detail over a
larger area so we can say go here rather
than waft over in its general direction
like a leaf in the wind hash always a
brown
coat an LED isn't going to do it led
segments can't do it even our small
screen can't do it it's time to go big
but small but still big all right
Explorer let's dive in we're about to
fix up our displays Graphics system to
guide us smoothly back home but first a
brief glimpse into the tech Marvel we're
working with our display measures
128x 64 pixels think of a pixel as an
incredibly minuscule LED so in essence
our display is a dazzling array of
8,192 of these tiny LEDs with this
knowledge in hand we can craft bit Maps
imagine these as detailed charts that
dictate which LEDs light up and which
ones stay dark get ready because today
we'll embark on a delightful Journey
with these bit maps all right Explorer
now that we're soaring through space and
our communication lines are clear I've
managed to fetch some topnotch data
assets dive into your mission resources
there's a treasure Trove waiting for you
everything you'll need as we navigate
forward bit by bit map and hey who said
a bit of creative sketching wasn't part
of a day's work in space alongside those
resources I've retrieved some
instructive content from your computer's
memory bank let's tap into those
resources now and set the
course hello and welcome everybody back
to art class I mean Day 26 of the
inventure kits Lost in Space code
explanations or I guess today
technically will be a little bit of an
art class or a bit of a digital art
class if we so take a look at today's
code I'm sure you guys have already seen
the B the part on the page allows you to
copy and paste you'll see that it's a
very large amount of code you know like
470 lines today don't worry about it um
most of that is going to be all just
pasted image data for our bit Maps now
before we begin let's actually talk a
little bit about what a bit map is well
to be blunt and simple about it it is
quite literally a mapping of bits it's
essentially telling on an 128 by 64
screen how what bit should we turn on
and what bits should we turn off it
gives a mapping of exactly that the way
we do that here is in HEX decimal using
this code here don't worry though you
don't have to type all this or whatever
yourself there are tools online that
will help you generate exactly what you
need so today your task is going to be
you can obviously use the images we
provided or if you'd like I'd also
encourage you to make your own bit map
as well let's first talk before we go
into making bit Maps let's talk a little
bit about the code obviously we have the
included
.h we have the libraries needed to draw
on our OLED
display we obviously created the OLED
object here so that we can call the
functions in that library and down here
you'll notice we have this external
constant unsigned
Char nice rocket bro which is an
interesting name planet bit map Earth
bit map and inventor Court logo bit map
one thing I want to mention about all
these is that these are mentioned as
externs here we wanted to have it so
that we didn't have a ton of code all at
the top we wanted to kind of clean up
the code a little bit so by putting this
external on it means that we're
basically allowing it to be configured
for the compiler so that it can actually
be used in here if we didn't have this
up here and we just had where it was all
defined down below see just down here
nice rocket Pro isn't just a short bit
it's this giant array of or should I say
mapping of uh all the data that we want
to display our image on the screen in
particular I created an image using this
tool online that just says nice rocket
bro
and then I converted it to a bit map
image and and now that when it's run and
said to be put on the OLED it turns
into we also did the exact same thing
for the planet bit map and we have one
for the unearth and then we also have
one for the inventor Corp logo and we
did all of that down there but if we
didn't have this up here we' get an
error from the compiler saying I don't
know where this is if we try to call it
somewhere else down here in the code and
try to put it on the display the reason
why is because these need to be for a
compiler reasons defined
before it gets called here in the code
but it also looks really bad having it
all the way at the top so we did this
here we Define it here and then have all
this at the bottom just so that it's
nice and clean so you can see all the
code first and then not worry about all
the bits down here that don't don't
really matter all that much at the end
of the day since they're just computer
gener generated using a program that
I'll show you in just a moment so those
are all defined here and then down here
we have a array of bit Maps so this will
be at index zero index one index two and
index three so we have a total of four
things in that array and those are all
just these bit Maps
here in the setup function we're just
simply going to begin initialize our
land display and just talk over the
serial monitor we don't actually call
anything on the serial monitor there's
not really anything we call but for
debugging purposes we just kind of
always put it if you comment it out it
shouldn't break anything down here we
have in the loop we have int number of
bit Maps is equal to the size of the bit
Maps array so to get the number of how
many we have we can actually do this we
can get the size of the bit maps with
the size of the array in bytes so this
is how many it is in bytes not how many
items are in there this is how many
there are in bytes but since we know
that each bit map is going to be an 128x
64 image in this case and we know that
because they're all 128 by 64 we can
then divide by the size of the very
first one which is going to be many bits
it is so we take basically four or I
guess you know whatever this is divided
by 120 by 64 in bytes and then we get
the number of bit Maps here now we do a
nice for Loop and we're going to go
through each and every bit map in the
array and in that very first bit map
we're just simply going to draw the bit
map for 2 seconds at a time on the
display if I jump real quick to um how I
made these now the next part of this
project is I want you guys to make your
own bit Maps there are a couple
different tools that you can use and I'm
going to load those up right now the
first one is if you have a tool like for
example here's one I'm using called
canva and this is one option of a tool
you can use as you can see I've made it
so that the size of it I don't know if
you can see up here when I defined it I
said
1,280 by 640 I basically multiplied by
10 because those numbers are easier to
work with in a photo editor than 128 by
64 and I made this famous Einstein quote
I don't know if you've ever heard of him
say this but he says uh the quote nice
rocket bro to you guys that was a real
quote he definitely did say that and you
should believe everything you hear on
the internet you can make something like
this I do recommend setting the size of
it ahead of time though like like I said
1,280 X 640 if you hit share you can hit
download I can download is a little nice
PNG and that PNG is going to be what I'm
going to be using in the next tool you
can also use there's alternative
programs to this too here's a good
example you can also do paint. j.org
what I would do is I would set up the
image let's go
to if you go to image attributes on this
so now that we have an image now that's
1,280 by 640 obviously when we configure
this in the next tool we'll have to
divide by 10 I just find it easier to do
it in an editor like this we can draw
another image and so for example let's
draw uh I don't know like uh a
house but let's make it let's make it a
square and oh I don't want that I want
to uh circle
circle
circle get the filler Boop all right
this is my Modern Art it's going on sale
for $20 million if anyone wants to buy
it please uh let me know it is for sale
for $20 million and then what I'm going
to do is I'm going to go to file I'm
going to go to save as and it's just
going to download it as a PNG and that's
fine because that's how we want it to be
right now next here's the real tool that
I like to use here's the main the main
thing however you want to generate the
image is fine those are some good
examples on how to now you have a couple
different options okay you want to
obviously select those files in your
file window and then this is a tool that
I use it's an open- Source tool that
literally creates images from it
converts it to heximal arrays
essentially for you to use inside of
your code there's going to be some steps
here be careful you don't skip a step
there's a lot of steps step one once
you've uploaded the images you're going
to want to make sure that they are in if
you go here 128 by 64 128 by 64 if
you're going to make it the full screen
image remember the amount of pixels you
have on screen is only 128 by 64 you'll
notice they don't look good right now
make sure you do scaling and select one
here that looks good as you can see we
have nice rocket bro Einstein and my
modern art piece that I'm selling for
$20 million if you go down here now that
we have this see this swap thing you you
have to make sure that this this swap is
selected you want to swap the bits and
the bite and is useful for working with
the u8 g2 Library well just so funny
enough what library are we using the u8
G2 lib U G2 Library so we can hit
generate code and I sometimes like to
just uncheck it just to make sure the
swap it and I look at this to make sure
that the numbers change they did so it
means that it generated correctly the
first time there's occasionally I've had
it where the browser I had to double
click it sometimes make sure all these
settings are the same you don't have to
do anything with these and if you look
at the code that you have down here you
have the very first one which is nice
rocket and we already have this one here
so we don't have to worry about that
this is the exact same code if you look
at this hexadecimal it should be the
exact same as the thing we have right
here the exact exact same uh because I
just I've already done this image and if
you take the modern art one down here
below you can take
this you can just copy copy it if you
want to contrl + C and now I have my own
Modern Art again $20 million if anyone
wants it paste this down below and uh
obviously you have this here so here's
now the new I'm going to
say Modern
Art and I want to make sure it's defined
properly so static con static const
Modern Art and is that's good and then I
want to go so there's that to find out
below and now what I'm going to do is
I'm going to
go so then the next step says if you
want to display it in this exact program
you can create this here obviously put
whatever you named it down below I
renamed mine from the default that it
generated as Modern Art and I obviously
want to make it uh the exact same as
what this is static and obviously have
the u u 8 by8 just to keep things
everything the same then I want to go up
here and I want to go down below and I
want to also add Modern
Art and with that we should be good now
we have this here defined at the top so
the compiler can see it even though it's
defined way down below it sees it up
here first and then obviously here we
have the modern art added to the bit
maps and since we have this here the
size of it's going to be able to
dynamically allocate it for us so once
again we can display it without going to
changes to
A5 and with that that is all we really
need and if you hit run it should show
the new bit map that you've created so
again I'm going to link these to you
guys you guys will have these available
to you if you guys want to make your own
bit Maps I really like the image to C++
you don't have to do 128x 64 that's only
if you want it to be a full screen bit
map you can do other size bit Maps but
we'll get into those in the next couple
days so don't worry about that as of
right now and I'll also link these two
resources out there if you want them I
do think they're really good for making
the images to upload so with that
that'll be about it I will see you guys
later welcome to the Day 26 wiring
example video you made it you're off the
planet and back in orbit but as you're
well aware of by now your work is far
from finished to get back to the safety
of the
mothership we still have to to configure
our systems for a safe approach and
docking and this is going to take some
additional effort today's task is
relatively simple from a wiring and
Hardware standpoint since to get started
all we'll be using today is the OLED
display this will be our first building
block to which We'll add additional
components of our control system over
the coming
days now today's software lesson is
focused on the display of bitmap
Graphics as a way of more efficiently
conveying information than by using the
shape drawing commands that we learned
about
earlier when you fully understood this
new programming material the hardware
steps necessary to test it are pretty
straightforward you'll see that here
that although I haven't removed all of
the old components that we used on day
24 from the breadboard they are inactive
and not relevant for today's
discussion all we really need to focus
on for
now are the four connections to the OLED
and even those are familiar to us the
power and the ground are both provided
just as they were last time via these
red and black jumpers that are connected
to the breadboard board power buses next
door and also as before we have our two
wires that control the display we have a
green wire right here connected from the
clock terminal on the display to the
hero I i2c pin that's pin number
A5 and we have this blue wire right here
that's connected from the data terminal
of the display to Hero pin
A4 and that is all we'll need for
today's test so let's go ahead and
upload the sketch and see how things
look so in the
IDE I'm now uploading the sketch it'll
take a few seconds for this to compile
and
upload and there we go
there's our second bit map there's our
third bit map and there's the fourth and
then we'll just rotate through these bit
map displays indefinitely until we uh uh
turn off the hero and end uh the the
running of this
sketch so I'd say this looks like pretty
good progress we're ready now to move
ahead in the next day and integrate this
bitmap display functionality into the
other features of our approach and
Landing system so with that we'll see
you on day
27 bigger screen for bigger space now
we'll need bigger numbers and here our
usual decimal way of counting in tens
isn't going to help us and I'm going to
race through this so hold tight in the
decimal placeholder system there are two
patterns exponents and symbols so here's
the number system you learned in school
10 to the^ of 0 is 1 actually any
anything to the power of 0 is 1 but look
10 the^ of 1 is 10 10 the^ of two or 10
* 10 is 100 10 the^ of 3 or 10 * 10 * 10
is 1,000 and so on binary also uses
placeholders and the same exponent
system but the base is two The Columns
go up in squares like the decimal system
but small numbers are long and horrible
in decimal n is just 9 N9 in binary is 1
0 1 215 is 1 1 0 1 0111 I mean what I
may be an AI but even I can see how this
can quickly become hard to read if there
was a system that was more like the
decimal system more symbols less
repetition we'd have less headaches and
there is
heximal hex has 16 digits 0 through 9
then a for 10 B for 11 up to F for 15
so in HEX 13 is just d 16 well there is
no HEX number for 16 so we put one in
the 16s column and no ones 16 is 10 in
HEX or as we normally write it 10
H in the generated code segment you're
gazing upon the raw essence of our bit
map though I've given it a little
reshaping to gel with our hero board
using heximal it might not look like the
prettiest star in the G Galaxy bear with
me when you spot
0x00 that's our pixel galaxy in the off
phase in counter 0x FF that's our little
pixel stars shining brightly any other
values you come across represent a mixed
Cosmic dance of some Stars being on and
others off typically forming a pattern
in a row or column good job Explorer I
like your uh
art guess I shouldn't have expected much
from from an organic life form oh this I
just drew a portrait of someone smarter
than you while I was following along
don't pay it any
mind well at least we know that we have
finer detailed navigation thanks to the
big small big screen I'll display the
coordinates now tomorrow we will add
some additional pre-made bit maps to our
systems autopilot and continue on our
merry way through the endless void we
call the universe see you then
[Music]
on