[Music]
good morning star Voyager another Cosmic
day awaits us yesterday we journeyed
through the wonders of bit Maps
navigating the constellations of pixels
today we shift our trajectory slightly
venturing into the realm of binary
counters imagine it as laying the
foundation for understanding the binary
language of the universe using our
trusty dip switch we're going to
construct a three- bit binary counter
this is a pivotal step before we launch
into the challenging task of mending our
docking gear ready to play with some
switches and send signals across the
vastness of our ship system
let's light up the binary Stars I want
you to think of each of our switches as
an individual bit since we have three
switches that means for today's
calculator we will have a total of three
bits when all three are off we can think
of it as representing 0 0 0 when all
three are on we can think of it as
representing 1 one one but you haven't
learned how to count in binary yet have
you all right deep breath Explorer let's
set our sites on my personal favorite
way to represent numbers binary in fact
by definition it's the only method I use
think of binary as a language that can
only use one and zero with our three
switches we have three positions like
three light bulbs in a row farthest to
the left represents the largest value
and farthest to the right is the
smallest each of these light bulbs can
be either off low signified by a zero or
on high signified by a one starting from
the right most
bulb the first bulb represents the
number one the next one to its left
stands for the number two and the
leftmost one symbolizes the number four
now if only the rightmost bulb is on
your number is one if the two bulbs on
the left are on and the rightmost is off
your binary reads 1 1 0 which translates
to 4 + 2+ 0 equals 6 in our usual
decimal counting with me so far great
now we're going to map this Cosmic dance
of numbers to visual imagery depending
on the binary sequence our switches
spell out we'll display a distinct bit
map it's a smart way to confirm that all
our switches are in tiptop shape
functioning flawlessly after all imagine
the anticlimax surmounting all
challenges only to falter on our final
descent due to a landing gear glitch
let's not be the comet that dazzles in
the sky but disintegrates upon Landing
safety always Orbits for first for
today's code we will need a way to
display a total of8 bit Maps so that
means we will need to do the following
first set up our hardware for the OLED
and Define inputs for dip switches Etc
second make a total of eight bit Maps
luckily for you I've already done that
so don't worry about making your own
unless you really want to and third
write a function to be able to calculate
which of the 8 bit Maps we are going to
be displaying this will technically be 0
through 7 since as you know good
programmers prefer to start at
zero let's think about that a little bit
further we will have a total of eight
different
cases case one where all are off case
two where switch one is on and two and
three are off case three where one and
two are on but three is off etc etc all
the way to case eight where all three
are flipped
on there are a couple different ways we
can do this maybe the good old if
statement I think this is okay for now
however if we had more than three digits
to deal with I'm sure you could see how
this could get messy quickly worry not
Explorer I've gathered some
instructional material that should help
alleviate any sense of uncertainty you
may have I've also added this to your
mission resources for future reference
take a
look hello hello and welcome back to day
27 of the 30 days Lost in Space
Adventure kit code explanations today is
going to be a little bit different than
most days if you you might be noticing I
have an empty sketch here usually when
you guys go into the course page you
might see something like this where you
have piece of code here that you can
copy into your IDE and then obviously
hit compile and it should hopefully work
with no issues but you'll notice today
there's two of them we have the regular
code and then we also have a new header
file and going forward we're going to be
putting all of our bit Maps inside of a
nice header file so instead of having
all of this random gibberish in our main
file because obviously that's just a lot
of space that's being used it feels like
on the screen so it's a little bit
easier to read we're going to put
everything all of our bit maps that
we've created for these lessons into
header files so you might be asking
yourself okay well how do I go about
doing that how do I go about putting
those into uh header file well let's
first copy the very first sketch like
you would normally if this is the way
you're going to be doing it you can go
ahead and copy this one and then they
have this nice little thing here and you
can go new tab and you can create the
new name for the file you'll notice
right here it says include switch Corbit
maps. spelled exactly that way with the
underscore if you create it and you
don't name it the right thing you will
get a compilation issue so you can click
okay and then obviously now that you
have this you can then copy the new code
into here I actually have it from
here so we go boop
boop Bo and so you shouldn't hopefully
if I click verify there should be no
compilation issues because it will
notice that there's a switch bit maps.
that you've included right here so for
today's lesson we're going to be showing
a couple of new different for things one
is going to be partial bit Maps where
instead of having it be the full screen
you do not have to have it be the full
screen you can actually have a bit map
be whatever size you want and then
specify where you want it to be on the
display so we're going to be introducing
that we're also going to be using the
dip switch as a three bit binary counter
and for each of those numbers that it
can generate 0 through 7 we will be
using those numbers to display a a
relevant piece on the OLED display for
exactly that and of course the last
thing we covered today was to create the
include file here which is a bit maps.
so let's quickly go through all of the
new code that we're going into today
obviously you have this up here since
we're in the ardino IDE it's technically
technically not necessary but just you
can keep it in if you want to it doesn't
hurt anything it will automatically be
put in for us if we go up here I'm just
going to erase all this Boop make our
stuff nice and easy to read we have the
u8 G2 lib library that we've been using
forever wire. this is all not new stuff
we've talked about before create the
Lander display easy peasy there we go
finally we have the new thing here we're
going to include our switch bit maps. H
just like we have with wire. u8 G2 lib
switch bit maps. and we include it this
is just another another file similar to
this that has definitions to things so
if you're ever curious ever want to look
into wire. those are all freely
available to go and look into and I
highly recommend if you're curious about
how they do i2c Communications and all
that other stuff um make your life a lot
easier you can go in and see all the
work they did that's the beauty of Open
Source down here below we have the
following we have switch bit Maps now we
have a total of eight
different numbers that
A3 bits can produce for so if we assume
that bit one is going to be the
rightmost of the dip switches bit two is
going to be the middle dip switch and
the third bit is going to be the very
left one we can have all of them be off
in switch zero we can all of them we can
have the very first one be on um all the
way up to all of them being on which
would be not eight but seven because
remember we start at zero as programmers
so we have zero one two three four five
six seven and these are all the
different places that they can be in and
you'll notice we have switches zero
switches one switches two so this is
just a simply a array of pointers to the
bit map images that we have in switch
bit Maps finally we have the include for
our uh seven segment display we tell
them what pins we're using for the seven
segment display in our case we're using
two and three and then we're going to go
down here and we're going to use
following to set up the switch bit pins
so the very first pin is going to be for
the dip switch is a z A1 and A2 the
reason we're using A1 a z and A2 you
might be noticing why are we're going to
be using analog pins there's a reason
for this don't worry um normally you
would be using digital pins it doesn't
make sense to be using analog pins for
this but when we get to day 29 we will
well as you'll hopefully shortly see in
a couple days we won't have enough room
for all of the pins we want to include
on our board so we're actually going to
be able to use luckily analog pins are
backwards compatible as digital pins um
digital pins are not compatible as
analog pins though and since we did not
have enough pins on our board on very on
the late day 29 when we want to include
every single component in our survival
kit we have here we needed to make sure
that we used everything that we possibly
could so we used analog pins because
they do technically work as digital pins
because when we get to day
29 there will not be any room for
them otherwise so let's hop down to
setup we have serial begin
9600 um you'll also notice we
technically don't do any printouts or
anything so if this was removed
technically nothing would break but it's
nice if you want to do a print statement
and debug if you're going to add your
own cool stuff maybe create of the idea
bit map number display we're setting the
counter display to just be on a
uh which is the seven segment display
we're just going to set it to seven
which is the maximum brightness and
we're going to just clear the display
configur the dip switch and make the
Lander display initialize and do all of
the things that it needs to in the begin
function in here which is probably going
to be pin mode is my guess and some
other things down here in Loop we have
the bite offset for X and Y for our
bitmap Graphics since we're using a
partial bit map this bit map that we're
using is not
128x 64 pixels it is not the entire
screen so we need to specify where we
want it to be preferably we could
technically not specify it and it would
just kind of go up in the top left
corner of the screen um instead of it
being in the very top left corner um we
want it to be kind of centered in the
middle and somewhere where it makes
sense in fact technically we want it to
be a down so that we can have some text
on screen as well so what we do to do
that is we simply calculate a good x
value and a good y value to make that
happen here we're just calculating the X
and Y offset now when we get to this
part of the code here you might know
that our functionality of our program is
to display up to eight different values
that it could possibly be depending on
what switches are switched on on our dip
switch now in order to calculate these
values we could theoretically have eight
different if statements where it's like
if this is on and this is off and this
is off then it's this and if this is on
and this is on and this is on then it's
this and if this is off and this is off
and this is off and it's this but that
would be really gross and that's not a
great way to do things um especially
because if we had any more than three we
just exponentially make it worse for
every number we add on every additional
bit so if we ever wanted to upgrade this
to an eight position dip switch then it
sucks so we don't want to do that so
what we have here is we have this
wonderful thing called bitwise shift
operators and what it does is it simply
takes okay if the value of the very
first one that we read um which is going
to be this left one here is a one then
we want to set it to one otherwise it's
zero that one's really easy because
remember the way this works is if equals
equals High then we want to set it to
one but if it's not on we want it to be
zero that makes sense right so switch
value would be set to one zero would be
set to the it if it was off that makes
sense for the very first one but what do
you do about these right because you
can't you can't really get these very
much this is where the bitwise shift
operators come in you can basically
think of it as it basically sets it to
switch value then is going to be or
equals so read bit one which is going to
be the second one on the bit and we're
going to set set it to high or we're
going to set it to one if it's high and
zero if it's off but then we're going to
shift it over by one so we put it back
in its position and we're going to keep
that in switch value finally we read the
very last one here and the reason we're
using or equals is because then we can
actually calculate it all as one
wonderful number we have the following
uh if it's equal to high then we're
going to set it to one
otherwise we're going to set to zero
this is all the same for every single
one but then since it's the very next
bit the this bit here if we didn't bit y
shifted by two we're going to override
what was in this position so we need to
shift it over boop boop to this position
here and so by doing that we're going to
create a number and we're going to be
able to display it then on our display
so switch value now will be equal to the
number whatever it is so if all of them
are on we will have it just be like for
example like 11 one sort of kind of
thing so what we could do is we can go
to down here below and we can say bit
map number display. show number decimal
X ex and we can display that switch
value on our seven segment display and
then finally depending on which one this
matches up with we have obviously down
here switch is 0 1 2 3 4 5 6 7 and we
can know what index sets in so if it's
in if we know that we want to display
the number four it's going to be five um
in this case so what we can do is we can
do Lander display. first page do Lander
display. draw draw XMBC and we're going
to display that image that we've created
that bit map in the switch bit map image
file and we're going to display that
centered on the display matching
whatever we calculated here and that is
it for today for day 27 of the code
explanations tomorrow we will be getting
into fixing our landing gear and don't
worry we will also be using lots more
fun bit maps and we will be putting
those again in a separate file tomorrow
as well so um be ready for that and so
without further Ado I look forward to
seeing you guys
tomorrow welcome to the day 27 wiring
example
video okay things are starting to ramp
up now both in in terms of hardware and
software as we continue to build up our
Landing control system today's task
brings back a couple of old friends of
ours the seven segment LED numerical
display and the three Channel dip switch
bank that we'll use for mode
selection now this is in addition to the
OLED from last time that will also be
using looking at the dip switch since
each of the three dip switch which is
has two possible positions on and off
that means that there are a total of
eight different combinations or
configurations that we can use to invoke
eight different modes in our system and
we'll talk a little bit more in detail
about that shortly but for now let's
focus on the hardware wiring connections
necessary to bring all of this together
because free pins on the hero are going
to start to become a Lim lied Resource
as we build up our system we'll need to
juggle things around a little and be
somewhat strategic about how we design
our connections and layout now as for
the OLED display since the hero really
only provides with us with one way to
send the i2c communication protocol that
it uses we'll have to keep that
connection unchanged so the analog
A4 and A5 pins will be used just as they
have been before now the four-digit
seven segment display here needs two
hero digital output pins and so we'll
connect those two pins the CLK and the
Dio to pins two and three so pins two
and three down here in the digital row
are located as we're looking at it here
over on the left and in this setup we've
chosen to make that connection using
these two wires here here's the brown
wire that's connecting for the CLK
connection and this white wire right
here for the Dio connection so those are
connected to pins the CLK to pin 3 and
the Dio to pin
two we're leaving leing most of the
remaining digital pins down here on the
hero
free and that's in
anticipation them needing to be used in
the future as we build up our system
leaving those free however means that
we'll need to do something a little bit
different than before in order to read
the status of our three dip switches and
so you'll note here that what we've
chosen to do is to connect the logic
test points that is the points here on
the high side of our three logic
resistors our 10 kiloohm resistors we've
chosen to connect those to three
available analog pins up here on this
upper row of pins on the hero switches
one two and three reading from left to
right we've connected to pins
a0
A1 and A2
respectively and we've accomplished that
here using our orange that's for the a z
our Brown for the A1 and our green for
the A2 those three jumper wires are
connected to the
corresponding analog pins up above the
power and the ground connections for all
these subcircuits should be fairly
straightforward to for us to follow now
we've created two common ground buses
this blue line along the bottom and this
blue line up along the top of our
breadboard and connected them together
into a common bus using these black
jumper wires so this is a commonly
available ground to be used uh by all of
our
subcircuits the bottom one down here
provides the ground connections for our
switch logic resistors and completes the
circuit to ground for those when those
switches are thrown the uh upper one the
upper ground line up here is available
for use by our two displays so you'll
notice that this ground is accessed by
the seven segment display at this point
right here and then this jumper provides
ground for the OLED so that's all fairly
straightforward and uh similar to what
we've done in the past the 5vt power is
accessed by both our displays and by the
switch logic using the same Red 5vt Bus
along the upper edge of the breadboard
the upper edge here as it's oriented in
our view here and so you can see that
this common uh we have a a red wire from
the hero that provides 5 volts and then
that's distributed to the switches using
these three red jumpers and then using
this red wire we provide Power that's
available to our uh our o LED display
and this red wire right here it's hiding
a little bit that it connects to the
same Red Bus so that takes care of the
issues of of ground and
power next we need to talk about what to
expect when we run the sketch that we
have written specifically for this
setup the state of the displays will
reflect and will change with the
positions of the dip
switches now as we mentioned before with
eight switch configurations possible
that means we have eight different bit
maps that we're going to choose to
display on the o
and those images we can number them
sequentially from zero up to
seven and so this image number will in
turn be displayed as a decimal on the
seven segment display that is if we've
written our sketch correctly we should
get a number here that corresponds to
the image being displayed and the
position of our
switches so as an example
switch number three would be on the
right 1 2 3 going from left to right
switch number three on the right would
represent the so-called least
significant bit and so in a binary
representation it would represent the
one's
position then moving over to the left
switch number two would represent the
two's position and then switch number
one would be in The Four's position
and if we could continue this if we had
a fourth switch we would have more
combinations so if we had four switches
instead of three then the most
significant bit would be in the E
position and then we would be able to
address the binary representation of
numbers from zero up to
15 but that's more than we need to worry
about right now we have our hands full
with just three switches and eight
combinations
now one very important point to mention
before we try running the sketch has to
do with the bit map data that we'll be
using to draw on the OED
display if you've already been through
the software instruction for today
you'll have noticed that we improved the
readability of the sketch by relegating
the bulky bitmap data out to an ex
external file and you'll see this in the
sketch line where it says hash include
switch bit
maps. now in order to compile and run
correctly the sketch needs to know where
to find this external file containing
the bitmap data and so for this reason
you need to make sure to place the
switch bit maps. file into the same
folder on your computer where Theo
sketch file is located before you use
the IDE to compile and upload your
sketch to run with that important detail
out of the way it seems like we're ready
to go ahead and try out our work so
we'll go to the IDE and we'll upload our
sketch and we'll have to wait a few
moments for the sketch to
load and once it has loaded we should
expect to see something on our
displays and here we are all right so we
see that it comes up with a display
number of zero which should correspond
to the binary zero all switches off and
that's how we have the the switches
configured and the OLED correctly
mirrors the state of the switches
because we have an image here that
detects three off switch
now we would expect that if we flip
switch number one that's the one on the
left that's the most significant bit we
would get 1 4
02s and 0 1es or in other words image
number four so let's see if that works
so I'll reach in here and flip the
leftmost
switch and sure enough we get number
four on our display and we get image
number four which mirrors the state of
our
switches all right likewise we can
activate image number two so I'll go
ahead and return that back to zero and
flip switch number
two and that gives us binary number two
and we get the corresponding image and
we can do that with the least
significant bit taking the third switch
and that's the one in the ones position
and activate that and we get the
corresponding change in the image and
we're now looking at image number
one so we can get additional
combinations by having more than one
switch in the on position so for example
if I leave the number three switch on
and
then rais the number two switch I now
have one one and one two two for a total
of three binary three and we have the
correct
image I have all three switches on
that's the binary seven so there's image
seven there's the the number seven and
there's image seven and I could continue
to look at all the possibilities so
here's switch number two off and so that
corresponds to Binary 5 and so
on so we see here that the displayed
number
and the images correctly correspond to
the configuration of our switches and
that indicates that our wiring and our
logic design were
successful so I hope that you were
successful too and we will see you for
the next day's addition to our system as
we add on and add functionality so we
look forward to seeing you
then as another Cosmic day con cludes I
can't help but Beam with pride
navigating the nebulous intricacies of
binary and ensuring our Hardware is
primed and ready you've tackled it all
with Stellar Precision it feels like
just yesterday we were stranded and look
how far we've
come but let's not let the Stardust get
to our heads just yet tomorrow awaits a
crucial task fixing our docking gear
using Knowledge from today a smooth
descent is the grand finale of our
Interstellar Journey rest up and
recharge with will need all hands and
switches on Deck to ensure we land as
gracefully as a feather in zero gravity
until then sweet Celestial
[Music]
dreams