[Music]
good morning Stellar traveler as the
gentle hum of our ship fills the void
around us we find ourselves at the
precipice of a momentous task Can You
Feel the anticipation just 48 hours away
from the mother ship and we're ramping
up for our final challenge repairing the
ducking gear this isn't just any repair
it's a symphony of all we've learned all
the tools we've acquainted ourselves
with converging for one grand purpose
let's ensure that when we touch down we
do so with more grace than a dying star
The Horizon of Home beckons and we have
much to do today's task Explorer is both
intricate and comprehensive remember the
code from our previous day's Adventure
we'll need that along with the Symphony
of our passive buzzer and the visual
Allure of our
ol and ah don't forget the 4x4 keypad
which will serve as the bridge between
our will and the Majestic mechanism of
our landing
gear yesterday we ensured our dip
switches are safety compliant so once
all three are flipped that very keypad
will be our instrument to both deploy
and retract our Landing system the rest
of our tools will come Center Stage
tomorrow let's glide through this with
the Precision of a St our ship pilot
shall we let's move on to how we're
actually going to code this we need a
way to figure out if we have flipped all
three of the dip switches and passed our
necessary safety checks we can probably
do this by checking all of the switches
States and only continuing once they've
been activated next we need to add
today's additional Logic for our 4x4
keypad we will be using that to deploy
our landing gear it doesn't necessarily
matter which button makes it deploy so
let's just use a that should work let's
review the cast instructural material
from your mission resources and give it
a quick
test hello everybody and welcome back to
day 28 of the Lost in Space code
explanations today again I'm starting
with an empty sketch and the reason why
is because I want to make sure that you
guys set this up correctly since we're
going to be using a header file and this
file is going to be including all of our
bit Maps we want to make sure that we
get this right when we see our code on
day 28 you'll notice we have the
following we have obviously the wiring
diagram we have the code that we
normally see but you'll notice down
below we also have an additional piece
of code which is our landing garor
bitmap. and the way we can create this
properly is we can obviously copy our
first code here by going up here hitting
the copy and when we go up to the next
bit now we've copied this we can hit
verify and oh look at that you got got
an error here and if you're getting this
error it's because you need to go up to
the top right hit new tab and type in
landing uncore garor bit
maps. hit enter make sure you copy the
code from that other file and make sure
you paste it all in here if you go and
you hit verify now you'll notice that
nothing breaks because it has the bit
maps and it knows where it's at so
that's perfect if you're getting that
error please make sure you obviously
include that in the
IDE obviously at the very top we have a
lot of the same stuff we've done every
other day I can just delete a lot of it
boop boop get rid of that and it will
still function the same because .h is
automatically included assuming you're
using the Arduino IDE if I go down here
we have all the libraries we used we
have this and we obviously just included
just now the L New Year bit Maps make
sure that was done correctly finally we
have array of pointers just like
yesterday if you remember for the
switches we have it for the Lander bit
maps and this is going to create a nice
cool smooth animation showing the Lander
um extending and bringing back its
gears down here below we have the
calculate how many gear bit Maps we have
divided we have in total so if we ever
want to add more bit maps to this
animation we can uh if and you're free
to do so and that's just what this does
so we have gear bit map count we could
just assume that it's going to be four
but if you ever want to add more
yourself this is going to make it so you
can without any issues whatsoever
finally we have an enumerator gear state
in this uh we have the following we have
a total of three different states that
the gears can be in for our landing
gear zero is going to be where we're
considered
idle lowering is going to be equal to
one and we're going to set raising is
equal to netive one and we're going to
have this thing called index and index
is going to be what keeps track of what
state that we are in the reason why
that's important is because later on in
the code we'll have a potential issue
and that's that if somebody were to
raise a landing gear uh before we were
fully ready to land
tomorrow we got to make sure that we are
able to cancel all of the landing thing
at any point if we accidentally rais the
landing gear we don't obviously want to
land at that point so we have an ability
to back out down here below we have the
four-digit seven segment display
setup that we're just going to call the
bit map number display which basically
is going to tell us what bit map that
we're displaying finally we have the
defined pins for our dip switch
again we're using analog because of the
fact that we won't have enough on day 29
otherwise and finally we're introducing
our 4x4 key bad button Matrix now the
total amount that we're going to be
using on day 29 is going to be strange
though you'll notice that we are only
going to be using rows 1 2 and three and
we will be using all four comms which
means the very bottom row of our 4x4
keypad is not going to be used that is
going to be completely unused but
luckily the way we have our setup for
our keypad in our library and how
awesome it is is we can do that we don't
need to have it plugged in we can use 10
11 12 13 and 987 the reason we're doing
this and we're not we didn't have six
normally we would have had something
like six here before but we don't
because we don't need that last row so
it makes it a lot easier for us finally
we have the Lander controls we have the
controls known as
unused unused and then obviously raise
and lower gear today we're just focusing
on raise and lower
gear all the rest of them right now are
unused and going tomorrow on day 29
we'll use
these this this this and this and also
this but we won't technically this will
end up being unused tomorrow and this
will be unused tomorrow tomorrow we'll
be focusing on the direction of our ship
and making sure that we're actually able
to control it once a Landers are
disengaged but here we have the raise
and lower gear for our landing
gear right now most of it is unused so
we just focus on these two here in the
top right corner we down here have the
keypad Lander controls where we are
going to obviously create the keypad and
we're calling it Lander controls so the
seven segment is display was called the
bit map number display and if you ever
want to call any of the nice keypad
function we can use the Lander controls
and call whatever we want to from there
finally we have the approach State now
here is uh some of the states that our
code will one will be running through
we'll be building on this later to
reform the actual approach flight and
landing in the Mother Ship Bay so this
isn't going to be used too heavy right
now but this will be used tomorrow in
much more detail starting in setup we
have a Serial begin 9600 technically
this doesn't do anything we don't
technically print anything so if you
accidentally deleted this um it
technically wouldn't break anything down
here below we have the following we have
the bit map number display we're going
to set up we're going to configure that
the dip switch just like yesterday the
Lander display just like yesterday we're
also setting the text font which is
something we didn't do
yesterday we're defining how the max
height the text height is calculated and
we're setting the y coordinate to be the
top of the tallest character so that
whenever we print it we want it to
obviously print from the top down
instead of the bottom up so that it will
display on the thing so if we did z0 it
will be showing on the display instead
of kind of off the
display down here we have the loop
function which is where the most of our
Logic for today is going and let me tell
you there's quite a bit of it so I'm
going to be going through this kind of
briefly otherwise I'm going to be here
kind of forever a lot of this logic down
here is mostly going to be displaying
the graphics on our display and I will
primarily instead of going into every
single bit of calculation I will be
primarily going over a higher level of
it we have the first three of these we
have the thrust lever the systems lever
and the confirmation lever for our dip
switch this is going to be using a lot
of logic from the previous day so if
depending on what state it's in we will
be displaying a certain type of bit map
on the screen or changing up the text
that's on the screen we're going to
start with the index being
zero as you recall I mentioned up here
we're going to be keeping track of what
uh State we're in the gear state by
using an index counter that counter is
going to be here the current gear bit
map
index when we have the approach State
meaning we're approaching Mothership
we're going to be going into approach
initialization and when we're in the
initial gear State the initial gear
State we're going to be just setting to
idle which is going to be
zero going down here below we have the
obviously very first initial state which
is going to be the approach
initialization state so if switch
approach state depending on what state
we're
in again up here we have initialization
pre- fight and final initialization is
going to be the very first case and if
we're in this state and only if we're in
this state we're going to assume that
all switches are off now and we're ready
for the pre-flight and that means that
we're going to switch our new state
going forward to the approach PreFlight
assuming that all of them are off we're
going to go into pre-flight if we're now
in pre-light flight pre-flight all
switches are off to begin with if the
chance happens that through this version
of loop all of the levers are switched
to on that means that we're going to be
uh going into the approach final State
and we're going to switch the final
State once all three are on finally this
is the most complicated State because
there's just so much U more stuff in a
lot of this if we are in the approach
final State we're going to get the
Lander controls. getet key this is where
we're going to be able to press on our
keypad to raise and lower the landing
gear if we want to lower the gear we
will current gear bitmap index we're
going to lower the gear and we're going
to set the gear state to gear
lowering what this means is that since
we're in the gear lowering State we have
another whole bit of case statements
down here which says if it's lowering we
want it to display the graphic and we
want it to show the animation of the
gear lowering on the OLED display and
then obviously we want it to continue
and break after that otherwise we have
the raiseed gear state so if it was
lower and we're going to raise it up
from there we want to show the gear
raising which is essentially that same
animation but in reverse because we
specified our gear States is either 0 1
or negative 1 we can change bit maps by
simply adding the gear state to our
current gear bitmap index that makes it
really easy so if we want to lower it we
can just you know subtract one and if we
want to add it if we want to switch to
the other state we can plus one Etc
makes it really easy for just basic
logical math computations to make that
work if the gear animation is completed
that means that the index is either zero
or whatever then we can change our gear
to the idle State here assuming that the
animation is complete
finally here's all the logic using the
first page next page all these other
methods to actually show those
animations on the
display we get this is all this stuff
here we have all of the logic here that
simply says if you have switch one on
switch two off switch three on whatever
we want to tell what we actually have on
and what we don't have on this is all
the logic to do that here we have the Y
offsets to show where where we want to
put it on screen we have obviously the X
offset is just zero we have the text you
want to display at the top and then
finally we have the final display
functionality here which is just simply
going to display once everything is all
done and ready to go we also have the
liftoff this is just a helper function
that just takes whatever the liftoff
State we're in and it just simply says
init or pre-flight so if we're
initialization we'll say init and if
we're in the pre-flight case we're going
to say pre-flight and that's something
that we can then put on our Ola display
um a little bit easier than the case
that we have here so just gives us text
to work with that we can then use to
work finally we have the draw string
function that we're using that is
another helper function that is used for
on the display as well just to display
any string we want to on our OLED at a
specific x and y coordinate and that's
it that is the bulk of day 28 we don't
have currently anything for controlling
our ship to get to the Mothership and we
also don't have anything for what
happens when we do get to the end of the
mothership a confirmation of success or
failure if we landed successfully
because that is coming tomorrow and I
look forward to seeing you then see you
on the last day tomorrow and day 29 safe
travels and your journey is almost at an
welcome to the day 28 wiring example
video today we'll take the next step in
building up our Landing system we're
almost finished but we still have some
components and functions to add before
we're ready for the grand
finale our additions today will allow us
to visualize and control the status of
our vehicle's landing gear now last time
time our dip switches and OLED display
were hooked up in testing mode but today
they'll be giving us real time control
and feedback on the landing system most
of this is being accomplished using
exactly the same wiring and Hardware
that we used on day 27 and it's brought
over then
unmodified however the one big addition
today
is our
reintroduction of the push button keypad
which here we'll be using for landing
gear deployment and
retraction quickly reviewing our setup
here all the power and the ground
connections are exactly the same as last
time so you can review day 27 if there's
anything there that's not clear likewise
all the display data lines and the
switch logic
connections remain just the
same now we're finally using those hero
digital pins that we set aside last time
and we're using those to connect to our
keypad using an 8 conductor ribbon
cable counting here from bottom to top
on on the keypad our eight keypad pins
are connected through this ribbon cable
to Hero pins 6 through 13 and those
should correspond to what you see in
your software
sketch that pretty much covers all the
modifications to the hardware for today
so with that review complete we're ready
to go ahead and run our day 28th sketch
to verify our setup and operation up to
this
point note that just as on day 27 we
have a new set of landing gear display
bit maps that are coming in through an
external file so make sure you've
included the file landing gear bit
maps. in the folder with your sketch
before trying to upload and run it I've
done that already so let's go ahead and
try it so we'll go over to the IDE and
we'll begin the upload of our
sketch it'll take a few moments here for
it to compile and
upload and we're just about
there okay so we can see that we started
with all of our switches in the off
position and our status indicator here
on the OLED
verifies that we have all three of our
switches in the off position and we're
in the countdown pre-flight condition
now before I go any further I just want
to point out that if you've looked at
the software sketch for today you'll
have noticed that we are using two of
the buttons on our keypad for landing
gear control the upper right hand button
a uh here's a little reminder of how
we've mapped those buttons button a in
the upper right hand corner will be used
to deploy the landing gear and if we
need to pull the landing gear back up
button B just below a will be uh the one
that we'll use for that okay so let's go
ahead and run through uh a little
rehearsal here and pretend like this is
an actual approach and Landing sequence
so first thing I'm going to do is I'm
going to uh sequentially enable each one
of our of our dip switches so switch
number one going to the on position and
we can see that we have an on condition
for
thrusters next we'll go to switch number
two place it in the on
position and so we have a second on
finally we'll confirm and when we press
the third button when we uh rather uh
throw the third switch this should put
us in
to Readiness
mode and so now you can see that uh
We've successfully gotten through the
Preparatory phase and we're now ready to
test landing gear deploy so when it is
time to deploy the landing gear we
should be hitting button number a uh
button designated a here and when we do
so we can see landing gears come down
and if we want to reverse that that and
pull the landing gear back up button a
does that for us and we can repeat that
if necessary if I press a again it
doesn't have any effect because the
landing gear are already down I can pull
them back up with
B so everything seems to check out
correctly we're just one more rather big
step away from being ready for arrival
in docking so we'll see you then for the
big day
29 Explorer as we sail through the vast
expanse of space our monolithic Mother
Ship beckons in the distance our docking
gear stands ready like a faithful
Guardian ensuring our safe descent we're
on the cusp of completing a journey few
could even imagine let alone accomplish
rest and rejuvenate the Final Approach
awaits Us in less than a day tomorrow we
return home good night and dream of the
familiar sights and sounds awaiting
[Music]
us