[Music]
hey Explorer launch day up for it let's
let's just do another gear check we're
at a critical juncture so let's go over
what's in store we have a full roster of
equipment to wire up number one our dip
switch to toggle all system functions
and initiate the countdown of our seven
segment display number two our
OED which will serve as our control
panel display and number three our
trusty buzzer to keep us Alert in case
of any safety concerns our task is
immense our hearts are stout and our
minds sharper than ever so let's roll up
our sleeves strap in and prepare for
liftoff the vastness of space beckons
and we will answer it call to paraphrase
an ancient Teran to close to Infinity
but never Beyond we're going to put
together our OLED seven segment display
dip switch and passive buzzer into one
masterful circuit this intricate
Symphony of Hardware will be the central
nervous system for our liftoff the OLED
will serve as our main control panel
display the seven segment display will
take care of our crucial Countdown the
dip switch will be our trigger to
initiate all system functions and the
passive buzzer will be our trusty
Watchdog alerting us of any
anomalies today we are adding the grand
finale to our code but before we
initiate the spectacular conflagration
that will power our Escape we need to
start with the smaller Sparks it all
begins with our dip switch dip switch
three systems all need to be on before
we're go to launch timer is wired up
correctly and well to the seven segments
eyes on the clock and then we'll see
what happens there's some instructional
material as usual check things over I'll
do a flight check you know got to make
sure good
luck hello everybody and welcome back to
day 24 of the 30 days lawon space code
explanations today we're going to be
taking what we did on day 23 adding in a
wonderful little dip switch and a
passive buzzer onto our project before
your lift off later today now before we
get into the full bit of the code I want
to talk to you guys about how the
program will work from a higher level
perspective when you first start the
program all of the dip switch positions
should be set to the off position so
that very first state that we can
possibly be in out of five is going to
be called initialization if I go down
here we'll see this wonderful little new
struct that we've cre created that you
guys can actually look at here and this
is the very first state initialization
when all the dip switches are off now
pending is where we're waiting for all
of them to be turned on once they are
all on we have the following we have
countdown now if at any point during
this countdown we turn off one of the
dip switches we're going to go to the
abort State because we just accidentally
cut off the state here and finally if we
do actually make the countdown all the
way to zero we'll finally enter this
liftoff State here but if at again if at
any point we decide to turn that lever
off into the off position we will abort
the countdown and we'll have to then
restart it now let's go over the code
from the top to the bottom and let's
take out the stuff that we talked about
in the days before so that we don't have
to restate that this obviously we've
talked about this in every piece of code
this is included by default by the
Arduino IDE but we're just excluding
putting it in here explicitly just so
you know that it's there here's a seven
segment display the graphics libraries
and of course we talked about the Define
macros yesterday and how they convert
things to minutes and seconds yesterday
down here below we have the pins that
are required for the seven segment
display as well as the Constructor for
the seven segment display so we can make
that and actually call the functions
from the library down here below we now
have the pins for the dip switch is this
is new for today this just simply
defines what pins we're going to be
using pin n will be for our lever uh
thrust pin this one's going to be for
our system lever and this one's going to
be for our confirmation lever down here
below we have the buzzer pin is going to
be equal to six and we're putting that
on a pulse withth modulation pin so that
we can obviously play all the various
tones using pulse withth modulation on
pin six talked about this yesterday
don't need to go over this again this is
just simply
making similar to what we did with the
seven segment display same exact idea
here for our Lander OLED we are also
going to be defining how big our Lander
graphic is so in the very bottom right
of our program we will have a Lander
that when we finally do take off we'll
have a little animation that shoots
itself up to the top of the screen now
we are defining how big that is in bits
and we have 25 by 20 down here say
segment display defining the done value
again talked about this yesterday and on
day 16 here we have the countdown in
milliseconds now one thing that we
changed on this line of code here from
yesterday as you probably have
remembered yesterday we had the
countdown it was 5 Seconds time 1,000
but this time we're changing it to 70 so
it would be a minute and 10 seconds uh
that's what it should display but
however we put this UL here and what
this is going to do is this is going to
going to make it so that we have it be
done as an unsigned long remember when
we're talking about data types signed
variables can go negative unsigned
variables can't go negative um there's
no sign bit at the end which allows it
to determine if it's a positive or
negative number so unassigned variables
don't have that they don't have that
sign and they always by default just use
positive numbers or obviously zero can
be done as well so if we're using
unsigned numbers we're just making sure
because it's a countdown there's no
reason to go to negative 1G -2 neg3 you
know obviously as for a countdown reason
so we're using unsigned and we're
putting this here just to make sure that
there's no way that this can
accidentally be misconstrued uh when we
want to be using onside numbers down
here below we have the en that shows the
five different states that we can
possibly be in throughout this program
now depending on what state we're in
we're obviously going to be executing
things differently so an enumerator is a
Comm and to Define multiple related
values where distinguishing between the
different values is important but the
actual values are not so this is perfect
for something like this when we're
trying to talk about the various states
that our program can be in each name is
then given its own value and in this
case it starts with zero so this would
be zero 1 2 3 and four so out of the
five states it's you can think of it is
almost like an array of uh variables 0 1
2 3 and four so now we've talked about
the enes let's hop down to void setup
and let's go on to here to talk about
what's new for today now obviously we're
talking about serial monitor set to
seven segment display settings set the
OLED settings all stuff we talked about
yesterday finally we're setting all the
dip switch pins as inputs and we're just
going to clear the old display that's it
for the setup let's jump down to Loop
one thing we'll notice though is that
this time we're going through Loop we
are going to have a slight issue with
how we're doing things the reason we'll
have a slight issue is because in order
to keep the beeping and animation steady
we really have to make sure that each
time we go through the loop is the same
amount of time meaning we can't have one
time going through the loop be quicker
than the other times otherwise it could
break things and the way that the
functions in our Graphics library and
tone libraries work they don't really
care they will break if you're not
careful about it so the way we're going
to be doing this is we're basically
going to make sure that the minimum time
that we have to go through Loop is going
to be about 200 milliseconds and we're
going to set a defined value basically
limiting how long it takes to go through
each time occasionally Loops may take
longer but this constant defines the
minimum time each Loop will take at
minimum to run so each iteration going
through this whole bit has to take at
least at at the minimum 200 milliseconds
so that that way we can make sure that
anytime that we call any of our tone or
Graphics things it has enough time to
execute everything it needs to execute
especially when we're using the first p
uh first page next page stuff saving all
that stuff for memory saving reasons we
need to make sure that we actually have
enough time to then execute that since
it does take more time to execute to
save the memory we need for the program
down here in Loop we're going to
obviously initialize our static
variables all the way at the top and
we're going to obviously start here in
the initialization State remember that
en we had before initialization state is
where we're going to start then we're
going to do the following as you
remember last time we had the following
Loop start time these are obviously just
variables to keep track of where we are
in the loop and of course we even have
this Loop toggle equals true which is
just going to be defined to say whether
we are going to be tone or blink a text
this way through the loop so every time
that we go through this loop we're going
to change this variable here to onof on
off so we can keep the looking flashy
and Blinky up at the top with our text
and beeping tones and so on here we have
all the levers um where we're going to
read the state of each lever before we
decide what we're going to do next now
we're after we do all the reading of
what we have we're simply going to
update the display with the current
status of our liftoff sequence this is
either going to be on or off this is
either going to be on or off and this is
either going to be on or off and then we
have obviously one of the five liftoff
states that we can be in as well so
we're going to quickly update the Lander
display this calls a new function we
created this function down below if we
go past all this stuff here we can find
the update OLED display on this display
we set the max Lander speed that it can
go up to the top this is our little
funny little rocket ship we have in the
bottom right corner corner of our
display that will be going up upon
execution we're simply setting the Speed
Max Speed to be five we don't want to go
too fast otherwise it'll just appear off
disappear off the screen way too quickly
and you won't even be able to see the
animation down below we have void update
Lander display taking in those things
and then obviously depending on what
they are we just want to set the up the
display to say what it is properly
expiration Lander left off sequence at
the top and finally we simply just say
if it is on we want to say that it is in
state liftoff aborted if it is in
liftoff then we want to say liftoff but
if we accidentally abort it then it's
aborted else we want to be able to
display as well the is if it's on we
want to put it on otherwise if it's off
we want to put it off in programming
this is going to seem like a very very
awkward thing to look at this here is is
a very interesting unique way to
basically write if thrusters level is
true everything after so you can think
of it this way the question mark is
essentially like the brackets right so
if this is true then you're going to do
the very first one else you're going to
do whatever is after this colon here
this is a very shorthanded way of
writing that entire if statement but
using strings this is basically going to
determine what we're going to display
so if it's on we want to put up we want
to say it's on otherwise if letter is
off we want to say it's off if this is
on we want to say on otherwise off on on
off off same exact thing for all three
of them and we obviously have the all of
those being displayed on our olded panel
and then we just simply update the
display with that information finally we
also have this helper function that
basically turns whatever state it is
into a string so if we're in the state
of an it we want to return the string in
it pending pending countdown we want to
make it active liftoff we can change
this to complete in abort we're just
going to keep abort obviously we use
this up here so lift off to string and
we can get the state of that it's in and
we just return that as a string and push
that onto our display this is the
functionality we discussed yesterday to
display the counter on our seven segment
display this draws a string on our OLED
and this obviously displays our Lander
draws all the boxes and everything to
displayed in the bottom right corner on
our display if we go back to the loop go
back to where we left from here under
the update Lander display after we've
updated the Lander display to display
all the information that we need to have
it display we're basically going to go
down and we're going to make some
decision making decision making based
off of what state we're in the first
state we could possibly be in is is
initialization so if we're
initializing we want to check to see if
all three switches are off false and if
that's the case then we can turn off the
beeping next we have to check to see if
we're in the pending State meaning that
at least one of them is turned on and if
that's the case then if let's just say
all three of them are now turned on at
this execution throughout the loop then
we want to go down here and we want to
make sure that we change eventually this
state to
countdown finally we're going to go and
we're going to say else if liftoff state
is equal to countdown meaning that all
three are now in the on position we'll
simply be keeping track of the state of
the countdown timer and also in the off
chance that one of them happens to be
turned off if not thrust lever or not
system lever or not confirm lever if one
of them happens to be taken off then we
want to switch to the abort State
immediately because obviously we did not
complete the countdown and if we did
successfully get all the way down and
all the way to zero on our liftoff
sequence we want to set the segment on
our seven segment display to done play
it to do tone and obviously update the
Lander and make our little animation
thing in the bottom right go up to the
top make the little ship animation go
up and with that that should be
everything that's required for you to
take your ship up to space today Cadet
for day 24 of the lost and space code
explanations I look forward to seeing
you guys in orbit see you
then welcome to the day 24 wiring
example video all our wiring programming
and simulation practice has finally
brought us here to launch day in this
video I'll walk you through the hardware
setup and operations that should closely
resemble your experience as you prepare
for today's
liftoff this should should provide you
with a final chance to check your
systems and prepare yourself for the
events of the launch sequence including
any contingencies that might crop up
that would require an abort or
recycle to start off let's look over the
complete wiring
setup as we had on the previous day we
are including the seven segment
countdown
display and the O LED
Graphics screen in our system in
addition we're adding the buzzer module
to provide us with audible feedback and
warning indications during the launch
sequence much of the wiring today
resembles the previous days but we've
rearranged the power and ground
distribution just a little bit in order
to service all of our devices in a clean
way as before we've spread things out a
little bit onto a secondary breadboard
in order to make things easier to see
here in the video but you may well have
your circuit wired more compactly than
this in any case you'll notice that in
this example we've actually provided two
ground buses it's really just one ground
bus connected together as one but we're
using both the lower ground bus here on
the bottom side of the breadboard and
the upper ground bus as well you'll see
that the lower ground bus right here is
connected by a black jumper wire to the
hero
ground and this lower ground bus
provides the ground side connection for
our three switch logic resistors and so
this is uh a convenient place for us to
access ground here
we uh also have the uh ground
connections on the
upper ground bus you can just see it up
here on the top side which is used to
provide the negative or ground
connection right here for our buzzer and
we have a jumper that connects over to
the left side to provide ground for our
two display
modules we're able in this example to
get away with just a single plus 5vt bus
and this is distributed from the hero
5vt Supply through this R line and
connects to the upper bus line the red
bus line here along the top side now
you'll see that it supplies our three
switch circuits right here through these
three red lines so these power are
switch circuits which we'll use to
detect status on those
lines and in addition we have a jumper
that extends the 5 volts here over to
the left to provide 5vt Power once again
for our two displays on the left
side so now the last things in terms of
wiring that we need to check are our
output pin connections the positive
signal for the warning buzzer connects
to Hero pin 6 through this yellow wire
right here that connects the positive
terminal of the buzzer to Hero pin
six our three switch status lines switch
one switch two and switch three are in
turn connected to the hero pins 9 8 and
7 and those in this example are
connected by these three wires this
orange brown and green wire connect to
those three hero
pins and finally as we had before the
seven segment clock and Dio lines are
connected to pins five and four down
here on the hero through these two lines
through the uh brown and white lines
that connect to those
pins and the
OLED this display right here the OLED
clock and data lines are fed by the
heroes analog
A5 and A4 pins that's through these this
green and blue wire so that pretty much
summarizes the hardware setup and the
wiring necessary for this uh launch
sequence so now let's run through the
launch countdown sequence we'll load the
sketch and uh we'll run through a
simulated launch of course it won't be
simulated for you so that's why we want
to be careful to uh figure everything
out here in advance now in that Spirit
I'm actually going to start off right
now with an intentional mistake what I'm
going to do is I'm going to leave one of
the control switches in the armed
position rather than in its correct off
position which we would expect for
initialization so let's go ahead and
load the sketch and see what happens in
this
circumstance so going to the
IDE go ahead and upload the
sketch uploading and compiling is
done and we have a warning buzzer and we
have an indication that we are not able
to begin the liftoff sequence we have a
problem so we notice oh yes we did not
have the switches properly configured so
I'm going to go ahead and switch those
back into their proper off configuration
so that we can begin the sequence
properly I guess what I'll do right now
is I'll reset the hero so we can start
from a clean start but now with the
switches in the correct
position and there we go we now have a
liftoff sequence prompt that says the
countdown is pending and so all we need
to do now is to in
order arm the three switches so first
we'll do the Thruster
switch switch one we get an indication
on the OLED that that system is on
second
switch for systems is on and confirmed
and so finally to confirm launch will uh
throw the final switch into the on
position and we should see the
initiation of our countdown so here we
go switch is on and countdown clock is
underway so at this point we can go
ahead and uh wait for the countdown to
run down and uh proceed with launch
however let's anticipate a possible
problem let's suppose that prior to
launch commit we notice that there are
something not quite right perhaps
there's something loose in the cabin or
or or something uh isn't really ready
for launch so we can go ahead and abort
the launch by flipping one of the
switches back to
off and sure enough we've aborted the
launch the countdown has halted and we
uh are going to await further
instructions so I'll go
ahead turn all the switches back to off
and we'll
reset the hero one more time and this
time we'll run it through to a nominal
countdown and launch and hopefully
that'll cover all the possibilities that
we're likely to see when we actually go
through with a launch so resetting the
hero we're back in the nominal countdown
pending mode the switches are ready to
go so let we fixed all the problems that
we had so let's go ahead with our
countdown and
launch first switch is
on second switch is on and now for final
confirmation countdown has
begun so now all we have to do is wait
for the automattic IC System to bring us
through the final count and to
launch and we're in the final seconds of
the countdown 9 8 7 6 5 4 3 2 1
lach and we're finally on our
way good luck with your launch if all
goes well the next time we talk to you
you'll be safely in orbit so we'll see
you
then the time has finally come Explorer
on my mark you'll flip the three levers
in sequence to initiate the countdown to
launch this is what we have been waiting
for we'll only have one shot at this
flip lever one to initiate Thruster
power
now
well done flip the second lever to power
supplemental launch circuits on my mark
now you're doing perfectly so far
Explorer now ready yourself to flip the
third lever and initiate our countdown
on my mark
now the sequence successfully initiated
Explorer performing failsafe
Diagnostics data readouts normal
diagnostic shows power system are
humming beautifully your moments from
freedom in the stars hold tight now
Explorer ready your body and mind for
liftoff
[Music]
go I didn't think we'd make it you did
great Explorer I mean you covered so
much code and wiring in such a short
span of time you rock we're in space
where we're meant to be well not quite
where we're meant to be but once we're
at the Mother Ship we'll oh oh
[Music]
no