[Music]
good morning Stellar Navigator we're
still bobbing a top the cosmic waves of
an alien ocean but not for long today we
can sit back and relax knowing we've
done everything we can to prepare for
lunch our big day tomorrow tomorrow yeah
big day lots of moving parts will be
launched tomorrow and everything needs
to happen at precisely the right time or
the ocean will turn into an Explorer
flavored crater time time is of the
essence time is short time won't give
you
time okay we're not quite done we need a
timer all right you clever Explorer
today today's Hardware task is a piece
of interstellar cake we're simply
welcoming back our old friend the seven
segment display to our current setup yes
that's right the same one that played a
crucial role in lighting our way up from
the deep ocean this won't be anything
new to you just plug the seven segment
display into the wiring layout from
yesterday easy right with each step
we're getting closer to our grand
liftoff as always ensure that your
connections are firm and correct let's
get to it let's have a small detour to
Define macros when you see Define in our
code it's essentially a way of creating
a shortcut or an alias we set a keyword
equal to a specific value or string of
code this way instead of having to type
out the whole thing every time we can
just use the keyword it is also useful
when we have the same thing written in
multiple places like occasionally
pinouts so we only need to change it
once this makes our code cleaner and
easier to understand
it's like having a code name or a short
hand for your favorite lengthy space
lingo all right on to today's simulation
we'll be adapting the done code from our
day 16 Adventures for our seven segment
display this time it'll be there to
Signal the end of our countdown like a
digital pat on the back if everything
goes according to plan tomorrow we can
connect everything up to our
thrusters and then well you know the
drill lift off we're in the home stretch
Explorer the stars are within our grasp
let's ensure this simulation goes off
without a hitch and prepare ourselves
for the Big
Show for today's cating spree we're
going to cook up a function that sends
us on a countdown Journey it's going to
be an exhilarating watch I promise once
we're done we'll celebrate by lighting
up our seven segment display with the
victory chant done just like we did back
on day 16 imagine it like a digital high
five if all all goes well this is
precisely where we'll inject the codes
for our long awaited liftoff tomorrow
it's exciting isn't it hold on to that
Curiosity Explorer as you walk through
every line of our code in the daily
breakdown as always I've cashed it to
your mission resources so buckle up it's
coding
time hello everybody and welcome back to
day 23 of the 30 days Lost in Space code
explanations today we're going to be
introducing the seven segment display in
order to a nice countdown timer for
tomorrow's liftoff since a seven segment
display is something we have talked
about previously in the past just is a
heads up if you want to learn about a
lot of the stuff that's talked about in
today's lesson a lot of the stuff that's
referencing the seven segment display
I'm going to glance over as it was
heavily discussed in day I believe 16 so
take a look there if you're interested
in any of Refreshers on the seven
segment display going down you'll see we
included that library and down below
that that we included the library from
yesterday so that we can draw our nice
fancy little shapes that we all enjoy in
particular we're going to be using it to
draw a spaceship on our olet display so
that's going to be really cool later on
down below that we now have a new
concept I'm introducing today and this
is called a macro now I'm sure you've
seen before where you can say Define you
know whatever pin to be five exactly
right here for here's a good example for
the seven segment display but you can
also use this to create essentially
calculations almost do the exact same
thing as functions another way you could
write this could be int number of
minutes with the input for this function
of milliseconds and then you could have
return obviously inside return
milliseconds plus 999 ID 1,000 / 60 this
could be the exact same thing um but
this is a nice shorthand version that
does the exact same thing so anytime we
want to calculate the number of minutes
uh when we know how many milliseconds
there are we can just take this and then
pass in the amount that we want here and
it'll do the calculation and return it
for us and the reason we're using the
Divide here is because obviously that
will get us a number of minutes and then
this is another symbol that I don't
think we've talked about too much this
is modulus and modulus gives us the
extra after a divide so let's think
about whole numbers for a second so you
can understand what modulus is so let's
say you have a person named Sally and
Sally has three apples and let's say she
has two friends and if you were to do a
divide she doesn't want any apples she
wants to give all of them to her friends
right so if you were to divide using
this symbol obviously um you would get
exactly one and then half but let's just
say you wanted to know the remainder and
you want to divide only an even number
so you can't give half an apple the
modulus gives whatever the division is
so each person gets one one and then the
remainder is one so each person gets one
and then you have one left over the r
remainder of one the thing that's left
over at the end is what the modulus
equates to so if we go back to our code
and we want to look at this the number
of seconds is simply going to take the
number of minutes and then how many
seconds are left after that right and
then that's what the modulus gives you
so if you only if if you have still like
you know 32 seconds out of the minute
well that's what number of seconds is
going to get you 32 seconds out of the
minute the reason these calculations are
going to be really nice in the later on
in the code is that it's going to be
able to let us display exactly what we
want to on our seven segment display
which we'll be showing here in just a
minute obviously these are the defines
for the pins for our TM display all this
was talked about in how the library
works I believe on day 16 so I'm just
going to briefly go over that and down
here we talked about this yesterday this
is we need to Define our Lander display
from our library and wonderfully we can
just use this here and so instead of
calling this every time we're going to
call Lander display because that's a lot
easier to call then this mumble jumble
garbage down here we have the height and
width of of the Lander that we're going
to be drawing on our OLED today and we
will be drawing that using the library
up here that gives us all the functions
to draw the squares and triangles and
all this other stuff we can say done on
the seven segment display by doing this
again explained in day 16 each of the
segments defining each one that's lit up
for d for o for n and for E down here we
have the countdown milliseconds in how
much time we want it to countd down so
if we want to change the countdown and
instead of being 5 Seconds which is how
this is currently at to let's just say
we want to make the countdown 30 seconds
we can
change that right here if we so desire
going down into setup setup's actually
pretty big today normally all we would
be doing in setup is saying you know
here's the pins here's the pin outs that
need to be set here's whatever here for
example we're setting the brightness of
our display because we only really need
to do that once um for our seg seven
segment display we're clearing it the
land display we're just going to
initialize it with the OLED which is
going to set the pinouts Etc set the
text font set the reference height text
S the font position to top so all the
text going forward will be rendered from
the top down so instead of it being by
calling this function we're going to
allow it so as I explained yesterday so
as you recall when as we talked about
yesterday you can if you want to display
the text like hello world and you're on
our little OLED display by setting the
position to the top it's going to start
here and render it down like this but if
you didn't have that and you had it set
the other way it would start from here
and it would then say h e l l o world
you know like that but the issue is that
obviously so if you wanted to say it at
0 for example that's going to be off
screen so by putting it so it renders
from the top and just setting that
position that in here in the code we're
going to make it so that it uh when you
do it it's going to start from the very
top left finally we have probably I
would argue the most complicated thing
that I've had to teach so far given the
code that we've looked at in general now
I want you to remember what device we're
using we're using a
microcontroller that has a very very
limited amount of memory on it a limited
amount of ram so only a certain amount
of functionality can be done now let's
be real we've already done quite a few
amazing aming things with the very very
limited processing power that we have
available to us but with that being said
I think we're finally on day 23 and
we're just starting to finally hit some
limitations so as you might know
Graphics take a lot to render a lot of
memory to render Graphics there are
however methods that you can use to
reduce the amount of ram necessary it
does does take a little bit more
processing time in order to do that but
there are methods to do that so if
you're going to be drawing an image on
the screen in this case anytime we want
to update our screen we literally have
to tell it put this pixel at this point
put this pixel at this point put this
pixel at this point essentially you know
we're saying which ones we want to turn
on we want to say which ones we want to
turn off what we can do is we can get
the entire defined like let's take all
this and then plast it to the screen but
but um that's going to take a lot of
memory so what happens is first your
code does some calculations right it
says Okay I want to display a smiley
face on the screen that's what your
functionality is for let's just say this
theoretical program okay so you could do
this in a few different ways one is you
could Define okay let's I want to draw
this I first this I and then this is all
being saved in memory right now this is
not on the display and then I want to
draw the nose and then I want to draw
the big old smiley face and this is all
memory and then I want to push it now
push the entire thing right now all of
it all at once this entire face all on
here this will all being stored in
memory is on here and eventually goes
down to be empty so this is memory and
now just empty and then this turns to
obviously the face the issue with that
is that by doing it that way way you're
going to store a lot of extra stuff in
memory all at once so the amount of
memory you needed to store all that
extra volume of stuff in this top left
is a lot more so instead of writing
everything that you have in all the
screen all at once we can save a little
bit to memory at a time and we can send
a little bit to the screen at a time and
remember this is going to happen so
quickly that it doesn't really matter at
the end of the day because it's so quick
your eyes won't even be able to really
see
it let's start
by step one we're going to draw maybe
the top left or we're going to draw like
the very first little bit of the image
right it's going to be the eye and then
that very first part of the nose Okay
step two and then after each step we're
going to push this to the display so
this is now going to have this on the
display we're going to push just this so
this is going to be Memory this is going
to be what's actually showing currently
on the display and these four things are
going to execute very very quickly so
you don't have to to like think too
heavily about it because it's not like
you're going to see these in between
changes cuz the computer's processing
everything so quickly so the first way
we showed of doing it is by just taking
the entire face loading it into memory
and then pushing the entire thing to
display but by doing it this way you can
use 1/4 of the amount of memory in this
theoretical scenario by just putting
this in memory pushing it this into
memory pushing it this into memory
pushing it and this in memory pushing it
which uses way way way less memory to do
it that way and you can divide it up as
little as you want or as much as you
want that's entirely up to however
whoever designs the algorithm to do that
in this case the algorithm was made by
the library and they use a function to
do all of this it's called first page
and next page and you usually do this in
a do while type structure of a loop and
what it'll do is it'll say it'll just
call first page and then it'll say do
all this stuff stuff we're basically
going to what we want to do is we want
to essentially instead of loading parts
of a smiley face into memory we want to
load into memory the strings exploration
Lander liftoff sequence and uh countdown
active and then we want to obviously
display a picture of our our Lander in
the very bottom right corner right as
the countdown timer is going to take off
and this so we're going to be storing
bits and pieces of this into memory in a
form of a loop to save on obviously The
Limited memory that our controller has
then we're obviously going to Blink the
countdown timer on our timer before
beginning the countdown and we're also
going to after all this is completed and
all that setup is done we're going to
jump to Loop time remaining is a static
variable which means it's going to
remember the value that it had last time
we went to the loop so this is
essentially going to be as effective as
a global variable sort of kind of in its
own roundabout way but we don't actually
have to make it a global variable next
we have this static variable called
countdown start time and this is quite
literally going to get the start time of
when it got to this point in the code
when it calls Mill Millis or uh is is
function built into the Arduino library
and all it does is it gets it checks to
see how the time from the very beginning
of the execution on your board to the
second it hit this line of code so that
what this is going to do is it's going
to get the exact moment it hit right
here next for debugging we're just going
to print the time remaining and we're
going to put the time remaining on the
counter display so hopefully these match
up if not you might want to check the
wiring on your 7 segment display finally
if the time remaining has officially hit
zero then we want to display done on our
seven segment display if it doesn't then
obviously check to make sure that the
wiring is correct and then go down and
we should by using the first page last
page memory saver um functionality that
I really really do enjoy we're going to
display the following information on our
OLED and those are going to be
expiration Lander lift off aborted we
have the confirmation systems and
thrusters all off and then we're going
to have the countdown abort because
that's something we're going to be
getting into tomorrow down here below we
have the functionality that calculates
the elapsed time essentially how much
time that we have been executing in the
loop and this is going to be the Millies
which is what time it is right now at
this point of execution minus the
countdown time where we called it
earlier so we're just counting the time
between this line of code and then we're
going to count the time between this
line of code and if the elapse time is
less than the countdown
milliseconds then we're going to Simply
set the time remaining equal to
countdown milliseconds minus the elapse
time otherwise time remaining is zero
and finally we have this functionality
here for our seven segment display all
this is going to do is it's just simply
going to tell us how many minutes and
seconds we have left on the counter so
if we put something like 70 seconds then
it will be able to display it as one 10
or you know what I mean minute seconds
so this can work with any any number of
seconds technically if you try to do
something larger than 99 seconds you
will probably not be able to display it
properly using the display but I don't
know why you'd want a timer that long
anyway next we have the draw string down
here which simply just draws a string on
our OLED and we used this yesterday and
finally we have the display Lander so
this draws an image of our Lander with
triangles in various frames um
essentially rectangles and X location Y
location um relative to the upper left
corner and with that that should be the
end of day 23 code explanations it was a
long one and tomorrow is probably going
to be just as long just so be prepared
see you
then welcome to the day 23 wiring
example video last time we succeeded in
testing out the function and programming
of our OLED Gra trffic display today
we'll take another step toward getting
our craft ready for launch by
incorporating the display into our
countdown checkout system using what
we've learned in previous days we'll be
displaying the minutes and seconds to
lift off using the four-digit s segment
numerical display while simultaneously
providing system status information to
the pilot on the
OLED now to wire up this combination of
devices we need four wires each for both
of our displays connected to the hero
two of these wires the black ground and
the red plus 5 volts are common to the
two displays and can be shared now we
might choose to share these connections
using a breadboard bus as we've done
several times in the past and is shown
on our provided illust ative wiring
diagram
alternatively you can find equivalent
ways to wire the connections that might
be easier or more convenient for your
circumstances as an example you'll
notice that here since I've been using
an extra breadboard to provide
convenient connections to the OLED
display it was easiest for me to share
the ground and 5 Vols directly on the
corresponding Columns of this extra
breadboard thereby avoiding the Clutter
of a few extra wires we see that the
OLED is connected just as before to the
hero with the clock that is the green
wire and the data the blue wire
connected to pins A5 and A4 respectively
as for the four digit display right here
the power and ground are tapping off the
same
two RedBoard columns as used by the
OLED while for this display the clock
and Dio wires go to the hero output pins
five and four and those numbers agree
with what's specified in the hash defin
lines in our software sketch if you want
to check that now whether you choose to
wire your circuit up using power and
ground buses or perhaps using a shortcut
similar to this you'll want to try to
keep in mind to set aside some blank
real estate on the breadboard in
anticipation of the additional
components that we'll be adding to our
launch system in the coming days as we
uh build up things and and get them
ready for launch for now all we have
left to do is to run our sketch for
today and verify that the things we've
built so far are functioning as designed
if we review the sketch we see that we
would expect the sequence to begin by
initializing the countdown clock and
flashing it on and off three
times then we should also see an
introductory graphic
on the OLED
screen next our numerical display should
enter a test countdown mode showing the
time left until liftoff and then finally
when the countdown reaches zero since
this really is just a test with several
of our Vital systems not yet
operational the sequence is terminated
awaiting further instructions so let's
go ahead now and run it I'll go over to
the uh
IDE upload the sketch take a few seconds
for that to compile and then we should
be looking for the uh beginning of the
countdown flash sequence and the
introductory message on the
OLED so our compilation phase is almost
done and there we go there's 1 minute
and 10 seconds and the countdown has
begun and we've got our
introductory message on the OLED indic
indicating that our countdown sequence
is active and the countdown is underway
so in just a little under 1 minute we
should reach zero and at that point the
countdown will be halted as this is a
test so we'll just uh sit and watch this
and see uh if everything finishes up as
expected 30 seconds left in the
countdown
and in just 10 more seconds we should
reach the end so we'll watch the OLED
and see what it indicates to us 3 2 1
and zero and there we go so our uh
numerical display indicates that we've
finished the sequence we're done and our
OLED indicates the status of our system
we didn't actually lift off we didn't
want to we still have to uh take care of
these additional systems and so the
countdown was aborted but uh this is all
as expected it looks like our countdown
test sketch is a success and we're ready
to to move on so that looks pretty good
so far just make sure that you
understand the logic both of our
software and our Hardware hookups at
this point and then we'll be ready for
the next day's addition to our launch
system so we'll see you then
what an extraordinary day it's been
Explorer we've programmed a successful
countdown simulation if that doesn't
scream Readiness I don't know what does
I'm tempted to have a miniature
celebration right here in this spaceship
of ours even so let's hold off on that
for a while shall we we've got the most
thrilling day ahead of us tomorrow we'll
be tying up all the Loose Ends
integrating countdown with the rest of
our hardware and preparing to break
through this planet's gravitational pull
so rest up tomorrow we're literally
aiming for the Stars sleep well you've
earned it light speed Explorer and try
to be you know on
[Music]
time