[Music]
welcome to the final creative day of the
course congratulations on making it back
to space the mothership is only a short
ways away at this point you have enough
knowledge to make anything you desire
there will be no prompts for today only
a vague request I want you to create
your flag on the moon in quotes or in
this case project on a foreign Planet
something to let people know you were
the first ever to lay foot on this
Uncharted quadrant of space what that
means is totally up to you maybe it's
your name or something that represents
you maybe it's just a cool project that
you are proud of and you just add your
name in the comment of the source code
code whatever it is when you're done be
sure to place your flag in the drop pod
so it can be securely delivered to the
planet's surface
below then like always share on
inventor.
i/f with the hashtag creative
day25 it's been the journey see you back
at the mothership and light
speed
[Music]