[Music]
we're this close to liftoff and you
stepped out priorities Explorer but I
blame myself you need to see a lot more
data at the same time than what four
characters will allow and
Di is not GNA fly the problem is again
power If We Shrunk LEDs down they would
use less and less power meaning we could
use more and more small LEDs good news
Explorer the hero scientists have done
just that they placed a whole bunch of
LEDs on the breadboard threw it in a hot
wash with their underwear and what do
you know they got an organic LED screen
and shredded their
underwear but that's an issue for
another mission today's task will
involve having the screen display a
simple message hello world and an
age-old greeting used by programmers
across the galaxies it's not just a test
it's a symbol of the communication we're
about to establish with our spacecraft
that will ultimately be our ticket back
home remember while these may seem like
simple tests they hold vital importance
for us these checks and validations will
form the basis of our ability to
navigate our way back once we burst
forth from this planet's atmosphere so
Explorer shall we dive into the
wonderful world of user interfaces
buckle up it's going to be an
enlightening ride all right Explorer
let's start with understanding our
screen's display
pins take a look there are some pretty
obscure tlas here but here's what they
mean and do gnd D is ground VCC is power
duh SDA is serial data and sends
information or data over the serial line
using the i2c
protocol I do want to call out that a
Serial clock is isn't something that
wakes you up in the morning it's a
signal that keeps the data here from
getting out of Step or out of sync like
traffic lights at an intersection or
drummers at band practice usually if
they're good I mean some of them just
sound like you've dropped a bag of
marbles on a water cooler you're not a
drummer are
you now let's talk about protocols in
the world of electronic devices a
protocol is a set of rules or procedures
for transmitting data between devices
think of it like a common language that
allows devices to understand each other
two common Protocols are i2c which
stands for inter-integrated circuit and
SPI which stands for serial peripheral
interface both are used for
communication between devices but they
do have their differences i2c like our
display uses just two wires one carrying
a sync signal the other carrying the
data a great system for simple
components to talk to each other SPI
uses four wires and we're not using it
so take a hike no it's important but
right now i2c will do just nicely our
screen uses the i2c protocol simple and
versatile a multi-tool
protocol all right Explorer let's get
our hands on the necessary library and
put our OLED display through its Paces
first things first head over to
inventor. libraries and download the u8g
Library this library is going to be our
faithful Ally when dealing with our OLED
display once downloaded let's get it
installed into our IDE here's how to do
that click on sketch in the menu then
click include library next click add zip
library then simply locate and select
the downloaded file which should be this
one terrific now our library is all set
up and ready to go now that we have our
library installed it's time for a quick
test to ensure our OLED display survived
the crash unscathed what better way to
do this than the classic hello world
check thankfully our new library makes
this easy with a handy function called
drawring which looks like this a string
is a collection of letters and numbers
like a word sentence or even this train
wreck of a term seriously that might be
my new
password this function will let us
display the phrase hello world or any
other string for that matter on our OLED
screen a successful display of this
message will confirm that our o is in
working condition and is ready to
navigate us back home and with that it
looks like you're ready for the next
phase of today's Mission we'll turn to
the instructional material that I've
gathered cached on the computer it is
also readily available in your mission
resources I know I know I know I'm the
best hello everybody body and welcome
back to day 21 of the 30 days loss in
space adventure kit code explanations
first of all I'd like to congratulate
you guys on getting out of the water
from what it looks like here you guys
are currently doing very good it looks
like the solar panels are working at
full capacity and the flotation devices
and all these other calibrations are
done correctly so good on you guys it
looks like you guys are one step closer
to making it back to the Mother Ship but
before we do that we do need to take a
moment to set up the GPS system which is
obviously not working correctly and in
order to do that we're going to need to
set up a new piece of Hardware to make
this display on your control panel
working in fact it's probably the most
important display on your entire control
panel this is the
128x 64 OLED display and this has a
total of you can think of it as 8,000
128 tiny little LEDs if you consider
each pixel to be an individual LED now
I'm sure you've noticed uh we don't have
8,128 pins on our hero board so there's
no way we could ever do that and plus
these pins or pixels I suppose are
substantially lower power as well for
the little tiny display but uh do not
worry the people back in the 2020s were
very clever and came up with a good
solution to that problem of not having
that many pins and that is what this
display is so instead of having one pin
for every LED our hero will use two pins
to send and receive messages with our
Ola display and then we'll tell the
display which pixels we want to light up
using a special language or technically
it's the protocol i squar c similar to
SQL or some people call it SQL you can
some people also might call this I2 C
but it technically is i squ c the herob
board uses pins A4 and A5 for i squ c
Communications so we will wire those two
pins to our display along with power and
ground giving us four necessary wire
connections for displaying messages or
pictures on our new display starting at
the very top of our code we have what we
always have the include
uo. we don't really need to worry about
this we're using the Arduino IDE so this
is going to be automatically included
anyway in in our use case going down a
little bit lower we now have a new
library that is required in order to get
this display working you will not be
able to compile this unless you have
this Library installed if you do not
already have this Library installed just
like always
inventor. libraries once the page loads
you will be able to scroll down and
you'll be able to find the adventure kit
30 days in space required libraries make
sure that when you go here you select
the u82 lib library and then once you
have that downloaded you should be able
to go to sketch include Library add zip
libraries and make sure you include that
in the one after you've included it it
should show up down in the contributed
Library section down below now this u8
G2 lib Library supports many different
types of displays it does this by having
a Constructor for each display that it
supports that means that our display
that we're using is just one of many
different types of displays that this
could possibly support our specific
display that we're using is this really
really really long complicated name you
see here this is a very specific OLED
that we're using the u8 G2
s1106 blah blah blah blah blah blah blah
blah blah blah blah
i2c but don't worry just copy and paste
that one I will give you 100% leeway way
to just copy and paste this whole piece
of stuff here and we're just going to
call it for simplistic reasons we're
just going to call it Lander display
because that's a lot easier than saying
this once we've used the library to
Define our Lander display we're going to
go and we're going to be able to use
that later on in our code here we are in
setup where we're going to be talking of
the serial rate of 9600 delay by a
second and then we're going to begin and
begin essentially says okay set analog
pin A4 and A5 as the pins that we'll be
using to communicate with our display
blah blah blah similar stuff that we do
with pin mode in regular setup this just
calls it here inside of the library so
when we say do begin we're just doing
the typical pin mode setup and just
initializing everything that's needed
for our display in here next we're going
to select a font for our character to
display the library supports hundreds of
different fonts but in our case we're
just going to choose this one here you
can change this if you really want to to
something else if you go to this GitHub
link and you want to change it to
something else you totally can and it
will still probably work just fine we
chose this because we thought this was a
nice suitable font from the list on here
now this is how you would set the
rotation if you want it to be upside up
and by upside up I mean where you're
holding it and the pins are supposed to
be on the top and that should be like
where you're looking at it from but
let's just say you have it set up on a
Contraption where it doesn't make sense
to have it orientated that way you can
actually rotate it 100% upside down
essentially flipping whatever is on the
screen 180° by uncommenting this line
here if you set the display Rotation by
R2 which basically says turn it two
times 180° you can technically turn the
text 100% upside down if you wanted to
I'm keeping this commented out because
it's not necessary for what we're doing
here after setup is completed we will
hop down to our wonderful wonderful
little Loop now one thing you have to be
careful about depending on which font
you're going to be using is each font
might be slightly different so the
maximum height that you can use for
specific fonts that you can choose from
for example is is a little bit different
so we want to save what our maximum font
height will ever be in a variable called
font height and we can actually grab
that really really easily because guess
what there's a function included in that
Library called get Max Char height this
is going to be taking the max maximum
character height from the library that
we defined up here and we're going to be
taking it and putting it into this bite
font
height next in the loop we're going to
take the Lander display and we're going
to clear the buffer this is essentially
just going to clear the internal memory
and this is going to make it so that
there's nothing to display on the
display we're going to basically clear
what's on the display next we're going
to have another function again a lot of
functions from this Library this is
almost like a library explanation video
more than it is an actual code
explanation it's kind of
50/50 the next function that we're going
to be talking about is the set font
position top and the reason why this is
important is because even though we're
only going to be displaying text in this
lesson we want it to display hello world
or something similar to make sure that
we have it connected correctly but even
though we're only going to be displaying
text the library has a set cursor
function to locate the first character
to be displayed and by default the
cursor position is set to the bit at the
lower left of the first character
but here we want this to be set to the
upper left of the first character which
makes it easier to position our first
line of text on our display but here's
the issue if you want to tell us uh to
start at 0 which is going to be the very
corner and we want to say exploration
Lander right what's that going to do
we're going to start displaying
exploration Lander e because we're
starting right here at the bottom do you
see what the issue is we're not in the
display we're currently displaying this
off screen this isn't even going to show
up so the issue is that if you don't set
it the top because it's by default
bottom you want it to be this by doing
it at this point which is the very top
of it and we actually be you displaying
it on the bottom by setting the position
to the top we're going to make it so
that any fonts that we use going forward
will be starting at the very top part of
it so that at least if we're starting at
the default to z0 we won't have the
issue of it not showing up it'll show up
on screen so here we're starting at uh
centered string so we're taking the
total width and that just basically
takes the whole width 128 and finds out
where the center point is for where you
want your string to be and we're just
going to display exploration Lander now
if we want our hello world message to go
on line two instead of starting at zero
we can start at font height which is
something that we were able to grab here
so let's just say that this e maybe this
is the biggest letter that we're going
to have let's just say this e is a total
of I don't know let's just say it's like
pixels then it's going to save this in
here because it knows that our biggest
one is 15 and it's going to put that in
here so that we start at least one down
below that e so we don't have any
overlapping text so this exploration
Lander hello world is going to remain
statically on screen at all times it's
not going to be taken off it's not going
to Blink the only thing we want to have
blink to show how this could work is
we're going to have the message
standby blink and we want standby to
Blink on and off and on and off and show
up and show go away and show up and go
away and show up and go away and the way
we're going to do this is we're going to
have it go where we have a Boolean and
every time we go through the
loop since it's a static it's going to
remember that last time it was true so
this time it's going to be false does
that make any sense or last time it was
false so this time it's going to be true
that's how this works so static
basically means that next time we go
through the loop it'll remember what it
was last time so let's just say we
wanted to Blink on in this execution
through the loop well I want it to look
pretty so the way what this is doing
here is it's going to Center both
horizontally and vertically in the
remaining space that we have so the
centered y
position is going to be getting the font
height finding out what was taken up by
this and the reason we have a
calculation for this is because while we
could use variables that tell us
exactly what to use we could hardcode it
but if you decided hey I want to use a
different font and that font has
different values and the other than the
font we're using that's going to make it
not censored anymore so the reason we
have this nice big calculation is
because that also gives you the option
to choose what font you want so we can
take whatever font you had multiply it
by two because we have obviously two of
that same font height and then we can
take the Lander display. getet display
height and we can subtract this font
height times two / two big mey
calculation but basically it just tells
us where the censor point is of the Y
position it's actually not as crazy as
you might think it
is and then once Lander displayed uh we
can get the font censor
position and we can say
standby given whatever font we have
we're going to censor that and then
we're just going to Blink on
standby now assuming that we have now
gone through here we're then going to
say the following we want to switch
every single time right so we have we
have this cool logical not statement
here I'm sure you've seen the if
statements before where they're like if
something double equals 12 right or if
something double
equals you know like true what this is
is this is saying not the exclamation
point is essentially The Logical not
negator so if you say one way you can
write this is if blink on
an LH handed form of writing this is if
blink on is is double equal to true and
another way you can write this is if
blink on is not equal false this is a
lot more stupid to look to read at
though than just having that so but you
could think of
this not equal to false is essentially
the exact same thing is saying equal
equal to true cuz what else could it be
it's Boolean it's only one or the
other in this case we're taking whatever
blink on is right in this case blink on
at this time through the loop could be
anything it could be true it could be
false but we want to switch every single
time so we're going to set blink
on to be not blink on which sounds
really confusing but essentially we're
just going to be setting it to be if
it's true this time through we want to
change it to false and then next time it
goes through the loop it'll be false and
if it's false right now we want it to be
true so by heading the not negator the
negation to it we're just going to swap
swap it to whatever the other value is
and since they're booleans this is
really easy to understand this wouldn't
work very well if this was something
like an integer obviously but since it's
Boolean it actually works pretty good
cuz only two states it can be in next
we're going to take the Lander display
and we're going to send that buffer
we've accumulated the entire buffer now
we've made the expiration Lander hello
world and then we got determined are we
going to put on the standby or are we
not going to put on the standby I don't
know but uh whatever it is in this
version of the loop it's either one or
the other whether this was true or false
or not we're going to send that buffer
to the display And Delay by half a
second for a little tiny blink of effect
next time we go the loop we'll do the
exact same thing but it'll do the
opposite of for for standby at least and
it will either turn it on or off this is
obviously the function we use to
calculate the centered string but that's
about it for day 21 that should be all
the code explanation I look forward to
seeing you guys
tomorrow welcome to the day 21 wiring
example video as we make preparations
for our liftoff we need to learn to use
a new piece of Hardware the 128x 64
pixel OLED display panel today's task is
designed to test its basic wiring and
function before we call on it later for
more complicated
operations you'll notice that in order
to keep things clean and easy to follow
we've temporarily removed all the
unneeded components and wires from the
breadboard and tucked them out of the
way so that we can focus today on the
connections to our new
display as you have learned by now the
OED display uses the i2c protocol to
communicate with the hero and only
requires four wires to do the job the
first two on the left
here are simply the ground and VCC five
volt power connections which are
connected by our traditional black and
red wires here and here to the
corresponding pins on the
hero the two remaining pins are the i2c
clock and data lines which the hero
accesses through analog pins A5 and A4
respectively in our setup we have a
green wire right here connecting clock
pin the clock pin on the display to pin
A5 on the
hero and we have a blue wire right here
going from the data pin to Hero pin
A4 you of course can use any colors you
like if you find those either convenient
or
clearer our test sketch today Deals Only
with the display of text although soon
we'll also be using it for
graphics we'll use some of the display
Library functions to print a title and a
hello world message on the screen and
then finally we'll use some delays and
looping to Blink a standby message on
and off just to further test our ability
to control the display that's all so
let's just go ahead now and give it a
try so going to the IDE and loading the
sketch in a few moments we should see
something appear on our OLED
display there we go so there's our title
our hello world and our blinking standby
message so it appears that everything uh
in our sketch is functioning as
expected and so that is pretty much all
for today's test look it over and make
sure you understand all the steps and
next time we'll keep the same wiring
test setup that we have here but we'll
run it through its Paces on some nontext
tasks so we will see you
then oh what a great day Explorer we've
achieved Our Miss Miss today thanks to
your steadfast determination and
concentration the OLED display is all
set up and is working seamlessly with
our ship's control panel this is a
massive leap towards getting us off this
aquatic expanse and back into the
familiar emptiness of space tomorrow
we'll delve deeper into the newly
installed Graphics Library we'll harness
the power of code and fully explore the
capabilities of our OLED display I am as
excited as my programming allows to see
the Myriad of images and data we can
display on this little device so take a
well-deserved break and rest up for the
next exciting chapter the Stars Will
Keep Us company tonight good night
[Music]
Explorer