[Music]
ah welcome back dear Explorer I trust
you've managed to get some rest after
yesterday's uh H unexpected musical
interlude it appears someone out there
in the vast Cosmos has a sense of humor
a Rick Roll as you earthlings call it
quite the antique prank but I suppose
humor is scarce in the vacuum of space
anyway it's time to get back to business
don't you think the endless void isn't
going to explore itself on the docket
for today we have some interesting
challenges lined up to enhance the
security of our ship's control panel we
will be utilizing our keypad we're going
to set a personal identification number
or pin this will prevent any mischievous
extraterrestrial beings from fiddling
with our control panel or a future U
pranking the past you time gets pretty
wibbly wobbly in space you know
additionally we're going to make use of
our passive buzzer to provide auditory
feedback this will help ensure that each
key press gets the recognition it
deserves and gives you the user feedback
that an input has been
registered well then let's not delay any
longer explore let's dive in and Ensure
our systems are secure and interactive
onward to the
adventure ah the beauty of continuity
dear Explorer you see the Marvel of the
universe is that it remains for the most
part constant Stars keep burning planets
keep spinning and black holes well they
continue being quite black and very
holishkes to detangle the cosmos has
blessed us with a touch of Simplicity
today so we will bypass the wiring stage
this time and leap directly into the
vast and Mysterious World of code brace
yourself Explorer because today we dive
head first into the celestial sea of
ones and zeros let's embark on this code
Adventure shall we life as an
Interstellar Explorer may feel solitary
and indeed it mostly is however one
mustn't Overlook the odd chance of
bumping into unwelcome guests after all
space isn't a private Garden it's a vast
unending sea teeing with possibilities
and yes even potential space pirates
don't look so shocked it's not all fun
and games out here it'd be awfully
Dreadful if your ship's autopilot Got
Hijacked mere moments after finally
getting out of this planet's atmosphere
you're welcome to get stuck again but I
think I'll pass thank you so with that
Merry thought we turn our attention to
an essential system in our spacecraft
the security system today we'll give
that a nice little upgrade we're going
to add a personal identification number
or pin to our control
panel consider our two-dimensional array
from two days back our beautiful little
keypad with all those character inputs
now let's assign two of those keys for
some functional fun one key an asterisk
will let us change the pin the other key
a pound symbol will be our magic access
key press that punch in the correct pin
and there you have it the control panel
is all yours speaking of pins we need a
default one don't we something nice and
simple to start with how about 000000 0
and before you roll your eyes remember
this will be changed immediately after a
quick note on system Integrity you see
we only want to allow pin changes if the
user which in this case is you already
knows the pin a little layer of security
if you will so we'll split this logic
into a separate function to prevent
duplication remember our discussion
about functions yes we created one using
void because we didn't need it to return
anything well that is no longer the case
we need to know if the pin was correct
or not so let's switch void with Bo when
we call this function it will now return
a Boolean value either true if the pin
is correct or false if it is not we also
need to make sure to add the proper
return statements as well where
needed and don't worry about the
function going on a spree of
calculations once it hits return it
jumps right back from where it was
called I've got a line byline breakdown
of today's code waiting for you I advise
you take a look it's packed with
knowledge and could very well be your
key to survival in this Cosmic expanse
off you go then Explorer please make
make your way over to the instruction
material that I was able to gather
cashed on your computer I've also added
it to your mission resources for future
reference should you so need
it all right welcome back to day 13 of
the 30 days lost and space adventure kit
code
explanations today we're going to be
building on what we had yesterday where
we added in the buzzer to our little
keypad thing and made us essentially
like a little piano to make sure that
the buzzer and the keypad were both
functioning
properly I hope you had fun with the
little bonus project and I hope we got
you there the next thing we're going to
be doing is we're going to be adding a
little bit of extra security to your
control panel as you know there's
currently no security meaning there's no
password so if anyone wanted to access
your ship as soon as you got into space
you could probably guarantee that
somebody would likely remotely get into
your machine even if you didn't want
them to so to prevent this we're going
to go in and we're going to add the
functionality for a PIN unlock to our
Landers control panel now the new
Concepts we'll be talking about today
are the following two things one is what
a return function is basically at the
end of a function we've been using void
which returns well void which is
essentially nothing we're not returning
anything at the end of there so when we
call that function it just execute some
code and then hops back and that's all
that void does but a return statement at
the end is a different way to do
functions which will essentially return
a value such as you know if an integer
of 10 or a Boolean of true or false but
whatever that we end up deciding we want
it to do we'll be going over that today
and as well as the new type which I just
mentioned Boolean which is you can think
of it as it only has two states it is
either zero or it's one and there's no
other scenario that it can be anything
anything else it is just zero or one you
can think if it is false or true or yes
or no but the only two values you can
save it as is true or false and that's
it if we hop down here we'll see the
following obviously we've gone over this
gone over this and gone over all of this
up until well up to here this is all
stuff from yesterday where we Define the
keypad create the keypad object and
obviously we have it mapped to to
certain Buzzard pins and Etc later on
for Simplicity sake we've actually
removed the tone 2D array and we're just
going to have it hardcoded for different
success and failure pin tones later on
in the code if we go down to setup we're
going to set the buzzer pin as an output
and then we're going to serial begin
9600 talking over the serial Monitor and
obviously just a quick tiny little delay
before just displaying The Prompt just
to get let us know hey by the way if you
want to create a new PIN cuz we're going
to start with the assumption that there
is no pin currently in system as you can
see here we've defined this is the only
new value we' defined at the top
constant bite pin length is going to be
equal to four so we're requiring the PIN
to be four numbers and or characters and
down here we're having the pin set
initially to just 000000 Z press the
star key which is on the keypad that
bottom left key um to enter a new PIN or
this to access the
system and that's going to be at the
very very beginning of setup after that
you can guess where we go right to the
beginning of loop we go to the beginning
of Loop and we say hey let's check what
key is on here let's wait until we get a
key press and until a key is pressed
obviously this is a wait for key I'm
going to guess if I go into this
function inside of the library we'll
find that we have a while
um key is not being pressed we just
continue to Loop forever and ever
endlessly so while we wait for for key
to be pressed it is just going to
continue to execute that as soon as one
is pressed we will jump we will check to
see what that button is in just a moment
but we have uh button character is where
it will be saved as as a value serial.
print Ln tone buzzer pin uh we're going
to print the frequency 880 and we're
going to do it for 100
milliseconds now that's just let us know
that a button was pressed and then we
finally go down to check what the heck
was actually pressed there's only two
things that really could be okay because
there's only two things that initially
you want it to be it's either going to
be the star if you want to enter a new
PIN or this if you want to access the
system so let's say it was this to
access the system if it was that then
we're going to say Boolean aess allowed
equals validate pin so here's where we
get to the new function return
statement this is essentially doing two
things it's one setting this value to
whatever this is going to be but that's
also essentially just checking to
see if we are allowed to have access and
I'm going to guess validate pin is a
function that simply allows us to check
to see if we have access and if you go
down here to bully and validate pin
that's exactly what we need to do we
need to enter the PIN to continue the
default pin is is 0 0 0 0 so this first
time around you go through you'll
probably be typing in each time you go
through 0 0 0 0 and this is exactly what
you're doing in this for Loop 4 and I
equal 0 I is less than pin length I
++ inside of this function we're going
to go through each time and we're going
to set the we're going to wait for a key
press Give a Little Tone input thing
saying hey a button has been pressed on
the buzzer if the character they press
is not equal to what the value of at
that uh place in the current pin is
supposed to be so let's just say the
very first one you decide to type in is
one well that's not equal to the
character of zero um that's mentioned up
here as a default pin so what's going to
happen is it's going to go down here and
it's going to say hey that's wrong this
is not equal to it so we're going to do
this statement here here's where we get
to the new the new thing we're going to
return false you'll notice that this
isn't void validate pin it's not int
validate pin it's not nothing like that
specifically it is Boolean validate pin
and the reason that that's important is
because that means that at some point in
this code we need to return in order to
leave this function properly otherwise
it's not set up correctly we need to
return a Boolean which means at the end
of this thing we're either going to
return true or false it's going to be
false if we inputed the wrong PIN
meaning that we do not have the access
or know how to access the system and it
will return true if we did input the
right pin so as soon as we input one of
the incorrect ones here we're going to
immediately return false and we won't
continue any further otherwise if let's
just say we did go through this entire
for Loop and we made it just fine and we
didn't input anything incorrectly we'll
return true now you'll notice something
is kind of off about this if you go and
test this in your code we left this in
here for a specific reason and that's
that this pin here is actually easily
brute forceable if you're interested in
learning more about this security flaw I
highly recommend checking out day 15
where we'll be going into more detail on
how to remove this security issue
entirely from the code so that no one
should be able to brute force it by
typing in random characters each time so
let's just say we returned false here
because we typed in one instead of zero
for that first
character if we hop up to the loop we'll
see if access is allowed in this case
it's false so we did not say welcome
authorized user we're not going to we
did not get to that point we're going to
jump to this lse statement we're going
to say access denied and it's going to
tell us this exact same thing press the
start enter a new PIN or the hashtag and
access the system and we can go through
the same thing again but if we did get
it right it'll go here now we have the
other functionality which is going to
Simply go and it's going to create a new
PIN obviously 00000000 is a pretty bad
default pin um I think most hackers
would probably put that in like a short
list to begin with if they're trying to
Brute Force something as one of them
that uh is so commonly used it's like
password password if button character
double equals the star key then we'll do
Boolean access allowed is going to be
equal to validate pin now if we want to
change the pin we're going to check to
make sure one do we have access to
change the pin first you have to input
the the old password before you before
you can change the new password if and
again this goes down to the validate pin
we went over this a minute ago let's say
in this
case it returned true you got the
initial pin you typed in the character
000000 and you're able to change that
default pin whatever you want it to be
now it says welcome authorizer user
please enter a new PIN finally we go
through and we're just simply going to
go through each of the loops and we're
going to say button character we're
going to wait for an inut put play
Little Tone and then we're going to set
the current pin I is equal to whatever
button we just press so let's just say
we want to set it instead of 0000 z z we
want to set it to a b c d well we can do
that we go through this Loop we the
first time we go through we type in a
sets the first one to a second time we
go through we type in B sets the second
one to B in this case remember zero one
two and three because the Rays always
start at zero once it hits that length
which as we know is four is the final p
pin length once we know that this
returns false it's going to exit the for
Loop because obviously four once it gets
to four is no longer less than four so
that's false and it'll exit the loop and
then it'll go down to here and it'll say
that the pin has successfully been
changed to whatever we had decided to
type in else we're going to say if we
did not initially type in that first pin
it's obviously it's just going to not
allow us to change the pin so we won't
be able to continue any further
with that um that should be all there is
for the logic for this day again if you
want to learn more about the security
flaw with how we actually do the pin
validation check out day 15 we will go
into more detail on that there on a good
way that we can show how to fix that
Brute Force vulnerability that is
currently part of that if you guys are
interested and with that that'll be
it welcome to the day 13 wiring example
video today we don't have any new wiring
or circuits to discuss the hardware is
all just the same as it was on day 12
instead today we'll focus on the
functions provided by our new software
sketch we are using our newly mastered
keyboard and buzzer to implement a
simple password security
interface once again we'll need to keep
an eye on the serial monitor console to
get feedback on how things are working
the rules of this security system are
pretty simple you must enter a four
character password to gain access to the
system also you may change the password
to something else but in order to do so
you must enter the old password
successfully the pound key is pressed in
order to request entry and the star key
is pressed to change the password we'll
be getting messages about success or
failures of these attempts on the serial
monitor the starting default password is
000000 although you can change this in
the sketch if you wish so with this
information in hand let's go ahead and
load the sketch and see how things are
working so going over to the IDE we'll
load our
sketch uploading now
done uploading okay so we should be up
and running now and so we can go ahead
and for example try to enter the system
using the default password so we should
press the pound
key and I'm prompted on the monitor to
enter the pin so I'll enter the default
password 0 0 0 0 and the device is
successfully unlocked so that part at
least works okay let's next see if we
can change the password to something
that's a little harder to guess so in
order to do that I'll press the star
key and now I need to enterer the old
password in order to go any further so
I'll go ahead and enter
00000000
again and it's now unlocked but now I
need to enter a new password so so let's
enter one that's almost as lame as the
first one 1 2 3 4 okay I get a message
that says that the pin has been
successfully changed so let's go ahead
and see if we can verify that this is
the new password so I'm going to press
the pound key again in order to attempt
to enter once again so pressing pound
I'm prompted to enter the pin if I enter
the old pin so for example if I start
putting in zero oh it says well I didn't
press zero I pressed the star so it told
me that star was the wrong character to
enter so it immediately aborted the
entry attempt let me try it again with a
zero so pressing the pound key now I'm
going to enter zero and up zero was
wrong as well oh I remember remember now
I changed the password it's now 1 2 3 4
so let's see if that'll work so I'll go
ahead and press pound and then press 1 2
3 4 and I'm successfully unlocked and if
I decide well that's really just you
know too terrible of a password to use I
can change it again so I'll go ahead
press
star press the old passord password so
I've
got the new
password is 1 2 3
four okay so the device is unlocked
please now enter a new password so let's
try something a little harder to
remember let's do
b987 so that's my new password and I can
check to see if that's correct so let's
go ahead and try and enter
press the pound key now let's enter the
PIN to continue so that was B
987 and that was successfully unlocked
so this seems to confirm that our
security sketch is functioning as it was
designed however if you've been paying
close attention you might have noticed
that our security system isn't really
all that that secure can you see how a
determined hacker might be able to
figure out the supposedly secret
password even after it's been
changed think about this a little bit
and if you want to work on ways to
improve this security be sure to check
out the activities on Creative day
15 but in the meantime we'll be looking
forward on day 14 to adding more
hardware and software features to this
system so we'll see you
then what an impressive day Explorer
you've stepped up to the challenge and
fortified your control panel like a true
Galactic Defender just imagine the
disappointment on the face of any Rogue
Mothership attempting to hijack your
controls delightful I dare say our
control panel is looking quite
formidable but wouldn't it be nice to
add a touch of theatricality to it
tomorrow we'll bring back our trusty RGB
LED from last week and to add more
Panache we'll also integrate some code
Logic for our buzzer to create a
symphony of auditori and visual feedback
on pin input lights and sounds for every
action the perfect Command Center for a
sophisticated space Explorer take a
well- earned rest now remember
Interstellar conquering requires both
body and mind to be at their sharpest
sleep well and get ready to add more
Intergalactic glamour to your ship
tomorrow
[Music]
so