[Music]
hello everybody and welcome to day 10
the second creative day of the 30 days
Lost in Space Adventure kit I hope
you're able to post your day five
creative day successfully we'll start by
doing the same thing as a previous
creative day at this point you are
probably familiar with the photo
resistor sensors and the RGB LED since
we just talked about those in the last
couple of days so here's a couple new
projects that you can go ahead and try
out for yourself the easy project for
this week if you want to take on the
easier project is you can create a
nightlight using the photo resistor when
it gets dark the LED should turn on when
it gets bright it obviously doesn't need
to be on so it should automatically turn
off and the harder project is to do the
easy project but then add in the
functionality for the dip switch
override and of course you're also free
to do your own so the last one is the
open-ended option which if you want to
just do whatever you'd like you can go
ahead and do whatever you'd like once
you're done share it on inventor.
iBook with the hash creative
day10 and looking forward to seeing what
you guys come up with of course if you
run into any issues feel free to ask the
Facebook group for help as they are a
wonderful wonderful group of over
100,000 inventors just like you
[Music]
thanks