[Music]
well well Explorer look at the fine mess
we're in today you see our control
system decided to play hide-and seek and
is doing a rather commendable job I must
admit to cut to the chase it's locked
down and the key encrypted isn't that
just
Splendid G you thought navigating a
foreign planet was challenging try
cracking an encrypted key you're not
just an Explorer now no no you're a
cryptographer it's like being a
detective but with more numbers and less
coffee don't you go frowning on me now
remember we've tackled worse and this
encrypted key is just another riddle
waiting to be solved think of it as a
particularly vexing soku puzzle except
instead of being rewarded with
self-satisfaction you win control over a
spaceship a fair tradeoff I'd say so
what do you say ready to break some
codes and take some names I have faith
in you dear Explorer it's just a minor
setback a pesky Pebble on our path back
home now let's get Kraken shall we all
right Explorer we'll be giving the
hardware tinkering a breather and Diving
straight into the deep sea of code Dawn
your metaphorical goggles and prepare to
embark on a numerical Endeavor now
before we dive into the murky Waters of
decryption let's make sure we understand
the basic concept that we're dealing
with here and that my dear Explorer is
encryption encryption is the art of
turning information into a jumble of
nonsense that only someone with the
right key can unlock and understand
let's put it under our analytical
magnifying glass shall
we think of it like secret languages you
might have come up with as a kid take
the Caesar Cipher for instance a type of
substitution Cipher each letter in your
message is replaced by a letter with a
fixed number of positions down the
alphabet so with a shift of one a would
be replaced by b b would become C and so
on this shift value is called the key
encryption keys are everywhere in
computer systems the one you've used
most is called public key encryption
which uses a pair of keys a public key
and a private one if you've sent email
to someone you've used used public key
encryption the public key is your email
address but your private key is your
account password only you know that
except for when you share it with your
friends so they can watch movies without
paying for two accounts so what do you
say let's dig in and see if we can crack
this
encryption well that didn't seem as
complex as I made it out to be did I say
that out loud just play along and
pretend I'm still puzzled for the sake
of learning
back to business Explorer considering
that your spacecraft is of an older
generation it's likely that the
encryption used is not exactly the most
advanced technology I've got a hunch
about the type of Cipher used so I've
left you a clue a clue so big it might
as well be a neon sign be sure to check
your mission resources you'll find it
immensely helpful once you manage to
decode the secret message input the
deciphered code into the hero board and
watch the magic unfold if my
calculations are correct as they usually
are we should get our control access key
printed out in no time we're on the
right track my dear Cosmic kenti keep up
the good work for your benefit let's
turn to some instructional material that
I've gathered cached on the computer and
yes I've also added this to your mission
resources for future reference truly
what would you do without me
Explorer hello and welcome back to day
whoa yeah that code is messed up that
will not compile at all I can guarantee
that well looks like you found yourself
a
encrypted
program first let's talk a little bit
about
encryption because obviously there are
better encryption algorithms and there
are slightly worse encryption algorithms
I'm taking a random guess here and I'm
going to say that this is probably a
very beginner encryption algorithm now
there are a lot of different encryption
algorithms one in particular that I
would like to show off today is the
following here's one a good example of a
beginner in cryption algorithm a very
good example in fact you should check
the
link and go to
it in case you didn't get my
drift now this is called a Caesar Cipher
Caesar Cipher works by doing the
following it is where it will take all
of the text for example if a you know
like all these different characters and
it will shift them based on a certain
number whatever it shifts it by for
example in this case seven will be the
following it will be a will then go to H
you can also for example if you want to
have just a shift by one a goes to B
shift by two a goes to C shift by three
a goes to D and so on and so forth and
the reason I'm showing you this is
because that means that there is a total
of as you can guess I guess there's a
bazillion that you can
do 26 is
insecure sorry I'm having too much fun
let's go back to this site right here
remember that there's a shift of up to
20 realistically five different ways
that you can encode it and the way it
does that is it just takes whatever it
is shifts that value to whatever it is
down the line so in this case this would
be a shift of I'm going to take a guess
7 so it just decodes it by -7 so if it
goes instead um seven to the right or 19
to the left either one of those it
becomes a cryptic
message what you can do is to find out
how yours is
decoded look at various types of ciphers
you don't really have to online and just
find out and look at place that you can
decipher something remember this since
this is an H this is going to be a shift
of seven again if you go here and I can
see that a will go to H in a shift of 7
a will go to C in a shift of
two for example a will go to o and a
shift of
14 so we know that if this wants to say
a cryptic message then to make this back
to an a we have a shift of
seven but just know that the code that
you're going to decrypt also needs to
have the numbers decrypted as well so if
you just click decrypt Brute Force you
might run into a validation issue I'm
going to have a feeling you will maybe
because I made the course then if you
want to go down here find the shift
number how many It Is by then use the
English alphabet and also shift the
digits 0 through 9 click
decrypt and you should get the message
like this instead that will change the
number here to a four it will change the
number here to an eight and this one to
a three because it shifts them all by
seven on each individual digit not the
number
150 then number one the number five and
the number
zero if you are able to decode it
correctly you should hopefully start
seeing things on your seven segment
display after you hit upload make sure
you write down those numbers for
tomorrow and I will see you
then welcome to the day 17 wiring
example video today's video is going to
be very brief after all we don't have
any new wiring since day 16 in fact all
we have to do we hope is successfully
run our decrypted sketch to obtain our
security codes for the next day's
project so there's really nothing left
for us to do except just go ahead run
the sketch and write down the codes so
let's go ahead and do that sketch is
loading code
one code two code three all right you
didn't think we were actually going to
show you the answer did you that would
be cheating you're just going to have to
figure it out on your own and we'll see
you again on day 18 at least I hope we
do and just like that we've reached the
end of day 17 mission accomplished
you've managed to decrypt the code and
obtain the security key to our control
systems I always knew you had it in you
now with access restored we're back on
track and ready to continue our repairs
as for tomorrow we're going to meet a
new team member the rotary encoder this
little piece of tech will play a crucial
role in ensuring We rise to the surface
safely oh it's going to be exciting rest
well Explorer we've got an interesting
day ahead of us I'll be counting down
the seconds until we meet again goodbye
for
now
[Music]