[Music]
good morning Intrepid Explorer it's time
for our final day of our third week
together and I do hope you're as excited
as I am today we have a delightful
rendevu with our former crew members the
RGB LED we'll be integrating it into our
setup and taking our control panel from
functional to Fabulous today we'll be
Transforming Our buzzer simple beep into
an expressive and nuanced system of
auditory feedback not only that but
we're going to coordinate it with our
RGB led to provide clear visual cues
depending on your PIN input think of it
as a form of immediate feedback when you
successfully input your PIN we will
immerse our spaceship in a comforting
green light on the contrary if your
input fails we will be met with a
piercing red light as a sign of
incorrect input green for Go Red For No
it's so Universal that even a Celestial
body could understand since there are no
new components today we will be diving
head first into the coating and wiring
ready to create a sophisticated and
intelligent spaceship let's get
started all right time for some wiring
if you remember how we set up our RGB
LED last week you're already one step
ahead today all we need to do is to
merge that RGB setup with our current
control panel configuration think of it
as a bit of a Celestial or I guess
aquatic engineering we're taking two
previously independent systems and
merging them into one harmonious unit
it's quite beautiful isn't it we're
building a network of devices that can
interact and coordinate with each other
in a most splendidly efficient manner
just remember to ensure your wires don't
look like a tangled seaweed cluster we
need our circuits clear and our paths
unobstructed once you've achieved this
glorious Fusion of wires and components
we can shift gears and explore the vast
depths of coating buckle up it's about
to get
exciting all right my Fearless bottom
dwelling mechanic it's time layout
today's game plan here's what we're
aiming to do step one we want to bathe
the RGB in an emerald green glow when
our system is either unlocked or a
correct password has been punched in
contrarily let it flare up with fiery
Red Rage when an erroneous input
infiltrates the system step two let's
turn that buzzer into our personal
symfony composing Melodies of success
and failure as as needed step three
moreover we'll make that buzzer emit a
Brisk beep every time a button is
pressed during the pin input sequence
while we're at it why not manipulate the
rgb's Hue to shades of yellow or blue
this way we can visually signal that
we're in the midst of pin input it's
clever no I've been tinkering with a
plan and I've decided that the most
efficient and organized way to handle
all this is by developing three new
functions one to Express success one to
denote error and one to indicate ongoing
pin input plus we'll breathe life into
the RGB LED color function from last
week by now creating new functions
should be as easy as breathing for you
my dear space farer as for our friendly
buzzer let's make it sing by using the
tone function a high-pitch note will be
our anthem of
Victory while a low solemn tone will
signify defeat
the bones of our code will remain as
sturdy as they were yesterday don't
forget to add a tiny update at the top
to Define our LED pins as usual I've
crafted a line by line explanation of
today's code and added it to your
mission resources while it builds on
what we did yesterday I highly recommend
giving a look over your survival does
hinge on understanding this after
all the days sure are flying by Explorer
now seems like a great time to grant me
a welld deserved break as you review
some instruction material that I have
gathered cashed on your computer as you
know I've also added this to your
mission resources in case future you
needs a bit more
assistance hello everybody and welcome
back to day 14 of the 30 days loss in
space adventure kit code explanations
today we're going to be building off of
day 13 by enhancing the wiring in a way
that we can add in an RGB led to our
circuit to give us not only the audio
feedback that we had yesterday after
button inputs we will also be getting a
visual glowing rgp indicator light
you'll notice though that the wiring
diagram is going to be a little bit
different the reason why this is the
case is because since the RGB LED
requires pulse width modulation pins we
had to modify the wiring diagram to make
sure that we give the pulse with
modulation pins to the RGB LED and then
give the rest of the pins to the devices
that don't require it the only new Aro
concept introduced or documented in this
lesson is going to just basically be
some complex logic with multiple devices
other than that there's not going to be
anything new taught in this lesson just
taking what we did yesterday and making
it slightly more advanced since we've
already covered the major majority of
what's here at the top R we know. keypad
setup library from two days ago we got
the pin length is four we talked about
how we want to make the
pins and then we obviously made the
button Tod array we have the column and
row pins remember these are changed
these are not the same pins because we
need to move the pins so that we could
give the pulse with modulation ones to
the RGB LED create the keypad setting
the buzzer on pin 12 which is a new pin
and the only really new thing at the top
is right here we have constant red pin
green pin and blue pin on pins 9 10 and
11 because those all have pulsewidth
modulation capabilities at the beginning
of setup we're using the pin mode
function and we're going to be setting
as normal LEDs or outputs so we're just
setting each of those pins to be an
output pin on this next line here since
we start off is locked we're initially
going to display every red color
remember display color this function
that we created before red Value Green
value blue value green and blue are zero
and then red is 128 so we're going to
display red just to say hey we're
currently locked out then of course just
like we've already talked about in the
previous lessons begin talking the
serial Monitor and then we have the
option to either create a new password
or access the system jumping straight
down to the logic of loop which is where
it would go in the flow of code
a lot of this is going to look the exact
same as before we did add a couple of
good extra additional functions though
you'll notice here we have a function
here called give input feedback give
input feedback give input feedback this
is located in a few different areas of
the code and instead of what we did
before which was hard coding each single
time hey I want to play a tone of this
Hertz rate every single time we simply
turned it into a function so now if we
ever want to change that tone or
whatever we don't have to do it in 50
places instead we can just call this
function give input feedback first we're
going to turn off the LED just for a
brief moment then we're going to have
the tone for 2/10 of a second play a
buzzer sound a buzzing sound just to
give input feedback to know hey a button
was pressed then we're going to display
the color and restore the blue LED that
should be on the
display we do have different couple of
colors that we're going to be using
throughout this program the first one is
red and that means you're currently
locked you're locked and you're not
doing anything you're not trying to
input a new password it's not trying to
unlock the system it's just currently
locked and currently just sitting there
you can think of it as like the lock
screen on your computer where before
you've actually gone to actually move
your mouse or press the
keyboard when it's in a moment where
it's thinking to itself or doing
something for example where when we're
unlocking the console we're going to
have blue light be the status light for
hey you are currently doing something in
this case either changing the password
or trying to unlock the system all of
this should be the exact same as what
was said mentioned yesterday so I'm
going to just glance over it and for
right now down here below we have the
same everything's almost the same except
we do have one more here which is the
input feedback is what we call here just
in instead of uh CH doing the tone uh
manually now down below we're actually
going to be creating a new PIN color
that we want to use in this case the pin
color that we want to use is going to be
yellow if you're entering a new pin and
as you go down into the section where
you're actually inputting the pin you'll
notice we have the function give input
feedback we didn't accidentally want to
change it to uh blue at the end of every
single time so at the end of of every
time that we call this function here to
give the input feedback which just makes
a buzzer noise we're also going to
override the color here so that it is a
yellow LED once again every time we go
to the loop now let's say that just for
example you've successfully done all of
that and the pin gets successful we're
going to have another function very very
similar to give input feedback which is
give success feedback and it basically
plays a tada sound and makes a green
light and as you go down here we have d
give success feedback we also have the
function give error feedback which is
another one that's called every once in
a while that basically turns it to red
and also plays a different tone to let
you know hey you typed something Mis
pressed something something went wrong
that's essentially all it does then we
also have the function display color
which is the exact same I'm sure you
remember from the RGB LED lesson from a
while back it basically just says hey
how what intensity do you want to set
the red blue and green to and then does
so so accordingly on the correct
pins but other than that in terms of
most the logic for validate pin all this
other stuff we have the give error
feedback we have give success feedback
give input feedback besides these new
little things that we're adding here
everything is basically the same logic
wise is what we went over yesterday so I
don't really have to go over it in too
too much detail the nice thing about
having all these functions here give
input give success and give error
feedback is that instead of manually
coding them into a bunch of different
places in the code like here if we just
did this tone buzzer pin 320 and then
this in like a bunch of different places
we can just give error feedback and we
know like hey this is supposed to be an
error right here it's we're reading
through the code instead of saying this
is a tone with this pin but I don't know
why they're playing the tone it gives it
better readability it's easier to go in
if you want to change the tone to be
something else let's just say you want
to make it a Zelda sound effect where
it's like d
you can change that to be anywhere you
want to instead of changing it in 60
places you change it in one good code
readability good code reusability um and
that's why we did it that way and with
that that should be it for day
14 thank you guys so
much welcome to the day 14 wiring
example video if you've studied our
plans for today you'll realize that we
are using a lot of what we developed on
day 13
but adding extra feedback both Visual
and
audible the red green blue LED will give
us a colorcoded status indication and
the buzzer will provide us in addition
to keypress sounds special tones to
indicate password success or failure now
we'll be returning to these indicators
in a minute but first let's have a look
at the wiring needed for today's project
now ideally it would be great if we
could just leave the keypad setup intact
from day 13 and simply add on the needed
LED wiring unfortunately though we can't
really do that because the LED can't use
just any of the hero output pins recall
that our RGB LED works by pulse width
modulation and only some of the pins
those whose number numers are preceded
on the board by a Tilda only those pins
support
pwm in our day 13 Circuit there is only
one
pwm pin left unused but we need three of
them to run the
LED this means that we'll need to
relocate some of our keypad wiring in
order to free up pins 9 10 and 11 for
use by our
LED fortunately we can accomplish this
by moving only one of our keypad wires
the uppermost wire of our ribbon cable
is the one that needs to move it gets
moved from its original position of pin
9 which was a pwm pin up to the right to
pin 13 and we're also going to reassign
and use pin 12 which is available as the
line with this yellow wire right here to
drive our buzzer you should check the
software sketch to make sure that these
new assignments that we've made are
reflected in the software
sketch now that we have pins 9 10 and 11
on the hero available we go ahead and
hook those up to the blue
blue the
green and the red channels of our LED
through current limiting resistors as we
usually do so this is pretty much just
as we've set up the LED
before finally with the ground
connections connected here's the ground
connection for the LED here's the ground
connection for the buzzer so with those
ground connections complete through the
ground bus that we've set up that's all
the hardware connections that we need to
verify for this project so now let's
quickly review what we expect to see and
to hear when we run the
sketch looking at what first happens
when we enter setup the status color is
red which we use to indicate that the
system is locked once the loop function
begins different colors and sounds will
be produced depending upon the situation
for example when the system is waiting
for the current password to be entered
the LED is blue so the blue indicates
that it's waiting for a password
entry on the other hand when it's
waiting for a new password to be entered
the color changes to Yellow so we'll
watch out for that cue when the password
is correctly entered then the LED shines
green so that's our success
indication anytime an incorrect password
is subsequently entered then the LED
goes back to Red Again by the way if
you're paying close attention during all
of this you might notice that the LED
blinks out momentarily whenever we press
one of the
keys this it turns out is by Design as
you can see if you carefully read the
code for say Play Input tone or any of
the other sound generating functions in
our software sketch now this is a little
bit of an obscure detail but we need to
do this because as it turns out the pwm
and tone functions both use the same
hero resources and so it can be
problematic to try using them at the
same time so we avoid all that by simply
turning off the LED while we're playing
a sound so again that's just a small
detail but uh in case you were wondering
now you have the
explanation well let's get on with it
and run the sketch and see just how well
these things work for us so moving over
now to the IDE we'll go ahead and load
the
sketch and upload is
complete and we can see that we have the
red LED indicating that the system is
locked and the first thing that we need
to do is set a new password and to set a
new password we'll have to enter the old
default password which we'll remember is
000000 so pressing star
key we see the LED blinked off and came
back on Blue indicating that it's
prompting us to enter the password which
will do 0 0 0 0 and we get the success
tone that indicates that we've
successfully unlocked the system and we
get the yellow LED indicating that we're
being prompted to enter a new password
so let's enter a new password let's try
H
9512 okay we got a success tone and we
got green which indicates that the
system is unlocked and we've
successfully changed the password all
right so now that we're in and we have a
new password we can try out a few things
and make sure that it responds as we
expect it to let's try re-entering the
system but let's intentionally give it
the wrong password so I'm going to hit
the pound key and I get blue which means
ready to enter password so let me enter
1 2 3 4 which is wrong okay as soon as I
enter a wrong character I get the red
LED and the the failure tone I could try
it again and I'll start with a correct
sequence so I'll start with 95 but now
I'll give the wrong character for the
next one I'll put in a three and that
failed as well so now let's go ahead and
enter the correct password so pressing
the pound key then 9 5 1 2 and success
and I'm back to green again so it looks
like the functions as we've expected
them to work the sound functions and the
LED light functions are uh working as
expected so it looks like our enhanced
security interface is working pretty
well now so looking ahead after you've
finished creative day 15 we'll be back
here on day 16 to tackle a whole new
output display device
and a new set of design challenges so we
will see you
then well look at you fish food we've
reached the end of day 14 and may I say
you've done spectacularly I'm impressed
no astonished at the pace at which
you're conquering these obstacles
halfway through our ship repairs and
you're still firing on all thrusters my
digital heart if I had one would be
brimming with Pride it's remarkable
isn't it how you've been able to adapt
and learn navigating through Uncharted
territories of tech Wizardry all in a
hostile environment millions of miles
from home from securing the control
panel to now giving it Visual and
auditory feedback you've become a force
to be reckoned with in Space
Engineering rest now weary traveler
you've earned your sea legs let the fish
whisper Tales of your endeavors across
the ocean as you recharge your human
batteries and remember the tides wait
for No One tomorrow we swim onward
congratulations on reaching this
Milestone it's not every day one gets to
say they're halfway done repairing a
spaceship stranded in Coral now is
[Music]
it