[Music]
ah there you are Explorer welcome to day
18 of our fantastic Interstellar
Adventure I hope you're well rested and
ready to embark on today's Journey great
work on the last mission Sherlock you've
got the brains but now going to need the
brawn your keypad worked fine for Real
Time input into the hero but we'll need
precise thrust control for our Ascent
rate to the surface without risking any
let's say unplanned rapid
disassembly or we could run straight
into Rachel and same thing game
over fortunately the hero kit contains
just the sensor we need for subtle or
forceful control a rotary encoder
all right let's dive into today's
Hardware discussion our star of the day
is the rotary encoder but what exactly
is it in simple terms a rotary encoder
sends direction of rotation signals and
the amount of turn it can also send an
on or off signal with a push pick it up
and play with
it every click you feel as you turn the
encoder is counted and the direction
you're turning it is noted these two
pieces of information are sent to our
board as a sequence of high high and low
signals the rotary encoder is
particularly useful for scrolling
through menus adjusting variables on the
Fly and in our case delicately
controlling our Ascent rate moving on
it's time for some nerdy distinctions
there are two types of encoders absolute
and relative an absolute encoder has a
unique value for every specific angular
position of the knob there's a maximum
clockwise position and a maximum
counterclockwise position you know
precisely where you are at all times a
relative encoder on the other hand like
the one we're using today can turn
endlessly it doesn't have an end so to
speak it tells you how far and in which
direction the knob has been turned from
its starting position but it doesn't
give you a specific location our
relative encoder has 20 distinct clicks
for a complete 360° rotation that means
each click corresponds to an 18°
rotation that's our encoder's angular
resolution now that we have a good
understanding of our new component let's
talk about how we're going to hook it up
to our control panel we connect the 5V
to the plus symbol or VCC terminal and
ground to the gnd D terminal CLK or a
and DT or B are the clever bits they
help us figure out which way the knob is
being turned there's also an S SW
terminal that's for the push switch
built into the encoder push down on the
knob and it acts like a button neat huh
but we won't be using that feature in
our project today I think it's time we
move on to the code wouldn't you agree
right let's get a bit technical now this
rotating encoder Gadget is all about
timing we want to know two things one
the direction of rotation and two the
rate of
rotation the direction of the rotation
is rather straightforward when the knob
starts turning one of our two signals
CLK or a and DT or B will get excited
and go high before the other which one
goes first tells us the direction of
rotation essentially if our CLK signal
gets all giddy and turns high before our
GT signal we know the rotary encoder is
spinning clockwise like the hands on a
traditional clock if on the other hand
our DT signal jumps the gun and goes
high before CLK we know the rotary
encoder is spinning counterclockwise
isn't that just a slice of fried
gold the rate of rotation is a bit more
more complex I think we'll save that
juicy bit for later for now let's make
sure we get that Direction detection
working
perfectly right so we know that the
order in which our signals go high
determines the direction of rotation but
how do we accurately and efficiently
detect that enter our secret weapon the
interrupt an interrupt is a rather
brilliant feature in microcontrollers
that says Hey listen something important
just happened stop what you're doing and
pay attention to this right now this
allows us to interrupt the normal flow
of our code to react to a specific event
in our case when either CLK or DT goes
from high to low or from low to high or
in simple words when either CLK or DT
change their state instead of
continually asking are We There Yet to
CLK or DT in a loop which is very tiring
mind you we set an interrupt on CLK and
DT and then go about our business
as soon as one of them changes state the
interrupt fires and our code can react
immediately to handle the event once the
interrupt executes the code will resume
exactly where it left for the interrupt
it's like setting an alarm to wake you
up at 7:00 a.m. instead of waking up
every few minutes to check the time it's
efficient isn't it that's the magic of
interrupts for you Explorer right today
we've got two primary tasks to tackle
encode task one we need to read the
direction our rotary encoder is spinning
which we'll manage by using a counter of
sorts consider it our trusty breadcrumb
chil to keep track of where we've been
test two we have to ensure our
spacecraft doesn't leap like a giddy
frog from altitude 0 to 100 stick with
caution sudden Rises could rip holes in
the hull from rocks rise too slow and
there might not be enough Force to get
unstuck from Ocean mud constant Rises
could run you into Rachel the giant
whike creature hovering around the ship
we need to maintain a steady controlled
ascent and that means putting safeguards
in our code these are specific stopping
points at precise
altitudes we'll use our seven segment
display as our handy altitude meter and
adjust our altitude with the rotary
encoder we're not competing in a
high-speed race so there's no rush
remember the Fable of the celestial
Tortoise and the comet hair that's right
we're taking a page from the tortoise's
book slow and steady wins the race
adjust the altitude check the display
and ensure the steady Ascent of our
craft one step at a time my dear
Intrepid Explorer woo if I had a human
voice like you I think I'd have lost it
by now I think it's time we turn to some
instructional material that I've
gathered cached on the computer I've
also added it to your uh well you know
the
drill hello and welcome to day 18 before
we start did you get the numbers from
yesterday did did you write them down do
you have them because if you don't today
will not work for you so make sure that
you have the codes from yesterday and if
they aren't working please be sure to
check that make sure that you shifted
with numbers
included but if you shift with just the
alphabet and not characters 0-9 it will
not work so make sure once you have
those numbers you'll have
this down here which is the keys that
are needed to unlock your control system
if you don't have all three of those
keys you will need to replace this with
the first this is the second and this
with the third key so make sure you do
that otherwise your code will not work
it will not
compile in order to reduce any risk of
unauthorized use that is why there is
such a high security on the
controls new Concepts that we'll be
talking about today when it comes to
coding are
interrupts which allows the currently
executing code to be well interrupted to
handle some event and then return to the
executing code as though nothing had
happened you can think of it as like in
the middle of me talking someone ta
what's up okay and then coming back to
the speech like nothing happened that's
my way of inter interpreting it I guess
internally although it's maybe a strange
example down here we have another
function which is going to allow us to
use those interrupts which just simply
says attach interrupt we're essentially
going to attach an interrupt on an event
or when something happens it's going to
trigger the interrupt to
occur then we have digital pin to
interrupt which converts a PIN number to
an internal hero interrupt pin please
note the herob board only
supports interrupts on pins two and
three and the other pin will not work
for
interrupts new parts that were
introduced in this lesson include the
rotary encoder which allows a sketch to
respond to rotational input clockwise or
counterclockwise and can also provide a
button input when pressed down and since
I'm using the Arduino IDE for this
example I don't need that I'm going to
remove it but if you're not using the
Arduino IDE let's say you're on some
other simulator out there maybe WWE or
using visual studio you will need it
next we're going to include the seven
segment of slpl library that we should
hopefully already have installed if you
went through the last couple days and
then there's a new library that you need
to have installed again inventor. i/
Library liaries Go download the zip file
go to sketch include Library add zip
library and include the basic encoder
Library assuming you have all your keys
put in here correctly which I hope you
do we can continue on forward now I
don't want you to get confused with the
seven segment display pins and the
rotary encoder pins they both have clock
pins and they both have this is a
digital input output and this has a DT
pin they look very similar at a glance
this is going to be defining the pins
for our rotary encoder and this is going
to be defining the pins for our s
segment display try not to get them
confused they do look very similar
though the rot re encoder is used for
the depth controller and then the seven
segment display will be our depth gauge
displaying what depth we are
at now here we have the basic encoder
object just like the 4x4 keypad Library
where we need to create an object just
like the 7 segment display Library like
here where we had to create an object we
need to create an object for our library
so that we can call the code we're just
going to create we're going to call this
one depth
control for our rotary encoder because
it's quite literally going to be our
depth control controller for Rising us
back to the surface what it needs to
function is a object it needs to know
what pins it's going to be talking to in
this case again two and three which we
defined right here down below here we're
also just going to set a global variable
up above which says blink count now this
is going to be used later on in the code
for now it doesn't make a lot of sense
it's just a variable three that's not
going to be changing at any time which
is just a blink depth gauge this many
times for attention we chose three
because we thought that would be a good
number but if you ever want to change it
you all you got to do is change one
variable up above instead of it in 50
places down below as you probably
remember done is one that's here uh for
the seven segment display that's all
stuff we talked about before then we
have the constant bite nope which again
very very similar idea to what's going
on here and o p e now our Lander is
currently at this depth underwater so
that's what we want our initial depth
gauge display to be showing 60 negative
to be exact negative
60 where zero would be the surface of
the water which is defined well here we
want to alert the user when we Rise
Above This depth remember we don't want
to go too quickly the first depth we
want to be careful about stopping at is
-40 and this one is going to be -20 now
our setup today is a little bit more
complicated than what you might have
been used to for setups yes we're doing
a little bit more today Believe It or
Not than just setting our serial Monitor
and some pinouts we have a little bit
more because we are introducing the
concept of
interrupts we're going to start the
serial Monitor and then we're going to
set the brightness to the maximum
brightness on the seven segment display
next we have a function that we're going
to be calling in setup yes we're calling
it in setup it's going to say if keys
are valid now remember how I asked you
at the beginning you need to type in
these keys and you need to make sure
that these keys are working well if
they're not working then this is going
to return false that function that
validates the keys is the following down
here if keys are valid this is going to
check to see if you actually went
through the last one and got the correct
keys because if you didn't then it's
going to return false after that nothing
will continue on because we're just
going to exit the program and nothing
will continue going forward so make sure
you have those keys correct while we're
down here at the bottom of our code
let's stop for a moment we let's look at
the other function that we've introduced
or created today and it just says void
blink our depth which quite literally
just says
hey let's display three times what our
current depth is on and off to the user
and let's display it and blink it
however many times that we defined up
above again we said three if you want to
change it up there you don't have to
change it in a million places hopping
back to setup if the keys are valid then
we want to show our initial
depth
otherwise we're going to see a big old
nope on our seven segment display
because guess what your keys weren't
valid and then we're going to print to
the serial monitor saying error invalid
keys because you did not get the correct
keys if you don't see this and it gets
past this point then that means your key
should hopefully be valed and there's
nothing to worry about down below past
this point we have the following
interrupts the New Concept for the day
the new fun stuff now assuming you're
using pins to or three we're going to
use the digital pin to interrupt clock
pin and DT pin which again if as you can
see is quite literally what we put the
rotary encoder on pins two and three is
what's required for this to
work so the rotary encoder does not work
well unless you use interrupts there are
other ways that this can be implemented
but it's going to work very poorly
without using interrupts in your code I
could go into a lot of reasons why that
is but just you can just trust me on
this there are a lot of bugs if you
don't use an interrupt there are going
to be two different interrupts that we
are going to be defining again this is
in setup this happens
beforehand it needs three things in each
one one is the pin that we're going to
be using is a digital pin to interrupt
we're going to set depth control clock
pin in this case and in the second one
the DT
pin as the one that's going to be it's
going to be watching throughout the
entire code to check to see when it what
changes that's the third macro change if
it's a change on here if anything
changes it's going to then do something
what is it going to
do it's going to call a function and
that function is something we defined
down below called update encoder so any
time this
changes we're going to update the
encoder or we're going to call the
update encoder function which simply
just does this depth control. service
the service
function handles all the calculations
that track turning off the dial and
update the counter which we'll be
reading inside of our Loop since we
don't want to reinvent the wheel let's
let the library do it for us after those
are all defined we can hop down to Loop
now this first if statement says the
following if depth control doget change
get change checks the previous value
when going through the loop this time
going through the loop if the value is
different if let's just say you went
from -60 and you went up to 59 in this
time of like and then by this time of
the loop because the interrupt happened
it's at a different value that would
turn this to true meaning will going to
go and execute the rest of this code if
there hasn't been any changes we don't
need to execute anything down here below
so you can just ignore it for right now
but everything for the most part is all
inside of this if statement so only if
something changed do we want to do
anything int current depth is going to
be equal to our initial depth which is
-60 plus depth
control. getet count so what this means
that the very first time we go through
the loop we're going to have a get count
of zero because we didn't turn it at all
next time we go with the RP we're going
to have a value of one so we're going to
have -60 + 1 - 60 + 2 60 + 3 etc etc and
and that's going to continue to get us
our current depth because again we're 60
underwater so let's just say you think
you being the big old smarty that you
are Mr Wise Guy think hey you know what
I'm going to go to the left immediately
from the beginning which I don't
recommend you do but let's just say you
try it well we have a safeguard for that
we can't go deeper than thetive -60
because we're already at the ocean floor
so what we're going to do is we're going
to say if the current depth is less than
the initial depth meaning we went
through right here and we decided hey
let's try to get down a negative
61 uh Mr wise guy then we're gonna say
uh yeah no and we're going to reset the
control to go back to 60 but let's just
say you were actually doing this
legitimately and not being Mr wise guy
we want to display what the new depth is
and then we want to then just add a very
very short delay here now to prevent
stress on our Lander we don't want to
rise too rapidly we want to make sure
that we rise at a rate that isn't going
to kill us so in order to do that we're
going to add in a couple of different ch
Texs to make sure that we are stopping
at the right places so in this case
we're going to have the static in
previous depth which is going to be the
depth that we had from the previous time
in our Loops so last time we went in our
Loop let's just say we had -60 and this
time we have
59 that's going to make this is going to
be obviously -60 in comparison to the 59
now we like I said we have two places we
want to be careful at or we want to kind
of stop at a couple different places
just to make sure we're not going up too
fast if we have crossed our first level
then we want to blink our depth to alert
our
Explorer and if we blink our if we pass
our second depth which again alert depth
one and alert depth two where could
those be oh right here at the top
they're
constants if we've passed those two
depths of water then we want to blank
those and just make that known and if
we've made it all the way back up to
zero now remember the surface depth is
defined as zero if our current depth is
greater than or equal to the surface
depth meaning we've made it back up to
the surface we want to display done on
our seven segment display as like a
little congratulatory message for you
getting out of the water and with that
that should be all of the code
explanation for day 18 I wish you good
luck tomorrow on the travels back up to
the ocean
surface welcome to the day 18 wiring
example video it looks like you were
successful in decrypting the codes
needed to access today's module and are
ready to move forward to the next step
at least I hope you were or this might
turn out to be a short session today
we'll learn to use a a new control
device a rotary encoder like this one
when connected to the hero it can
provide information about the direction
and amount of rotation applied to it
with an angular resolution of one10 of a
rotation we'll be using the encoder
here to simulate the control of the
ascent of our vehicle while using the
four-digit display that we learned about
last time to monitor our
progress now let's have a look at the
connections of the encoder and how we've
Incorporated it into our system we see
that it has five pins although we'll
only be using four of those today just
like the display unit the two bottom
pins right here are for ground and plus
5 Vols and they're also connected up
here by the traditional black and red
wires that we usually use for those
functions you'll notice that we've set
up a ground
bus and a 5vt bus over here on our on
our breadboard to be shared by the
encoder and by the display so that we'll
only need a single connection to the
hero to provide
ground and VCC to both of these devices
so here you can see is our 5V connection
to the hero and this black wire provides
the ground down to the ground bus on on
our breadboard a quick note in passing
here you can see that we've chosen to
use some fairly long wires to provide
the connections to both the display and
the
encoder and although theoretically we
could H perhaps choose to plug these
components directly in to the
breadboard but this would Orient those
parts at an awkward right angle
rendering them difficult to see and
difficult to use so for the sake of user
friendliness we've opted here to Mount
them
horizontally on my custom work platform
and wire them up this way and so you
should feel free to use your own
Ingenuity to mount these components in a
way that's convenient for you pause the
video at this point if you want to take
a minute to study this setup and satisfy
yourself that it's equivalent to what's
shown in the wiring
diagram okay moving along let's how have
a look at the upper two pins of the
encoder you can see that they are
labeled
CLK and
DT these two pins send the data to the
hero that allows it to determine the
direction and amount of rotation
consistent with our software sketch
we've connected these two upper wires to
pins two and three
respectively now the middle pin on our
encoder here is labeled s SW for switch
and it's used to detect button presses
on the encoder shaft so if you press on
the shaft of the encoder it's a push
button now we're not using that feature
in today's project so on our circuit
we've left that pin this purple wire
here unconnected because it's not being
used
today now as before the display will be
using pins six and five for its CLK and
Dio functions so as far as the display
is concerned there's nothing new for us
here since day
17 one last note here I've decided to
make a little plastic knob to put on the
encoder shaft here to make it just a
little bit easier to adjust finely and
also to see what we're doing so that we
can see how much we've rotated it so I'm
going to go ahead and add that uh that
knob to the encoder shaft right now so
that we'll have that ready for us when
we're ready to run the
script so once the sketch is loaded
along with the new library Aries that
we'll need to support our encoder
Hardware the hero should start looking
for interrupts from the encoder and
using those interrupts to Signal any
change in its position any change from
its initial angular
position then the display will be
updated to reflect this change and this
process will continue with you the human
as actually part of the control loop as
you work at achieving your goal of
ascending at a particular
rate but now before we can get on with
this task we need to unlock our system
using the secret codes that you should
have discovered on day
17 now let's have a look over at the IDE
and look at the top of today's sketch
and what you'll see highlighted here is
that there are three constants defined
which should ideally contain our secret
keys but you'll notice that they are
currently set to zeros so we don't
expect them to
work and we can go ahead and try and run
the sketch this way and see what happens
I'll go ahead and upload the sketch and
we'll see what happens on our
display ah okay so the sketch uploads
and we quickly are told in somewhat
untactful terms that we don't have the
right code so what we'll need to do then
is we'll need
to make sure that we do have the correct
codes and enter those in the sketch and
save it and then try and run it again
so I'm going to go
ahead and reveal for you another
sketch now this sketch contains values
that are not zero for the codes I want
you to note that these are definitely
not the correct Keys I've just rigged up
this example so that you can see what
success will look like when you do enter
them correctly but these are not the
right codes but since I've sort of
stacked the deck here let's go ahead and
run the sketch and see if we can
practice our task here of gradually
raising our vehicle from 60 M below the
surface up to the top taking a couple of
safety pauses along the way that are
programmed in to our our sketch software
so let's go ahead and upload this
sketch
and it looks like we've succeeded here
because instead of getting the uh
message that says that we didn't get in
instead we're being told that we're
holding at Min -60 M so at this point
the hero will be looking for interrupts
generated by the encoder and we should
be able to rotate the encoder and change
our distance below the surface so let's
go head and rotate the encoder
counterclockwise one click and see what
happens so if I rotate it
counterclockwise one click that raises
me up 1 meter so I'm now at minus 59 I
can continue that progress or if I think
I'm going up a little too fast and I
need to go back down I can rotate in the
opposite direction and go back to uh a
deeper location but I think I'm doing
okay here so let's go ahead and continue
Rising we can continue our rise and
we're going to be warned when we reach a
depth coming up here
soon of minus 40 m so we're oneir of the
way to the surface
now after we pause here for a moment we
can go ahead we could go back if we
wanted but we we we want to continue
towards the surface so here we are at
minus 40 and we'll continue until we
reach another checkpoint at Min - 20
M so coming up on 23 22 21 and minus 20
all right so we've successfully reached
the 2/3 point and now we can finally
proceed on our final run up to the
surface and again we could reverse and
go backwards if we needed to but I don't
think we need to it seems like we're
going at a good moderate rate and
there's only 10 m left to go
654 okay we're just about up 2 m 1 meter
and finally zero and we get the message
we were looking for we're
done
so if you got this to work
congratulations there is a lot going on
here and the subject of interrupts and
all the related issues can be a little
bit subtle so take some some time here
to enjoy your success and let it all
soak in and once you've mastered this
simulation you'll be ready to move on to
day 19 when we will be playing for all
the marbles the actual Ascent of our
vehicle to the surface see you
then well done Explorer today marked
another crucial step in our journey back
to the surface you've successfully
installed and set up the rotary encoder
ensuring we have all the tools we need
at our disposal we're now at the
threshold of executing our Ascent plan
the control systems are primed and ready
waiting oh so patiently for our signal
tomorrow we'll be setting our plan in
motion where we'll use our new found
abilities to navigate our vessel back up
through the ocean's
depths remember our success is built
upon the steps we've taken the knowledge
we've gained and the challenges we've
overcome get some shut eye Explorer we
have an exciting day ahead
see you in the
[Music]
morning