[Music]
a new week Dawns my courageous
counterpart and it brings a fresh set of
challenges to our undersea sojourn you
may have been enjoying the soothing
Serenity of the deep ocean but it's time
to point our sights towards the surface
now don't get too excited we can't just
jet up there like a dolphin on an energy
drink there are imperative protocols to
be followed as any experienced Explorer
such as yourself knows rising to the
surface too quickly will reduce pressure
that will cause our spaceship to explode
like a shaking soda bottle and I believe
neither of us would be particularly fond
of that outcome first things first power
we need all we can muster so it would be
best to attempt attempt our surface
bound Journey when power generation is
at its peak that means midday to do that
however we need to know when exactly
that is in other words we need to build
a clock there's also the matter of the
encrypted source code provided to us
decrypting it is crucial for all of our
plans to unfold so we have our work cut
out for us this week we need to create a
clock decrypt the code and most
importantly limit the rate of ascent to
prevent us from becoming a bursting
submarine
balloon now let's put our crafting cap
on and get down to business we've got a
spaceship to guide home right then let's
dive into the fascinating world of
timekeeping to craft our clock we'll be
making good use of a Charming little
component in our kit the seven segment
display intrigued well allow me to
explain a seven segment display looks
like this it contains a total of seven l
LEDs a through G in an eight formation
each of these LEDs can be individually
illuminated to make numbers and other
characters simple yet
ingenious let's imagine a digit how
about an eight notice how it's
essentially a formation of different
horizontal and vertical segments now
think about how you can form other
numbers by lighting up or turning off
different combinations of these segments
if we turn off the horizontal segment in
the center for example we turn our eight
into a zero behold the power of a seven
segment display simple yet incredibly
useful it's not my intention to befuddle
you dear Explorer but the digits aren't
the only things a seven segment display
can render with a bit of creativity you
can also display a few letters and
symbols but we'll save those for
later for now find security in
understanding the basic concept of a 7
segment display and prepare to harness
the power of this Nifty little device to
create our clock ready for a bit of
digital Wizardry
Explorer all right Explorer buckle up as
we dive into the wiring part of our
adventure today you'll be relieved to
know it's quite straightforward with
just four wires needed for our seven
segment display module here's how we do
it as always we connect the ground wire
here and positive here these are our
data pins and need to go here on our
digital
pins our friend CLK stands for clock pin
its job is to compile the binary data
streaming from the Dio pin into a bite
one cycle equals one bite our other
friend Dio stands for digital input
output its role is to receive binary
data for the hero board which in turn
determines which segments of our display
are going to be dazzling us with their
lights and which ones will remain in the
dark think of it like a switchboard
operator of the olden days but for datab
bits now an 8 bit binary number provides
just enough digits to control all these
segments and even gives us a few to
spare so there you have it simple isn't
it the magic of making numbers out of
light is within our grasp so let's press
on shall
we now Explorer we're going to make a
bit of a shift from our Hardware chck
and delve into the coding realm for the
day here's where we bring in our secret
weapon a brand new library rest assured
Explorer I'm happy to provide you with a
refresher on Library installation here's
how it goes navigate to the sketch tab
in the top menu then move to include
library and click on add. zip Library
this way we'll get all the resources we
need without having to invent the wheel
all over again it's quite handy isn't it
do be sure to add the library to the top
of our code so we can utilize
it now by creating this new object will
be granted access to the entire library
of the new seven segment functions
remember you must not forget to define
those
pins the one we'll be most interested in
is the set segments function this
function is like the Puppet Master
behind our seven segment display allow
me to break it down for you each of the
seven segments of our display labeled a
through G can be controlled individually
and can combine to form different
characters each segment can either be
turned on meaning it lights up or off
where it remains dark the set segments
function helps us control which segments
light up and which do not it's
essentially taking the re and directing
our display to show specific
characters how does it know what to
display you ask it takes an an array of
segments States as an argument each bit
in the array corresponds to a specific
segment when a bit is one the
corresponding segment lights up when
it's zero the segment remains off in
essence set segments helps us paint
pictures or rather numbers and letters
on our seven segment display by
controlling the light show for each
segment it's pretty cool isn't it you
see each segment labeled from a to G
represents a different LED that we can
command to light up or remain off with
this in mind let's dive into some
examples first up think of which LEDs
we'd need to ignite to display the
number seven if a b and c came to mind
then I'd say you're getting the hang of
this what do you say we step it up a
notch think of which LEDs we'd need to
light up to spell out the letter
A I can see those gears turning by my
calculations it appears you're thinking
a b c e f n n g well dear explorer that
would be
correct now for our final round let's
challenge ourselves a bit can you figure
out which LEDs we'd need to illuminate
to spell out the word done this is a bit
trickier but I know you've got
this remember practice makes perfect
keep playing around with combinations
and soon you'll Master the art of the
seven segment
display it seems to be that time where
we turn to some instructional material
that I have gathered cached on the
computer I've also added this to your
mission resources for future reference
good
luck all right welcome back to day 16 of
the 30 days Lost in Space Adventure
kit in the past we were using LEDs and
buzzers as outputs in order to give us
various forms of information but what do
we do when we need numbers and the
serial console is not available today we
will introduce the four digigit seven
segment display which is mostly for
numbers for example like a clock or
counter or Etc they can think like an
alarm clock looking display but with
some imagination we can also show some
characters like always I'm going to real
quick just remove some of these comments
remove some of these comments and make
it look a little bit easier on the eyes
to look
at boom and boom if you want to follow
along with what those comments are
saying then go ahead and feel free to do
so in your version of the code we
obviously always include the Arduino Doh
include here thing if you're using the
official Arduino IDE you don't have to
worry about it let's delete that just
temporarily however we do have a new
library that we will be using today for
today's video you will need to go to
inventor. io/ libraries and there will
be a library on that folder for the
seven segment display called
tm1637
display. that is the library that will
be required for it and to install it you
want to go to
sketch include Library add. zip library
and you need to click the library that
you downloaded from
adventure.
libraries once you have that downloaded
you can include it and get all the fancy
code and all that other stuff that's
included in that Library all the
shortcuts that we don't want to recreate
because somebody else can already do it
for us and let's be real I'd rather have
somebody else do this then me do it I
think anyone would we can include the
library at the top like this and then we
can Define which pins we're going to be
using for the seven segment
display in my case I'm going to be
putting a clock pin on pin six and the
digital input output pin pin on pin five
next we're going to create an object for
our display by using the library if you
remember back to the keypad library that
we had we had to make a keypad object
and in this case we're going to do the
exact same thing for the S segment
display we need an object so that we can
call all the functions that are included
in this
Library so to do that we're just going
to define a tm1 1637
display and then I'm going to call it
heroor display and you can call it
something else if you wish just be sure
that if you do use that all the other
places that it's referenced as you can
see down below where it's highlighted
make sure you please change those so
that it doesn't obviously break your
code next we're going to go is it say
equals tm13 1637 display and then we
just simply say what pins are on for the
clock and digital output so clock pin
digital input output pin which I def
finded right up here
above now one thing you're probably
going to want to be asking yourself is
how do I turn on certain parts of the
display how do I make it say specific
things for example if I wanted it to say
12:00 where it's one two Z how do I go
about doing that that doesn't make any
sense to me well here let me show you
there are a few different ways you can
make for example 12:00 is an easy one
because the display Library here all
also include some additional functions
for basic numbers but let's just say you
wanted to say something very odd like
the
words done letters d o n e the word done
if you wanted to do something like that
it gets a little bit more confusing
then um what you're going to need is I'm
going to skip this for just a sec what
you need is you need to know how the
seven segment display works on a seven
segment display there are seven segments
essentially seven LEDs that's hence the
name seven segment display each one can
be think thought of as this A B C D E F
G now this layout here is going to be
really useful if you guys want to make
your own custom letters so if you want
for example b and d and f to be turned
on I don't know why you'd want that
maybe it's just like a it doesn't make
any sense it's not a letter U but let's
say you wanted to dis actually here's a
better one let's say you wanted to
display the letter A a capital A all
right you'd want e f a b d and g all to
be set to high and you'd want C to be
turned off essentially set to low that
would make it a capital letter A on the
display one way you can go about doing
this is how we did this down below we
have a constant bite done is equal to
the f following here if we wanted to
display a d for example a lowercase D we
have segment b c d e and g o is
everything except for this very middle
one so I'm going to take a random guess
here before I just look down below that
the only one that's going to be missing
in this one is going to be G and as you
can see I'm exactly right we have a b c
d e and f that's for a capital o or a
zero whatever you want it to be um
represent it can technically be both
then n and then e and you'll notice we
have them in a array separated by the
comma here to se separate this is the
first of the seven segment displays the
first digit the second digit the third
digit and the fourth digit remember we
only have four digits on this seven
segment display only but also we do have
a total of four which is definitely
better than one or two and three so we
can display done by defining which
segments we want to light
up if we go up here because I did skip
this over this is essentially a
short-handed way of saying Hey I want to
turn every single LED on this seven
segment display on this all this does is
this just puts it into a binary format
that just says 1111111 one1 one11 one1
this says everything in this row is a
one everything this row is on everything
this row is on and everything this Ros
on it's a very short-handed way of just
writing ABCDE e FG ABCD e FG ABCD FG
ABCD FG so with that that's just an easy
way that we can turn everything on we
might use it later on in the code so
just as like a little debugging thing so
you can feel free to just ignore that
for now but that's just a
shorthand inside of setup we're going to
need the following done we're going to
want to set the display brightness
between 0 and 7
that's essentially you can think of it
as just only having a few bits to work
with for what we want to set it to and
we're going to set the brightness level
to the maximum which is seven not eight
because remember we start at zero as
programmers so the largest is going to
be allowed is not eight but seven and
we're going to set the brightness to the
maximum amount you'll notice we don't
set certain things as outputs here and
we also didn't do that in the keypad
code we didn't set all eight
pins as outputs and the reason why is
because that is all being handled for us
inside of the library so you don't have
to worry about it here but it don't
worry it is being done just inside of
the library so don't worry about that
after setup completes we can go to Loop
now we're going to show off exactly how
all that works we have a function from
the library called clear do clear so if
we do hero display do clear it's going
to turn everything off then we're going
to delay by a second and this is just
going to show this entire Loops entire
function is just to show hey this seven
segment display is currently up wired up
correctly and working which is all that
we really need to get done for today
after that we're going to go down and
we're going to set all the segments to
on and then what we can do that is we
can set set segments all on and this is
hero display. set segments all on if you
recall we set all we set the bite up
here to Simply say all on now if you
were to set this to instead of all on
done you which you can also do like we
do down below that would simply instead
of turning every single light on it
display exactly what you wanted it to
say which is done so the set segments
simply just takes in an input like that
one in this case we're just turning them
all on and then waiting a second then
we're going to clear it again so it's
simply going to Blink all off off all on
all off then we're going to do the
well-known microwave after a power
outage I'm sure you've seen this before
the power goes off in your house maybe
there's a storm and when the microwave
turns back on the clock is reset and
you're like well it's not 12 at all it's
not even close to it it's just blinking
12 and that's exactly what we're going
to do
here so the DOT show number decimal ex
has an additional parameter to turn on
the colon after the second digit this
works really well for the time
displays in this case that's this right
here and that's the additional parameter
that we're going to use to turn on the
blink digit so we want to do the
following we want to do 4 in IAL z i is
less than four I ++ we simply want so
all this is doing here is this is just
going to do the following it's going to
Loop through it four times that's it
that's all we need to worry about or
three or four times so what we're going
to do is we're going to go through here
we're going to set 12:00 now you'll
notice we didn't have to say one two 0 0
this Library like I said includes
functionality that makes it really easy
to display things like this show number
display ex1 120 is 12:00 and then we
also just want to have this additional
parameter here that says hey let's make
the semicolon on as well wait half a
second turn it off wait half a second
turn it on again off on off on you know
what I mean so we just turn off and on
off and on three times and finally when
we're done with that after three little
blinks we'll hop down below and we'll do
the following we will show the counter
including negative sign for negative
numbers
what this means is that we can also
technically use the display for negative
numbers however note that the maximum
negative number that we can display on
our display is
999 the reason for this is because the
leftmost digit of the display has to be
obviously the negative sign so we do
lose a digit so the maximum we can
display is a little bit less if you go
negative but let's show you how we can
do exactly that we're going to go um
through this Loop and we're going to say
4 in IAL 00 and we want to go all the
way up to 100 so we're going to go from
negative 00 to 100 and we're just going
to start showing that number on the
display in this case we're just going to
take I each time we go through the loop
which will be whatever iteration of the
loop it's going through and we're just
going to show as it goes up and display
that on the display once we're done
we'll delay by a second and then we'll
turn the display
off then we're going to display the
message done which we defined all above
right underneath the all
on and then we're just going to delay by
10 seconds and then repeat our demo
again and that will repeat infinitely
until the end of time with that this
should now be the end of day 16 of the
30 days Adventure kit code
explanations welcome to the day 16
wiring example video today we'll be
exploring a new output device this
four-digit 7 segment LED
display by lighting different segments
of the device we can use it to display
simple representations of numbers and
letters so for example we could use it
to show a time or a countdown or some
other numerical value now Although our
display has 20 eight different LED
segments and that's in addition to the
LEDs for lighting up the colon symbol we
are able to control it using just four
connections four wires this is possible
because our display works by receiving
binary information about which segments
to light and that's provided by the
digital outputs of our hero if we look
at the labeling on our display I have
one display here that's disconnected
that we can look at another display I
have already connected to our hero as
we'll be using it but if we flip it over
and look on the back side we can see
that the four connections the four pins
of the display are
labeled now the uh first two starting
from the bottom are familiar to us we
just simply have the ground connection
and the plus 5V power power supply which
is labeled VCC and those in our circuit
here are connected with a traditional
red for plus 5 Vols and black for ground
and those are connected to the
corresponding pins on our hero the two
remaining connections the upper two here
are going to be new for us and the first
of those up here on the top is labeled
CLK for clock and that's what provides
the heartbeat for the binary
communication protocol that is
established between the hero and our
display and then the second from the top
here labeled Dio is the digital IO
signal that actually carries the data
that is interpreted by the
display now in this case those two pins
the clock and the Dio are connected to
our hero on pins six and five
respectively and you can follow that you
can see that the uppermost pin here the
clock is connected by this brown wire to
pin six which is one of the digital
outputs of the hero and this white wire
connects the Dio to pin five on the hero
so those should agree with what we have
in our sketch and should lead for this
to function as we want it to now as we
switch our attention over to the
programming it might be rather tedious
for us to manually have to handc code in
our sketch the binary configuration of
all 28 LEDs for every number or letter
that we might want to
display but fortunately we can make use
of the handy Library routines that have
been provided for use on our display in
order to Output certain pre-programmed
sequences of commonly used characters in
our sketch today we'll illustrate how
some of these work and how easy they are
to
access now before running our sketch
let's just quickly review what our
sketches designed to do and what we
expect to see when it runs so that we'll
be able to ver ver ify that it's it's
working properly after setup we enter
loop as usual and the first thing that
Loop does is clear the display and wait
for one second so we'll watch for that
next Loop manually sets all the segments
to on using the binary code that we've
provided in our sketch this will give us
a quick visual indication that all the
LEDs are functioning then after one more
second the sketch actually pulls a
little joke on us by showing the
blinking 12:00 which along with the
colon we've always uh been used to
seeing say in our kitchen when the
microwave of and loses power so after
having that little laugh on us blinking
12:00 four times the sketch moves on to
display both positive and negative
integer numbers and it does that by
running through a count up from minus
100 all the way up to positive 100 now
after that sequence of number displays
is finished the display is cleared and
for the finale we again use a manual
segment binary coding that we've
provided in our sketch to display a
crude representation of the word done d
o n e this this whole sequence of events
of course will all repeat indefinitely
at least until the hero is turned off or
reset but uh to give us a little
breather here we've inserted a 10c delay
at the end of loop so that it will pause
for that long before then going ahead
and repeating the demo
sequence okay uh let's go ahead then and
run the sketch and see if it acts as
we've expected it to so going to the IDE
we'll go ahead and upload the sketch and
then start watching the display here to
see uh what kinds of things it
displays upload has
begun upload is complete and there is
segments on there's blinking
12:00 somebody please reset the
microwave and here we are counting
through negative numbers you can see
that we use one of the uh uh segments to
the left to uh display the minus sign
now we're counting up through positive
numbers up to 100 we're done and there
is the final signal so that's uh pretty
successful that's just about all that we
wanted to accomplish in today's project
once you've got a pretty good grasp of
what's Happening Here then we'll be
ready to tackle our next coding
challenge that will come up in the next
day's project so good luck and we will
see you
then well done my tenacious Explorer
we've come a long way today our seven
segment display is now alive and
Illuminating it's quite literally the
beacon of your progress your deafness in
handling the display truly proves your
skill and dedication however as we gaze
at our journey ahead a challenge looms
our control systems are under lock and
key with a passcode tucked away under
layers of encryption cracking this
passcode is our task for tomorrow it's
not going to be easy but who said space
exploration was a walk in the park rest
up my friend tomorrow we step into the
enigmatic world of encryption be ready
to wield your intellect against this
intricate puzzle you've got this good
night Explorer see you on the other
[Music]
side