[Music]
job well done Explorer I never doubted
you for a
moment
hey everybody my name's Alex you might
know me from the code explanations
throughout the course I want to
congratulate you on making it through
the 30-day loss in space challenge but
your journey does not end here luckily
there's still more for you to do if you
so want to I would say if anything your
journey has just begun so to give you a
quick history on the 30 days loss in
space challenge this originally was a
project that started back in 2020 with
just me and I had a little astronaut
suit in a green screen in Austin's
apartment back when we were very very
first Young starting um this inventor
company all right so welcome back again
this is day 25 uh and like every fifth
day of the 30-day challenge we're going
to give you guys that creative Outlet
once again and we got a lot of feedback
from you guys both critical and good and
we took that feedback and then came up
with a revision back in 2021 and we had
our wonderful man Greg Greg who you
might recognize was a person in this
version of the videos who did all the
wiring but in the previous version he
was kind of the ASD the entire character
cast for the entire thing um back in
2021 and he is a a man the myth The
Legend and I love him to death and thank
you so much Greg um I appreciate you I
am a pre-recorded AI who will attempt to
give you all the information necessary
for your success this version we had
obviously the code improvements and the
wiring obviously was Greg's Focus but
then we also got a little bit more
energy with ASD so I want to give uh
credit to the actor for that because she
did a wonderful wonderful job playing in
the 30 days loss and space so after
about 3 years of a total amount of
feedback we were able to get and over a
100,000 members in our Facebook
Community now that we've grown we have
grown to an insane number and it's it's
wonderful um we finally came up with the
revision that you guys have just
completed now so we hope you've enjoyed
and uh obviously we look forward to
seeing you guys hopefully joining us for
what's next so what is next well first
of all if you haven't joined the
Facebook group join it like I said we
have over I mean it was 100,000 Members
Plus at the time of recording the video
there's a chance when you join now it'll
be 500,000 plus I have no idea what it's
going to be when you join some large
amount of number uh probably cuz we're
just growing like crazy and we love it
in there we have weekly events we have
giveaways so maybe a chance to win
something don't get your hopes up too
much but uh we do have some weekly
events that we like to do live streams
Etc we try to put on we have a lot of
technical help so if you are building
out something on your own and want a
little bit of help the m numbers in
there are always super easy and
wonderful to help and they that's one of
the greatest things in the whole world
project inspiration I've seen a lot of
people post their INSP in their projects
that have inspired them so uh if you are
looking for project inspiration for
yourself it's a good place to go check
and if you want something more advanced
I highly recommend checking out we have
another adventure kit after this the
adventure kit 2 or um if you're looking
into the world of sensors and uh
interacting with the outside world I
recommend a 37 in1 sensor kit or if you
want something that works really well
with your hero board right now just a
quick popon device maybe a slightly more
beginner you can check out our Shields
kit finally if you want some more
projects with the parts that you already
have we do have an invent you catalog
with a repo of a lot of our old weekly
live streams that we're starting to
build up the first of which will all be
using parts that you already have
available in your adventure kit so if
you're looking for some additional
projects I highly recommend checking
that out cuz that should have a ton of
extra projects uh for you to build up if
you would like so with that I want to
thank you guys for once again completing
the 30 days loss and space challenge for
those of you who have been with us for
the entire 3 years I've seen some of
people in the comments that are going
through another time just because they
want to see what's changed thank you
guys thank you all so very much for
being here for those three years um and
for those of you that are new welcome to
the community of course join the
Facebook group and we're glad to have
you thank you once again and we hope to
see you guys around
peace
[Music]